<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The antinomians Christ confovnded, and the Lords Christ exalted. In which is contained a briefe confutation of Dr. Crispe and Mr Lancaster. Also, a combat with the Antinomians Christ in his den, his arraignment; and the fainting soule built upon the true rocke, against which the gates of hell shall not prevaile, Mat. 6.18. Imprimatur James Cranford.</title>
            <author>Bakewell, Thomas, b. 1618 or 19.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 229 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77730</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B527</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E17_16</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11989</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859177</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859177</idno>
            <idno type="VID">111244</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77730)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 111244)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 3:E17[16])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The antinomians Christ confovnded, and the Lords Christ exalted. In which is contained a briefe confutation of Dr. Crispe and Mr Lancaster. Also, a combat with the Antinomians Christ in his den, his arraignment; and the fainting soule built upon the true rocke, against which the gates of hell shall not prevaile, Mat. 6.18. Imprimatur James Cranford.</title>
                  <author>Bakewell, Thomas, b. 1618 or 19.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 67, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Thomas Bankes, and are to be sold at his shop in Black-fryers on the top of Bridewell-staires,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1644.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed: Thomas Bakewell.</note>
                  <note>A reply to "Christ alone exalted" by Tobias Crisp and "Vindiciæ Evangelii" by Robert Lancaster.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Nouemb. 19.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Crisp, Tobias, 1600-1643. --  Christ alone exalted --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Lancaster, Robert, b. 1603 or 4. --  Vindicæ Evangelii --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Antinomianism --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:111244:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE ANTINOMIANS CHRIST CONFOVNDED, AND THE LORDS CHRIST EXALTED.</p>
            <p>In which is contained a briefe confutation of Dr. CRISPE and Mr LANCASTER. Alſo, a Combat with the <hi>Antinomians</hi> Chriſt in his Den, his arraignment; and the fainting Soule built upon the true rocke, <hi>againſt which the gates of hell ſhall not prevaile,</hi> Mat. 6.18.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprimatur</hi> James Cranford.</p>
            <q>
               <p>If any man will doe his will, he ſhall know the Doctrine, whether it be of God, or whether I speake of my ſelfe,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>John. 7.17.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Becauſe they received not the love of the truth, that they might be ſaved; for this cauſe God ſhall ſend them ſtrong deluſions, that they ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve lies, that they all may be damned who beleeve not the Truth, but take pleaſure in unrighteouſneſſe,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Theſ. 2.10, 11, 12.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Many ſhall come in my name, ſaying, I am Chriſt, and ſhall deceive many; then if any ſhall ſay unto you, loe, here is Chriſt, or there, beleeve it not; for there ſhall ariſe falſe Chriſts, and falſe Prophets, and ſhall ſhew great ſignes and wonders, inſomuch, that if it were poſſible, they ſhall deceive the very elect; wherefore if they ſay unto you, behold he is in the deſert, goe not forth; behold he is in the ſecret chambers, beleeve it not,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Mat. 24.5.23, 24, 26.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> printed for <hi>Thomas Bankes,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in <hi>Black-fryers</hi> on the top of <hi>Bridewell-ſtaires.</hi> 1644.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:111244:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:111244:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IN my first Book againſt the Antinomians, I gave thee a ſhort view of their Errours in five generall heads, with a briefe and plaine anſwer to them; and having laid open to the world their ug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, in their owne native colours, they began to be aſhamed to owne them, and like common Whores, who ſeek to eſcape away and to leave their, bastards upon the pariſh, ſo theſe men when ſhame followed their errours; they ſought to eſcape away from them, by denying of them; but witneſſes came in ſo faſt both from their Sermons and from their books, and from conference with them, that they could not ſo rid their bands of them; yet being unable to maintaine them all, away they fled to Gods decrees for a protection, and for maintainance of the firſt of thoſe, which is this, <hi>That a man is juſtified actually in the ſight of God, before and without faith and calling;</hi> this being immediately begottten by them, their care was more for it then for the reſt, which they did but rake out of <hi>Eatons</hi> dunghill, and their labour there was but to raiſe up children to their eldeſt brother; but as for this which was of their owne begetting, was very deare unto them, and they ſay that they will be torne in pieces with wild horſes before that they will leave it; hereupon they ride poſt to Gods decrees to fetch from thence ſome maintainance for it, but a faithfull meſſenger was ſent after them to try their power in that laſt place of refuge, and in his purſuit of them, he found their Chriſt exalted above all by <hi>Criſpe</hi> and <hi>Lancaſter</hi> but he being a burden too heavy for them, downe fell he and fled to his den; but the faithfull meſſenger being ſent, and having commiſſion from the Lords Chriſt, followed him to his den, and there he was ſet upon by ſeaven of his chiefeſt ſouldiers, and a true relation of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat, and of his victory over them, and how he ſore wounded them with uncurable wounds, and brought away their Chriſt to his tryall; and
<pb facs="tcp:111244:3"/>after a true diſcovery of him, comparing him to the Lords Chriſt, he was ſound not worthy to be trusted in for ſalvation, but rather to be condemned for high treaſon and blasphemy, and the Lords Chriſt alone exalted alove all for ever; <hi>therefore try all things, and hold faſt that which is good, 1</hi> Theſ. <hi>5.21. and be no more carried about with divers and ſtrange doctrines; for it is a good thing that the heart be eſtabliſhed with grace,</hi> Heb. <hi>13.9. as ye have therefore received Chriſt Jeſus the Lord, ſo walke ye in him, rooted and built up in him, and eſtabliſhed in the faith, as ye have been taught abounding therein with thankſgiving; and beware leaſt any man ſpoyle you through Philoſophy and vaine deceit,</hi> Col. <hi>2.6, 7, 8. and that thou mayeſt be built upon the true rocke Jeſus Chriſt, and ſtand like Mount</hi> Zion <hi>unmovable,</hi> Pſal. <hi>125.1.</hi> Mat. <hi>16.18.7.24. 1</hi> Cor. <hi>3.12.</hi> I have laid here before thee the grounds of true Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Religion by way of Question and anſwer; read it with an honeſt and ſincere endeavour to be ſetled in the truth, and I doubt not but thou ſhalt ſee that the spirit of God will lead thee into all truth, <hi>John 16.13.</hi> and the Comforter, which is the holy Ghoſt, whomthe Father will ſend in the name of Chriſt, he will teach you all things, and bring all things to your remembrance, <hi>John 14.26.</hi> therefore I pray thee read it, and if thoureceive any benefit, give God the praiſe, and me remember in thy prayers; and ſo I commend thee to God, whom I know is able to keep that which I have committed unto him, <hi>2 Tim. 1.12.</hi> and ſo I reſt, unleſſe I be againe provoked by theſe troublers of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but the meane time I remaine</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in all Chriſtian duties, THOMAS BAKEWELL.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:111244:3"/>
            <head>THE ANTINOMIANS CHRIST Confounded, and the LORDS CHRIST EXALTED.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Borrowed thoſe fourteen Sermons of Doctor <hi>Crisps</hi> in which the Antinomians ſay, Chriſt alone is exalted, but I found ſo many errou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s in it, that it would have been endleſſe to have anſwered them all diſtinctly one after another; and having the Booke but two dayes in my hand therfore I thought fit to gather the ſubſtance of them to theſe c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aine heads; firſt thoſe errours a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout redemption: ſecondly thoſe about poſſeſſion; thirdly thoſe about juſtification; fourthly, thoſe about the new Covenont: fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ly thoſe about a holy converſation; with a briefe and plain anſwer to them, to ſhew how Chriſt alone by them is exalted. Firſt, their errours about re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, the Doctor ſaith, we may collect the univerſality of redemption of all and every particular man in the world, <hi>pag.</hi> 296. this he illuſtrates by this compariſon ſaying, That the Lord pardons ſinners as when a King by proclamation ſends forth a generall pardon for all Theeves without excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; ſo that if a man be but a Theefe it is enough the pardon is ſent him as a deed of gift univerſally exhibited <hi>pag.</hi> 162 163. but ſaith the Lord to <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, how ſhall I pardon thee for this? thy children have forſaken me, and ſworn by them that are no gods they commit adultery and aſſemble themſelvesn <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>roops to the harlots houſes,</hi> Jer. 5.7. <hi>obey his voice, provoke him not, for he will not pardon your tranſgreſſions for my name is in him.</hi> Exod. 23.21. ſome ſinners ſhall never be purged from their filthineſſe. <hi>Ez<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k.</hi> 24.13. he that blaſphemes againſt the holy Ghoſt ſhall never be forgiven <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.31. then is his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for all ſinners, he cals none but thoſe that are heavy laden with their ſins <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.28. and excludes thoſe that cry Lord Lord and will not do the will of his Father, <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l.</hi> 7.21, 22. and caſts him into utter darkneſſe that comes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his wedding garment <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.12.13. he is the author of eternall ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; but to whom? <hi>anſw.</hi> to them that obey him. <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.9. then did Chriſt redeem every particular man in the world? if this be ſo, then the Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:111244:4"/>was much to blame to ſay, he gave his life a ranſome for many if he redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med all. <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.18. and if this were ſo, why did not Chriſt ſay, that he laid downe his life as well for Goats as for his Sheep, <hi>John</hi> 10.11. and Chriſt ſaith I pray not for the world, but for thoſe that thou haſt given me: then would not Chriſt vouchſafe to pray for all and would he ſpill his blood for all? <hi>John</hi> 17.9. ſo then I conclude that Chriſt was fore-ordained for you who doe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve in God that raiſed him from the dead, and gave him glory that your faith and hope might be in God, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.20 21.</p>
            <p>Let this ſuffice becauſe Maſter <hi>Lancaster</hi> was ſo ſhamed when he was very briefs to ſoea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e againſt the Arminians; and I demanded whether it was not Arminianiſme to ſay that Chriſt redeemed every particular man in the world, he anſwered, yes; then I ſhewed him this of the Doctor, at which he was ſo blank that he had not one word to ſay, but that the Printer had miſtooke it, ſo much for the firſt head of errouts.</p>
            <p>The ſecond head of errours is about poſſeſſion, the Doctor ſaith that Chriſt is actually delivered unto a man before ever his blind eyes be opened or they come out of priſon, or before they have any gracious qualifications whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, <hi>pag.</hi> 154. I demanded of Maſter <hi>Lancaster</hi> how this could be, for he that is in Chriſt is a new creature, 2 <hi>Cor</hi> 5.17. and further, I ſaid that the huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of Chriſt is in heaven, and the eſſence of Chriſt fils all places and is in all creatures as well as in men, <hi>for in him they live, move, and have their being,</hi> Acts 17.28. then ſaid I this cannot be underſtood, that Chriſt ſhould enter perſonally and take poſſeſſion, but graciouſly when he worketh grace in the ſoule, and ſtampeth his owne Image upon it; to this he replied, that it was a gracicus poſſeſſion and yet before any qualification; I replied againe, that it was nonſenſe to ſay that Chriſt enters into the ſoule, and before that he wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth grace when as the infuſion of grace is the entance of Chriſt into the ſoul; he ſaid, this grace was the love and favour of God; to this I ſaid, the words are, he hath a poſſeſſion of Chriſt, which cannot be without faith, this he gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; but ſaith he, Chriſt may enter into us and have a poſſeſſion before any gracious qualification; I having drawne out his full meaning, anſwered, that it was horrible blaſphemy to ſay that Chriſt lives graciouſly in that ſoule where the devill reignes as lord and king, or to ſay that Chriſt dwels in a cage of uncleane and filthy luſts, or to ſay that he is an idle ſpirit doing nothing, or an underling to the devill, or to ſay that the divell is the Lord and rules a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the living members of Chriſt; yet ſaith <hi>Crispe,</hi> art thou rebellious, an enemy, ungodly, a harlot, nay, art thou worſe then enmity it ſelfe, Chriſt came for thee; marke, while thou art thus, and no better then thus, before thou art any better, <hi>pag.</hi> 67. whoſoever thou art in this Congregation, ſuppoſe a drunkard, a whoremonger, a ſwearer, a blaſphemer, a perſecutor, a mad-man,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:111244:4"/>in iniquity, yet couldeſt thou but come to Ieſus Chriſt, I ſay onely come; marke he mean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s a carnall comming for ſaith he it is no matter though there he no alteration in the world in thee I ſay, at that mſtant although t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ou be thus vile as can be imagined, doe but come to Chriſt and he is untrue if he caſt thee out, <hi>pag.</hi> 314. and he ſaith, ſuch a perſon as this without any change or alteration in the world, it his heart doe but ſay, I would have Chriſt, all that ſinfulneſſe though continued in, is no barre in the world to hinder this man from claiming his portion in Chriſt <hi>pag.</hi> 320. here this ſeducer makes no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions of any ſinne, no not the blaſphemy againſt the holy Ghoſt, which ſhall never be forgiven, <hi>Mat</hi> 12.31. for, ſaith he, in a carnall manner, thoſe that receive him were made the ſonnes of God, <hi>John</hi> 1.12. but he, like the divell, leaves out To them that beleeve on his name; yea further he ſaith, to take Chriſt upon his generall tender is as good ſecurity as any in the world; yea, moſt blaſphemouſly he ſaith, it is as good as any God can make him, <hi>page</hi> 163. but doth not the Apoſtle ſay, <hi>give all diligence to make your calling and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>tion ſure,</hi> 2 Pet. 1.10 but the Doctor ſaith God hath ſo paſſed himſelſo over to man as that he hath no more command over himſelf then the creature can have power over him, <hi>pag.</hi> 277 now follow his reaſons, why chriſt is made over to men before they have any gracious qualifications.</p>
            <p>Firſt, ſaith he, Chriſt is the beginning of all things, then as the builder of the houſe doth not come after the houſe is begun to be builded, but is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to lay the firſt ſtone thereof. I anſw, and grant, that Chriſt was from all eternity; but this is not our queſtion, whether Chriſt was before men, or whether man be before his houſe; but here is the queſtion, whether a man will poſſeſſe his houſe before he build it, or whether Chriſt will dwell in the ſonle before any qualification; then by his owne argument, as man fits his houſe before he poſſeſſe it, ſo Chriſt firs the ſoule before himſelfe will dwell in it: his ſecond reaſon, Chriſt is the head of the body, and all the ſenſes are in the head therefore ſaith he, men doe not ſee before they have a head, &amp;c. I anſ. will it follow, becauſe Chriſt is the head to his Church that are members of his body therefore he is ſo to them before they are any part of his Church or members of his body. Thirdly, he ſaith, Chriſt is the life, and all that come to the Father come by him, <hi>John</hi> 14.2.6. and <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>I live, yet not I, but chriſt livith in me,</hi> Gal. 2.20. hence he concludes, that a man cannot live before that life is breathed into him; I anſ. if this ſeducer had read the whole verſe he might have found faith where he found chriſt, for mark, <hi>I live by ſaith of the Sonne of God.</hi> Gal. 2.20. Chriſt dwels in your heart by faith, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.17. then chriſt doth not come and dwell in the ſoule before faith. <hi>We have acceſſe by ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th into this grace wherein we ſtand,</hi> Rom. 4.2. <hi>and God ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h given repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance unto life,</hi> Acts 11.18. Here Maſter <hi>Lancaster</hi> affirmed that faith and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:111244:5"/>were both the ſame thing and that he knew no graces of the ſpirit, but teſtimonies of Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s love, and (it we call theſe) graces, then ſaith he, our riches money, and cloathes, and victuals are graces alſo; I might here ſhew that theſe are cemporall and not ſpirituall; and againe, ſome that are ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all are common and ſome are ſpeciall, your heavenly Father will give his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to them that aske him, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.13. this is not to be underſtood the third perſon, but his gifts or good things, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7, 11. deſire ſpirituall gifts, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.1. abound in this grace alſo (after he hath named other graces) as faith, utterance knowledge and love, 2 <hi>cor.</hi> 8.7. ſtirre up the gift of God that is in thee, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.6. and to ſay that repentance and faith are the ſame thing, cannot be for repentance con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſts much of godly ſorrow, beway ling the breach of the firſt Cevenant and our miſery that came upon it. but faith is fixed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> fulfilling the ſecond Covenant for us, beleeving and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying the happineſſe that came upon it; but more of this anon: for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent it may ſuffice that here you ſee qualifications before that Chriſt doe actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally poſſeſſe the ſoule.</p>
            <p>But he replies ſaying, that it is a ſordid and a groſſe conceit in the hearts of ſome perſons, to thinke that there cannot be humiliation for ſinne, except perions be brought to di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>paire, <hi>page</hi> 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>4. <hi>I anſ.</hi> a man cannot he humbled for thoſe ſins in himſelfe, unleſſe he dupaire of all hope in himſelfe; <hi>thou ſardeſt not there is no hope, thou haſi found the life of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne hand, therefore thou waſt not gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed</hi> Iſa. 57.10. he that doth not deny himſelfe and forſake all and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Chriſt, is unworthy of him he cannot be his Diſciple. <hi>Luke</hi> 14 26.27. but ſaith he although a man be nt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erly undone before Chriſt come into the ſoule; yet ſaith he, the man is not ſenſible of it till Chriſt be actually given and come into the ſoule to work that ſenſibleneſſe, <hi>pag.</hi> 201. <hi>I anſ.</hi> the worſt of men have been ſenſible of their undone condition altrough Chriſt never came graciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly into their ſoules witneſſe <hi>Cain, Pharath, Saul</hi> and <hi>Iudas.</hi> all theſe by the law ſaw their undone condition for by the law is the knowledge of ſin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3, 20. but he replyes, that a though the law be a light like the Sun, yet it gives no eyes to ſee: <hi>I anſ.</hi> that it did give thoſe reprobates a ſight of their undone condition, and as an Inſtrument in the hand of Chriſt it may give a greater light, ſo the law may convert the ſoul, make wiſe the ſimple, rejoyce the heart and enlighten the eves. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19. but howſoever the law may ſhew a wicked man his ſinfull condition, becauſe ſome remainders of it are left ſtill in nature; <hi>The Gentiles by nature doe the things contained in the law which ſhe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es the work of the law that is written in their hearts,</hi> Rom. 2.14 15. this may ſuffice to ſhew that a man may be ſenſible of his owne undone condition, before that Chriſt comes graciouſly into the ſoule; but further, when Chriſt comes into the ſoule, he comforts thoſe that mourne, he gives joy for mourning, and the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:111244:5"/>garment of praiſe for the ſpirit of heavineſſe, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61.2, 3. then ſure they doe not mourne before they are ſenſible wherefore; all this ſhewes that Chriſt works ſome qualification before he come to poſſeſſe the ſoule; ſaith Chriſt to <hi>Paul, I ſend thee to open their eyes, and to turne them from darkneſſe to light, from the power of Satan to God;</hi> marke, <hi>that they may receive forgiveneſſe of ſinnes, and inheritance among all them that are ſanctified by faith in me,</hi> Acts 26.18. here you ſee that forgiveneſſe of ſins which is a great part of juſtification, is not the firſt work in the ſoule? but much preparation of common grace which goes before, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>peciall grace is the entrance of Chriſt as I ſaid before, which brings me to the third head of errours which are abont juſtification.</p>
            <p>He ſaith, that Chriſt enters actually and juſtifies a perſon before any graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous qualification be wrought in them, <hi>page</hi> 155. he ſaith, they are juſtified while they are ungodly, <hi>page</hi> 136. <hi>I anſ.</hi> this is horrible blaſphemy, for it makes God an unrighteous Judge, to pronounee a ſinner juſt before that he is juſt ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by inherent righteouſneſſe, or by that imputed righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, whereby alone he may be juſt: but ſaith <hi>Crispe.</hi> faith is a work and the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>to him that worketh not, but beleeveth on him that justifieth the ungodly,</hi> Rom. 4.5. it ſeems he takes this for a carnall beleeving, ſuch as may be in the ungodly, remaining ſuch, for he leaves out <hi>his faith is connted for righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> but it is of faith that it may be of grace <hi>Ro.</hi> 4.16. <hi>we have acceſſe by faith into this grace wherin we ſtand, being justified by faith we have peace with God.</hi> Rom. 5.1, 2. yet as faith is a work, we renounce it in poynt of juſtification, as a poore lame Cripple cannot get his living by working, yet he can receive an almes with his lame hand that ſhall maintaine him as well and better then working, but ſaith <hi>Criſpe,</hi> Chriſt is put upon a finner before they have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hand to put him on, as a Phyſitian uſeth to doe with an unruly Patient who ſhuts his teeth againſt his phyſick, then he forceth his mouth open and powres it cowne his throat, ſo ſaith he, the Lord forceth Chriſt upon us <hi>page</hi> 150 151. and he ſaith, Chriſt gets upon us as we get up to break a horſe, ſo ſaith he, was <hi>Ephraim</hi> yoaked and fettered: <hi>I anſ.</hi> this is nothing but the plowing and brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king that is by the law, before that Chriſt enters graciouſly to juſtifie us; but if this breaking be before, this confounds his former tenet, that Chriſt enters before any qualification or any prep. ration be made for him ſo then the Lord plowes up the ſoule to make it fit for the ſeed of ſaving or juſtifying faith; for ſaith Chriſt, I ſtand at the doore and knock, he doth not enter till the will be changed and made willing to receive him; I doe dot ſay as the Arminians doe that Chriſt waits till we will, but till he himſelfe hath changed our hearts, I ſay till then he will not enter graciouſly, nay, if his own<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Spouſe be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing unwilling he will depart, <hi>cant.</hi> 5.2. but ſaith <hi>Criſpc,</hi> Chriſt may come to us graciouſly as well as we may caſta garment upon a dejected body, having no hand to receive it,</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:111244:6"/>
            <p> I anſwer, the compariſon is not equall for all although this dejected bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy have no hand, yet he hath life and a heart to receive that mercy thankefully, <hi>but we are dead in treſpaſſes and ſinnes,</hi> Epheſians 2.1. then how can a dead ſtone receive any thing that hath neither heart nor hand, life nor motion to doe it? ſo then, faith muſt be wronght in the ſoule to receive chrut firſt, before that we can receive him to juſtifie us; <hi>we have acceſſe by faith unto this grace wherein we stand.</hi> Romans 5.2. <hi>with the heart man beleeveth unto righteouſneſſe,</hi> Rom. 10.17. the Gentiles attained to this righteouſneſſe becauſe they ſought it by faith, <hi>but</hi> Iſrael <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> not attained to this righteouſneſſe, wherefore? becauſe they ſaught it not by faith,</hi> Rom. 9.31, 32. ſo then, we muſt have faith before and by which we muſt receive the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, for before faith was wrought in the ſoule there was none righteous no not one, that every mouth may be ſtopped, and all the world may be guilty before God; marke, I doe not ſay guilty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore men, but before God, for all have ſinned; till the righteouſneſſe of God be imputed to us which is by faith of Jeſus Chriſt unto all and upon all that beleeve, for there is no difference, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.10, 19 22, 23. but the Doctor would faine be juſtified without faith, againſt the cleere light of the Scripture, and cannot tell how to make it appeare, therefore he almoſt yeelds; but yet he hath one ſtarting hole more, ſaying, although faith juſtifies yet ſaith he, this faith is confined in the perſon of Chriſt and not in us: I anſ. with <hi>Paul,</hi> even we have beleeved in Ieſus Chriſt, that we might be juſtified by the faith of Chriſt, that the promiſe by faith of Ieſus Chriſt might be given to them that beleeve, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.16.3.22. but when he comes to make his matter good at the end of the ſeventh Sermon, he unawares confounds all that he hath ſaid both before and after, in this point; for ſaith he, we are all like <hi>Jeremiah</hi> in the dungeon when Chriſt comes into us, and he is like <hi>Ebedmelike</hi> who let downe the ropes of his faith and puls us out; ſo then, here you ſee <hi>Ebed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melike</hi> did not goe downe to <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> but caſt downe the ropes by which he drew him up to him, ſo our <hi>Ebedmelike</hi> Ieſus Chriſt doth not firſt come into our filthy ſoules while the divell rules and reignes but firſt he caſts downe the grace of faith into our ſoules, and by that faith he drawes us out of our ſinfull condition, ſo then our <hi>Ebedmelike</hi> did not goe downe and get upon our backs as we goe to breake a horſe, and as a Phyſician powres downe the Phyſicke in ſpite of the Patient, but firſt reacheth downe the ropes of faith, and preſently we are made willing to come out, for by this rope of faith Chriſt and us are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> together; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>either doth the rope of faith manifeſt to our ſelves nor others, So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it was caſt into the dungeon, and as hard to be knowne as juſtification it ſelf; for <hi>Jerenmiah</hi> had the ropes, yet he ſaw them not till he came out neither did he ſee <hi>Ebedmelike</hi> till he was out, yet he truſted by that rope to get on
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:111244:6"/>although he ſaw it not; ſo <hi>Job, although thou hideſt thy face from me and hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt me for thine enemy yet</hi> ſaith he, <hi>though he ſlay me yet I will truſt in him.</hi> Job 13.15.24. and ſaith the Prophet, <hi>he that walketh in darkneſſe and ſees no light, let him truſt in the name of the Lord, and ſtay upon his God,</hi> Iſa. 50.10. but both <hi>Crispe</hi> and <hi>Lancaster</hi> affirmes, that faith acts no longer then it manifeſts it ſelfe, for ſay they, faith is the evidence of things not ſeene, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.1. but I had rather take <hi>Pauls</hi> word then both theirs, who ſaith <hi>we walk by faith and not by ſight,</hi> 2 Cor. 5, 7. ſight is reſerved till faith is ended, then we ſhall ſee Chriſt face to face, 1 <hi>cor.</hi> 13.12. but doth faith evidence all things to them that they beleeve? hence I gather, that their faith is the evidence of hell, for they beleeve it if they be not Atheiſts and it is not ſeene, and there is a ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtardly faith very full of confidence, as the true borne faith of a Chriſtian, like the ſtony ground full of joy, which failes them when they have moſt need of it; but ſaith <hi>Crispe,</hi> faith acted by beleevers is full of ſinne, but if this man had knowne what true faith had been, he would rather have ſaid, that faith acted by beleevers is full of Chriſt, and a weak faith may take hold on Chriſt and be juſtified, as well as a weak eye could look on the brazen Serpent and be healed <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.14.15. ſo then God juſtifies by pronouncing us juſt, and chriſt juſtifies by his merits purchaſing it for us and Faith juſtifies by applying thoſe merits of chriſt to our ſelves, and works alone declare it, <hi>Iames</hi> 2.21.25. or thus as faith acts by receiving or taking chriſt and his righteouſneſſe, ſo it ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifies, and as it works by love, and acts all other graces ſo it ſanctifies and manifeſts it ſelfe to our ſelves and others; this they deny, ſaving, that act which juſtifies is manifeſtation.</p>
            <p>The fourth head of errours is about the new covenant: In his ſixth Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon he ſaith, chriſt hath made a covenant without any conditions on our part, <hi>page</hi> 124. and he ſaith, in way of condition of the covenant we muſt doe nothing <hi>page</hi> 128. he ſayth, it is probable that chriſt was the firſt covenant, <hi>page</hi> 124. but was chriſt the firſt covenant? then how came the firſt to be faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? will they tax chriſt with faults, which was without ſinne? and againe, how came the ſecond covenant better then the firſt and built upon better pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes? <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.8, 9. is any thing better then chriſt, and any promiſes better then thoſe that are made in him? me thinks men ſhould be aſhamed and tremble to preach and print ſuch helliſh blaſphemy; ſo then the firſt cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant was made to <hi>Adam</hi> &amp; all mankind in him by nature, and the ſecond cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant was made to chriſt, both God and man, and to all the elect as they are in him by grace, now as no man was bound to the conditions of the firſt cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant nor guilty of the breach of it till they have a being in him by nature, ſo none of the elect are bound to the conditions of the ſecond covenant, till they have a being in him by grace; but both <hi>Criſpe</hi> and <hi>Lancaster</hi> affirme, that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:111244:7"/>this new Covenant is without conditions on our part: <hi>I anſw.</hi> in this they ſhew themſelves to be ſonnes of <hi>Belial,</hi> that ſay of God and Chriſt his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed, <hi>let us break heir bonds aſunder and caſt their cords from us,</hi> Pſ. 2.2.3. but this is to about <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> new Covenant, and quite overthrowes the Goſpell of Jeſus Chriſt, I do admire h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y are not aſhamed to call it a Covenant when as they deny the conditions of it: I muſt confeſſe <hi>Lamaſter</hi> was aſhamed to call it a Covenant and would have it to be only a legacy, or a will or teſtament, but this we grant as wel as he that we have nothing but what was freely given us of God by will or teſtament, but this teſtament and the new covenant may ſtand well together; for the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> had nothing but what he received from God as a free gift, yet that did not nullifie the conditions of the covenant, and make it voyd to him and his poſterity; ſo the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> receiving grace without meaſure, <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.34. <hi>and out of his fulneſſe we receive grace for grace,</hi> Iohn 1.16. yet all this hinders not the conditions of the new covenant, and as we were all bound to the conditions of the firſt covenant ſo that when <hi>Adam</hi> fell we all fell in him and as ſoon as we had our being in nature, we took that guilt upon us for the breach of that covenant, ſo as ſoon as we are in the ſtate of grace in the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> then we are bound to thoſe conditions of the new covenant, which is not another diſtinct and contrary to the firſt cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, but Chriſt hath fulfilled that firſt covenant which we had broke, and now our conditions are made more eaſie for us to keep; the firſt was made with a weake man therefore he ſoone fell, and we in him, but the ſecond was made with him that was both God and man therefore he was able to keep the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of it, and not onely ſo, but to give us power to keep our conditions al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, which are theſe chiefly, firſt, repentance and all thoſe graces that may humble us for that great ſinne in breaking the firſt covenant, and then faith to beleeve that Chriſt hath fulfilled for me; in particular therefore, the tenor of the Goſpell runs thus, <hi>Paul</hi> teſtified both to Jewes and Gentiles repentance towards God that was for the breach of the firſt covenant, and faith in the Lord Jeſus chriſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.20. <hi>repent and beleeve the Goſpell,</hi> Mark. 1.15. there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Apoſtles were ſent to preach repentance and remiſſion of ſinnes, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.47. and when men did repent of their ſinnes, then ſaith chriſt, <hi>onely beleeve, Mark</hi> 5.36. and when the Jaylor repented they ſayd, <hi>if thou beleeve in the Lord Jeſus thou ſhalt be ſaved.</hi> Acts 16.31. <hi>whoſoever beleeveth in chriſt ſhall not periſh but have everlaſting life</hi> Ioh. 3.15. and Chriſt blamed the Prieſts and Elders becauſe they beleeved not in him though the publicans and harlots beleeved on him yet ſayth he <hi>ye repented not when ye had ſeen it, that ye might beleeve in him,</hi> Mat. 21.31. ſo then, we muſt repent for our breach of the firſt covenant, and grieve and mourne for thoſe ſinnes for which our Saviour ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and then we muſt beleeve that he hath fully ſatisfied the law for us upon
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:111244:7"/>theſe conditions we enter into the new covenant; yet I grant that faith is the gift of God, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.8. and that Chriſt is exalted to be a Prince and a Saviour to give repentance to <hi>Iſrael</hi> and remiſſion of ſinnes, <hi>Act.</hi> 5.31. yet all this hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders not, but theſe are conditions on our part in the new covenant, they are given as a Legacy by will or teſtarment, to be imployed as conditions of the new covenant: but ſaith <hi>Crispe,</hi> it is called an everlaſting covenant, then ſaith he, if it ſtood on theſe conditions, we ſhould daily faile and make it fruſtrate, as <hi>Adam</hi> did, and then it could not be everlaſting, except ſaith he man were ſo confirmed in righteouſneſſe, that he could never faile on his part; but this is not true, for God made an everlaſting covenant with <hi>Abraham,</hi> Gen. 17. although he had his failing as well as other men; and whereas he faith, we ſhould make it fruſtrate as <hi>Adam</hi> did. <hi>I anſw.</hi> that we upon the conditions of faith and repentance cannot totally nor finally fall away, for in this new covenant of grace we doe not performe them in our owne ſtrength, but in the power of chriſt, and he hath put his ſpirit in us to cauſe us to walke in his ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes and his feare in our hearts, that we ſhall not depart from him, <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.4. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.27. now thoſe that want theſe inward abilities, may be in the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward covenant as it was made with <hi>Abraham</hi> and his ſeed, but if they have not faith &amp; repentance they fruſtrate the covenant of grace, for he that belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth not ſhall be damned, <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.16. <hi>except ye repent ye ſhall periſh,</hi> Lu. 13.3.5. But ſaith <hi>Crispe,</hi> theſe things are by way of conſequence, after we are in co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with God, as fruits and effects of that covenant; but ſaith he, they are not true by way of antecedence, <hi>page</hi> 124, this <hi>Lancaster</hi> affirmed alſo. <hi>I anſ.</hi> man will not enter into covenant till he is agreed, for there can be no cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant without agreement of the parties that are to enter into that covenant, therefore the Lord ſends forth his Ambaſſadours to beſeech us to be reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20. now mans heart is not fit to enter into covenant till he repent for the breach of the old covenant, and beleeve that Chriſt hath fulfilled the new for him in particular, therefore of neceſſity repentance and faith are ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedents and concomitants of this new covenant of grace; for what fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip hath righteouſneſſe with unrighteouſneſſe? what concord hath Chriſt with <hi>Belial?</hi> but God hath ſaid in this new covenant, <hi>I will be their God, and they ſhall be my people,</hi> 2 Cor. 6.14, 15, 16, 17, 18. but ſaith <hi>Crispe,</hi> becauſe God gives all, therefore nothing is required of man. <hi>I anſw.</hi> the legacy or teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is wholly of God, but the covenant that followes is not ſo and theſe may be cleerly diſtinguiſhed, although not divided; in the legacy, ſaith the Lord. <hi>I will have mercy on her that had not obtained mercy;</hi> then followes the covenant. <hi>I will ſay to them that were not my people thou art my people and they ſhall ſay thou art my God,</hi> Hoſ. 2.23. thus God in his great mercy puts his feare in our hearts, and writes his lawes within us, to enable us to enter into cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:111244:8"/>with him, and then he takes us into covenant with him, and wherever you find this covenant mentioned between God and his people, you ſhall al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes find theſe gracious qualifications going before ſee <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.25, 26, 27. then the covenant in the 28 ver. and ſo in all the reſt; but ſaith <hi>Crispe</hi> and <hi>Lancaster</hi> both, we may doe ſome duties and ſervice to God, but not as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of the covenant; but he hath no proofe to confirme it; ſo then, when God takes us for his his people in covenant with him we againe take the Lord to be our God and as God binds himſelfe to us to doe us all manner of good, ſo we againe bind our ſelves to God to doe him all manner of ſervice, duty and obedience; as when a Maſter makes a covenant with his Prentice, he binds himſelfe to find him all manner of neceſſaries, and the Prentice binds himſelfe to doe him all manner of ſervice; and wherefore ſerve our Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments but as ſeales of this covenant that is betwixt God and us and as often as we receive them we doe (as it were) renew our bond of obedience unto him: The Doctor ſaith when men are juſtified, then God hath made a cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with them; but ſaith he, this was done before man could doe any thing, before the children had done either good or evill; it was ſaid Jacob <hi>have I lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and</hi> Eſau <hi>have I hated. I anſw.</hi> that was not ſpoken before, but a long time after by <hi>Malachy</hi> the Prophet. <hi>Romans</hi> 9.13. but there is no ſuch thing in Geneſis, ſo that all which was ſpoken before the children were borne was this, that the elder ſhould ſerve the younger. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.11, 12. and for that other place, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.5. ſee his wicked inference, becauſe it is ſaid, to him that worketh not, therefore faith is not required to juſtifie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, when as the words are cleer, to him that worketh not, his faith is counted for righteouſneſſe, but ſaith he, becauſe it is not of works therfore it is not of faith, when as the words are expreſſe that it is of faith and not of works; and becauſe the ungodly are ſaid to be juſtified therefore he would gather hence that they are juſtified and yet remaine ungodly; but if he were not blind he might read his ſaith and he that beleeveth on him that juſtifieth the ungodly; now al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the ungodly here be named as a man may be ſaid to marry a Widow doth ſhe remaine ſo after marriage? ſo if Chriſt juſtifie the ungodly, muſt they needs remaine ſo after they are uſtified? no here is faith as ſoone as u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification: but faith the Doctor if theſe things muſt be as conditions then Chriſt juſtifies the godly and not the ungodly: <hi>I anſw.</hi> No: but the act of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification makes them juſt and therefore godly: but ſaith <hi>Crispe,</hi> the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant is nothing elſe but Gods love to man: <hi>I anſw.</hi> it is to covenant at all till man cloſe with God by faith; yet we grant that God is the Author of all this, and therefore all the glory is to be given to him and not to us at all, for he both makes us capable and then of his infinite goodneſſe takes us into cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with him; but ſaith the Doctor, faith is not a condition, becauſe it is a
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:111244:8"/>work of ours; it is true, the works of the law are excluded, but faith is a work of grace; again, faith as a work doth not juſtifie, but as an inſtrument, not for the worthineſſe of it, as a grace, but in regard of the worthineſſe of the object; for as the hand feedeth not the body as being food it ſelfe, but as it receiveth and miniſtreth food unto it, hereby it is ſuſtained; ſo faith juſtifieth by recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and applying Chriſt to be our righteouſneſſe and life; but the Doctor denies that Chriſt ſhould juſtifie by faith, becauſe ſaith he, if Chriſt ſhould doe ſo, then he muſt have a partner to juſtifie us: <hi>I anſw:</hi> it would be counted a folly to ſay, when a poore man puts out his hand to take an almes, that the man did not of himſelfe give that almes; but ſayth <hi>Crispe,</hi> he had a partner, and becauſe <hi>David</hi> had a ſling and a ſtone to kill <hi>Goliah,</hi> therefore he had a partner to doe it; this is the Doctors free grace, that will not admit of faith wrought in us by Chriſt, to receive and apply his righteouſneſſe unto us, this ſayth he, is to make himſelfe a partner with Chriſt, but if a common Whore doe but beleeve that Chriſt hath done this with ſuch a faith as may ſtand with her whoriſh heart, then ſhee is juſtified, becauſe ſhee did not repent and then beleeve that ſhee ſhould be juſtified, but ſtill remaining a Whore with a baſtardly faith beleeves that ſhee is juſtified, this is that hereticks devinity; and old <hi>Lancaster</hi> affirmes the ſame; <hi>but we receive the promiſe of the spirit by faith, even we beleeve in Jeſus Chriſt that we may be justified by faith,</hi> Gal. 2.16. being juſtified by faith we have peace with God through Jeſus Chriſt, by whom we have acceſſe by faith into this grace wherein we ſtand, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1, 2. it is of faith that it may be of grace, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.16. <hi>let him take hold of my ſtrength and ſo make peace with me,</hi> Iſa. 27.5. and Chriſt dwels in our heart by faith, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.17. <hi>by grace ye are ſaved through faith,</hi> Eph. 2.8. <hi>we are kept by the power of God through faith unto ſalvation,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.5.</p>
            <p>Thus Chriſt will neither take poſſeſſion of us to dwell in us nor juſtifie us, nor adopt us nor enter into covenant with us, nor ſave us without faith; then what curſed ſeducers are theſe that would make faith but an idle ſpectator, to ſee all thoſe great things that are, as they ſay, all done before and without faith: thus the devils inſtruments doe not onely ſeeke to aboliſh the law of God, but the Goſpell alſo, by taking away the conditions of the new covenant, ſo to make it void to their eternall ruine of body and ſoule for ever.</p>
            <p>The ſift head of errours is about a holy converſation; he ſaith, that Chriſt did not only put an end to the curſe, but alſo to the life of the law, <hi>page</hi> 237. thus that law that ſhould guide us in al holy obedience to the will of God, this ſaith he, Chriſt hath put an end to the very life of it; but muſt we beleeve this ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducer or the Prophet of God which ſayth, <hi>all his commandements are ſure, they ſtand faſt for ever and ever,</hi> Pſal. 111.7, 8. <hi>thy word is ſetled for ever in heaven,</hi> Pſ. 219.89. <hi>the Angels doe his commandements, hearkning to the voyc,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:111244:9"/>of is word,</hi> Pſ. 103.20. then hath Chriſt put an end to the life of the law, which is for Saints and Angels for ever; what a helliſh tenet is this: and ſaith <hi>Criſpe,</hi> a blameleſſe walking according to Gods owne law eſtabliſhed is a fruit of ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance and a cauſe of mans not ſubmitting to the righteouſneſſe of God <hi>pag.</hi> 206. what curſed blaſphemy is this! is not the law holy, and the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment holy, juſt and good? <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.12. is not the Lord righteous in all his wayes? <hi>Pſ.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>5.17. when <hi>Zacharias</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth</hi> walked in all the commandements and ordinances of the Lord blameleſſe, the text ſayth, then they were both righteous before God. <hi>Luke</hi> 1.6. but were they both righteous before God, and yet not ſubmit to the righteouſneſſe of God; the Goſpell reveales the righteouſneſſe of God <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.17. and doth not the law the ſame? <hi>Paul</hi> had not knowne ſinne but by the law, then did the law that ſhewed ſin, make him ignorant of righteouſneſſe, and did his obedience to the law make him diſobedient to Gods righteouſneſſe? what blaſphemy is this to affirme that Gods law ſhould make a man deſpiſe Gods righteouſneſſe: againe ſayth this Doctor, righteouſneſſe puts a man away from Chriſt, and yet he ſaith that no ſinfulneſſe in the world can debarre them from him, yet righteouſneſſe may debarre them from him, <hi>page</hi> 249. upon theſe things I tarried ſo long with Mr. <hi>Lancaster</hi> that he was almoſt ſpent, and his wife cryed out, that her husband was almoſt ſpent, and ſo my friend and I left him; and were it not for his wife who looked very big about the middle, I would have a third bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell with him, in which I am confident he would yeeld upon quarter, for I perceived his munition was almoſt ſpent now, for his argument that righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe hinders a man from Chriſt, when as no ſin in the world can doe it, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be the ſinne againſt the holy Ghoſt, which ſhall never be forgiven, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.32. this might convince him, if he were not mad upon his errour, but he confidently affirmed, that Chriſt excepts againſt no ſin whatſoever, but only righteouſneſſe ſaying <hi>I came not to call the righteous but ſinners to repentance,</hi> Mat. 9.13. to which I replyed that Chriſt came as well to call thoſe that are righteous in their owne eyes to repentance, as thoſe that are prophane and wicked livers, for <hi>Paul</hi> was ſuch a one, <hi>as touching the righteouſneſſe which is of the law blameleſſe,</hi> Phil. 3.6. yet Chriſt called him to repentance; then ſayd I, why ſhould any ſuch be excluded from the call of Chriſt, but this did ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage M. <hi>Lancaster</hi> that he was ſcarce himſelf and yet he would hold and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, that Chriſt came to call none but prophane ſinners as whores and drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards; but if this be ſo, then all that come to the ordinances before converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on have barred themſelves from Chriſt, unleſſe they returne to their former prophaneneſſe Chriſt will never call them to repentance, and by <hi>Lancasters</hi> judgement, Chriſt will call more to repentance from the bandy ſtewes at <hi>Venus</hi> then from our aſſemblies; for if any come to the aſſemblies, or conforme to any ordinance before he be truly called, this man hath barred himſelfe out of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:111244:9"/>heaven; O moſt horrid and helliſh doctrine! can they ſhew me an example from all their helliſh meetings, that ever God called three thouſand, as he did at one Sermon <hi>Acts</hi> 2.41. againe, if this were true, the Goſpell would damne us all, for we all have an outward conformity before we have any inward truth and ſincerity, thus <hi>Lancaster</hi> acts the devils part, to keep all before conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing any means that they may be called; now you ſhall ſee what he ſayth for thoſe whores and drunkards whom he ſayth are juſtified; ſayth the Doctor and <hi>Lancaster,</hi> all this ſanctification of life is not a jot the way of a juſtified perſon to heaven, <hi>page</hi> 69. thus you ſee that neither juſtified nor unjuſtified perſons muſt uſe any meanes to come to heaven; but <hi>Lancaſter</hi> ſaid, there is a twofold ſanctification, one in the perſon of Chriſt, that ſaith he is neceſſary, becauſe Chriſt is the way, the truth, and the life; but then there is another ſanctification in us; but ſayth he, that is not a jot the way to heaven. <hi>I anſw.</hi> and grant that the holineſſe in the perſon of Chriſt is the cauſe of our comming to heaven; but here I am not ſpeaking of the cauſes but of the way to heaven, now that way ſhall be called the way of holineſſe, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 35.8. for no uncleane thing ſhall enter into heaven. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.27. <hi>the pure in heart ſhall ſee God, but without holineſſe no man ſhall ſee the Lord,</hi> Mat. 5. Heb. 12.14. I may may cleere it thus; ſuppoſe I have a friend come to <hi>London,</hi> and I aske him the cauſe of his comming, he will anſwer me, ſuch a buſineſſe was the cauſe of it; then I demand by what way he came, then he will tell me, ſuch a road way; ſo the holineſſe of Chriſt is the cauſe of our comming to heaven, but our ſanctification is the way thither; but he replyed and ſhewed me many Authors, whom he ſayd, was of hir judgement, that Infants may go to heaven without inherent righteouſneſſe; for ſayth he, they are not capable of faith nor knowledge, much leſſe of practice, therefore ſayth he, uncleane ones may goe to heaven; and further he ſayd, all thoſe places I mentioned was to be underſtood of men of yeers, and he ſayd, faith came by hearing the word, but let any rationall man judge, whether this place be not rather to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood that the word is the ordinary means to work faith &amp; holineſſe in men of yeeres, and for Infants or Ideots, or thoſe people that have not the word God is able to worke it in them by his ſpirit, for certainly it muſt be wrought in them before they come to heaven, for without faith none can pleaſe God, <hi>he that beleeveth not ſhall be damned, for the wrath of God abideth on him,</hi> John 3.18.36. and another text I may retort back upon him, which he mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned without any wit or reaſon, ſaying, he that will not worke, neither let him eat, but ſayth he muſt none eat but men of yeers then what ſhall Infants and aged people doe; I know not how he applyed it to any ſenſe, but I may retort it backe, thus ſhall none have faith and holineſſe but men of yeers, then what will become of Infants, ſeeing none without holineſſe ſhall come to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. But is this their free grace to damne all the world but onely a few men of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:111244:10"/>yeeres that have the word preached unto them, but for any other, they muſt either goe to heaven without holineſſe, or elſe not at all; but there being but one way to heaven, God is able where ordinary meanes are not to ſupply the want of it by his ſpirit; thus when he hath made the way to heaven ſo broad that ſome may walk in it thither without holineſſe: then he comes to anſwer an objection, ſaying, <hi>ſtraite is the gate and narrow is the way that leadeth unto life, Mat.</hi> 7.13, 14. to this the Doctor anſwereth poynt blank againſt our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt, ſaying, the way to heaven is the moſt eaſie to walk in of any in the world, and they are falſe Prophets that ſay you muſt walk ſo preciſely, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling you that the gate is ſtraite and the way narrow that leadeth unto life, for ſaith he, there is aboundance of largeneſſe and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bbe-roome in Chriſt the way, ſo then, this ſaith he, is the meaning of Chriſt, that the way to heaven hath not that latitude in it, but is too ſtrait to containe man and his righteouſneſſe, ſo that all a mans righteouſneſſe muſt be cut off that walks in that way, ſee the end of the fifth Sermon; and therefore he blames men when ſinne abounds for faſting and praying to ſuppreſſe it; and when wrath breaks in upon us he ſaith, we muſt not think that this is the way to deliver us, this ſaith he, is the way to make our righteouſneſſe an Idoll, <hi>page</hi> 109.110. he ſaith, there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to be gotten that we have not already if we be in Chriſt, <hi>page</hi> 219. <hi>I anſ.</hi> We have a right to all things, but the prayer of faith muſt fetch them out for our uſe, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36.37. he ſaith, we muſt doe theſe for the good of others and not for our ſelves, to praiſe God and to ſerve our generation <hi>page</hi> 230. for ſaith the Doctor, the way to heaven is full of muſick and flagons of wine, as to a drunkard, who delights alwayes in tipling: but <hi>I anſw.</hi> that we muſt goe through much tribulation to heaven, <hi>Acts</hi> 14.22. this is part of the narrowneſſe of it, we muſt take up our croſſe and follow Chriſt; but the Doctor ſayth, all teares ſhall be wiped from our eyes while we are here, and that God hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away every thing by Chriſt, that can diſturb our peace and comfort, <hi>page</hi> 242, 243, 244. he ſaith, a man reconciled, God cannot tax him for any ſin, <hi>page</hi> 306. he ſayth, all occaſion of quarrell or controverſie between God and thee is abſolutely taken away, <hi>page</hi> 303. he ſayth, God doth never puniſh a belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver for ſinne committed <hi>page</hi> 25. the reaſon, becauſe the travaile of Chriſt gave the Father ſuch ſatisfaction, that he ſaith, it did the heart of God good to ſee his Sonne tormented for us, he ſaw it and was ſatisfied, <hi>page</hi> 46 47. <hi>I anſ.</hi> This is helliſh blaſphemy, for when our ſinnes were upon him, yet then ſayth the Lord, <hi>Thou art my beloved Sonne in whom I am well pleaſed;</hi> and in his agony he ſent an Angell to comfort him, and that place in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.11. is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of Chriſt himſelfe, he ſaw the travaile of his ſoule and was ſatisfied, not that the Father ſaw it and rejoyced to ſee it; the Doctor ſaith, although the free man of Chriſt fall into the ſame ſins that a reprobate doth, yet although
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:111244:10"/>the law ſay to the reprobate thou art damned for this, yet the law cannot ſay one word to the free man of Chriſt, ſo that he may eſteem of the curſe of th law, as an Engliſh man may eſteem of the lawes of <hi>Spain, page</hi> 189. but Chriſt threatned the damnation of hell &amp; other judgments to the Churches of <hi>Aſia, Mat.</hi> 23.33. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.3. chap. the Doctor ſaith, if a beleever fall into ſome ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous ſinne, as murder and adultery, as <hi>David</hi> did yet he may looke upon Chriſt and in Chriſt, at that very time he commits them he may ſee a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of his ſinnes and reconciliation by Chriſt and his part in Chriſt; nay, further he ſaith, a beleever cannot commit thoſe ſinnes that may give occaſion of ſuſpicion, that if he come to Chriſt he ſhould caſt him out, <hi>page</hi> 330 331. this alſo puzzeled <hi>Lancaster</hi> that he came off baſely; I demanded of him, if a beleever (having a cleere apprehenſion of God in Chriſt) can commit thoſe foule ſinnes; he anſwered 10; now this was well for ſaith <hi>Joſeph, how can I doe this great wickedneſſe and ſinne againſt God,</hi> Gen. 39.9. th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n I demanded of him whether <hi>David</hi> or <hi>Peter</hi> or any other in the act of thoſe foule ſins did ſee God in Chriſt to their comfort; he anſwered, whether they did or no, yet a man may doe it; I anſwered it was a flat contradiction, for he ſayd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if they had that cleere apprehenſion, they neither could nor durſt thus ſinne, and now he ſayd in the act of thoſe ſinnes they may have this cleere ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion, then he diſcerned himſelfe to be almoſt foyled and ſhuffled it thus ſaying, although he had not that cleere light in the entrance into that ſinne, yet God may ſhew it him before the act is over; I told him that he was yet upon his contradiction, but then he ſhuffled it off thus, ſaying that he ought to ſee his part in Chriſt at that inſtant, and nor to adde unbelieſe to his other ſinne; I anſwered he ought not to ſinne at all; but we are not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>king what he ought to doe but what he can doe at ſuch a time; but he could not find a ſtarting hole ready, therefore he ſaid the Doctors meaning was, that at ſuch a time they ought to ſee their part in Chriſt; yet I ſuppoſe all this will hardly cleere the Doctor; for I ſuppoſe in the act of ſuch a foule ſinne, that a man ought not to lay his foule ſingers on Chriſt, for ſome are too forward to cloſe with Chriſt; but faith the Lord your hands are full of blood, goe waſh you, make you cleane, and then he ſaith <hi>come, now let us reaſon to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, Iſa.</hi> 1.15 16 18. I need not to ſpeak how <hi>David</hi> being hurried in temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and ſaw it not till <hi>Nathan</hi> ſaid <hi>thou art the man;</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> was in a paſſion and not himſelfe, when he came to himſelfe he wept; and the Prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall, when he came to himſelfe he went home; but theſe were ſo farre from comfort in the time of thoſe ſinnes that I ſuppoſe they rather never ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained their former joy but they had ſome grudging of them to their dying day: ſayth <hi>David, ake away blood guiltineſſe, O God;</hi> and in his old age ſayth he, <hi>pardon the ſinnes of my youth,</hi> Pſal. 25.7.11. ſo then, I rather thinke
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:111244:11"/>he that can ſinne thus, and think he may then cloſe with Chriſt, that as yet he never had any true faith in Chriſt: but the Doctor ſayth, beleevers need not to be threatned, for ſayth the Doctor, the ſonne ſayd to the father, <hi>thy people ſhall be a willing people in the day of thy power,</hi> Pſ. 110. which is flat againſt the text, and that the Sonne brought down the Father to his articles, which over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwes the tenour of the Goſpell, which ſayth, the Father ſent the Son, and the Son came to do the Fathers buſineſſe and to finiſh his work and not to do his own will, then he ſaith, Chriſt is the way for whore and drunkards in his fourth Sermon: <hi>I anſw.</hi> Chriſt is the way for imitation to walk as he walked, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.6. we ranſt learne of him, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.28. <hi>Jah.</hi> 13.15. we muſt follow his ſteps, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.21. and Chriſt is our Counſellou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9.6. <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.8. now he that thus walketh imitating Chriſt and obeying his counſell, this man walkes in Chriſt, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.6. becauſe the word of Chriſt rules in their heart, 3.16. but for any to ſay, they walk in Chriſt, and yet for at naught his counſell, he will laugh at their deſtraction, and mock when their feare commeth, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.24. theſe men are led away with their Inſts, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.14. now ſuch the Lord may juſtly give up to their own hearts Iuſts, to walk in their own counſels, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 81.12 but <hi>bleſſed is the man that walketh not in the counſell of the ungodly,</hi> Pſal. 1.1. but freely yeelds himſelfe unto Chriſt to be guided by his counſell, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward brought unto his glory, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.34.</p>
            <p>So much in anſwer to Doctor <hi>Crisp</hi> and Mr. <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> in which their Chriſt is exalted above all, now followes the combat in the Den.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>A combat with the Antinomians Chriſt in his Den.</head>
            <p>WHen we ſeriouſly conſider poore heathen people who naturally ſeeke after a God to worſhip and cannot find the true God nor rightly how to worſhip him, then we bewaile the great loſſe that all mankind had by the fall of <hi>Adam,</hi> wherein we loſt the knowledge of the true God and rightly how to worſhip him: but what ſhall we ſay when <hi>Iſrael</hi> is a long time without the true God. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.3. or at leaſtwiſe halt between two opinions as not being reſolved whether the Lord or <hi>Baal</hi> be the true God, till the Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe by fire from heaven decide the controverſie, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 18.21.38, 39. but to the aſtoniſhment of all people that lay it to heart; when Chriſtians under the glorious Sunſhine of the Goſpell ſhall diſpute and contend about the true Chriſt, this is moſt abominable to all that heare it: it is true, when Chriſt came in the fleſh he came to his owne, and his owne received him not. <hi>Job.</hi> 1.11. and ſome ſayd he was a good man, and ſome ſaid nay, but he deceiveth the people; ſome ſayd this is the Chriſt, others ſayd, ſhall Chriſt come out of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:111244:11"/>
               <hi>And the Prieſts a ked him are thou the Chriſt the ſonne of the bleſſed? and Ieſus ſaid, I am</hi> Mar 14.61, 62. <hi>And</hi> Mattha <hi>ſaid, I beleeve that thou art Chr ſt the ſon of God which ſhould come into the world,</hi> John 11.27. Yet the Jews had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed, <hi>that if any man did corſeſſe that he was Chriſt, het ſhould be put out of the Sinagogue,</hi> Job. 9.22. The Centurion ſaid, <hi>truly this is the ſen of God; But o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers mocking, ſaid, let Chriſt the King of Iſ rael d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſcend from the croſſe that wee may ſee and believe,</hi> Mar. 15.32.39.</p>
            <p>Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> now he is declared to be the ſon of God with power, <hi>according to the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret of holineſſe by the reſurrection from the dead.</hi> Rom. 1.4. Apollos <hi>mightily convinced the Iews, ſhe wing by the Scriptures that Ieſus was Chriſt,</hi> Acts 18.28. <hi>And</hi> Paul <hi>was preſſed in ſpirit, and teſtified that Ieſus was Chriſt,</hi> verſ. 5. <hi>And he encreaſed in ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ength, &amp; confounded the Iews. proving that this is very Chriſt,</hi> Acts 9.22. Then what a miſerable ſhame it were for ſuch taught Chriſtians to diſpute whether this be the true Chriſt? Yet thus it wil be according as bee him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe propheſied long <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gone, ſaying, <hi>many ſhall come in my name, ſaying, I am Chriſt, and ſhall deceive many,</hi> Math. 24.5.</p>
            <p>The time when theſe falſe Chriſts ſhall ariſe, is when you ſhall heare of wars, famines, and peſtilences, and earth-quakes in divers places: and when Gods people are hated, afflicted, and killed for the name of Chriſt, and betray and hate one another, and iniquity ſhall abound, and the love of many ſhall wax cold, and the abhomination of deſolation ſtanding in the holy place. Theſe things have been all fulfilled ſince theſe troubles began, and now the Devill hath beene very buſie to ſow the tares of hereſies; But ſaith the true Chriſt, <hi>If any ſhall ſay unto you, loe here is Chriſt, or there, beleeve at not; For there ſhall ariſe falſe Chriſts and falſe Prophets and ſhall ſhew greas ſignes &amp; wonders, inſomuch that if it were poſſible, they would deceive the very elect,</hi> verſ. 23, 24. Now obſerve the ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtneſſe of Chriſt to prevent theſe ſubtile deceivers, that the Elect can hardly eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape their hands ſaying, <hi>Behold I have told you before: wherefore if they ſhall ſay unto you, behold he is in the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſart, goe not forth, behold he is in the ſecret cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, beleeve it not,</hi> verſ. 25.26. Why muſt we not goe into their ſecret cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, nor come at their private meetings? Becauſe <hi>of this ſort are they which creep into houſes, and lead captive ſilly women laden with their luſts, who are ever lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and never able to come to the knowledge of the truth,</hi> 2 Tim. 3.6, 7. Now the true Chriſt commeth openly. Ieſus anſwered him, I ſpeake openly to the world, <hi>I ever taught in the Sinagogues and in the Temple whither the lewes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes reſort, and in ſecret have I ſaid nothing,</hi> John 18.20. <hi>As the lightning commeth out of the Eaſt, and ſhmeth even unto the Weſt, ſo ſhall the comming of the ſon of man be,</hi> Math: 24.27.</p>
            <p>But before I proceed to make a further diſcovery of theſe falſe Chriſts, give me leave to declare the tydings of that faithfull meſlenger who was ſent to try the <hi>Antinomians</hi> power (in their laſt place of refuge) being ſent forth by the true Chriſt to maintaine againſt them that none are actually juſtified, ſanctified, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:111244:12"/>and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pted, and in the love and favour of God from all eternity: and ſo be having a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of protection from his Maſter, <hi>that the gates of hell ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> him,</hi> Math. 16. <hi>And when he went through fire and water <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> with him, that it ſhould mather burne nor drown him,</hi> Iſa 45.1, 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> it of victory, went on boldly to his den, and in this den hee was ſer upon, and now if you will attend, you ſhall heare the true relation of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in that den.</p>
            <p>Firſt, there ſteps up a ſervant of the Antinominns Chriſt, ſaying, that hee was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> before the act of beleeving; his firſt argument was this, Inſants <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, but Infants are juſtified. Therefore ſaith hee, ſome are juſtified <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> leeve; now his reaſon why Infants do not beleeve, is <hi>becauſe that ſaith commeth by hearing,</hi> Romans the 10. verſ. 17. <hi>And how ſhall they h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a Preacher,</hi> verſ. 14. The meſſenger of the true Chriſt anſwers, Firſt, that although preaching be the ordinary meanes to beget faith in men of veares, &amp; in that place where it is truly preached: yet God hath not ſo bound himſelfe to that meanes, that among thoſe people that have not the word preached, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not have ſaith wrought in them ſome other way extraordinary, where that ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary way is not to be had, as alſo that they which live in a place where the word is truly preached; If they be not able by ſome defect or other to heare it, the meſſenger of the true Chriſt is not ſo cruel, as to judge all the world to be dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, which have not the word truly preached unto them, and alſo all children that dye before they be able to heare it. But the true Chriſt ſaith, <hi>he that belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth not, ſhall be damned,</hi> Mar. 16.16. Then of neceſſity all muſt have it, <hi>or elſe he ſhal not ſee life but the wrath of God abideth on him,</hi> Joh. 3.36. Then conſider the cruelty of this cenſure, and be informed <hi>that the ſpirit of God is able to help all our infirmities.</hi> Rom. 8.26. But is this the honour you give to the ſpirit of Chriſt, to thinke him unable to worke ſaith without the helpe of your owne abilities? A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>game, faith may grow and act where we ſee it not, as well as trees grow in the winter downwards in the root, and we ſee it not. Againe, Infants are ſanctified, which flows from faith, <hi>Ier.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Luke</hi> 1.15. Againe, Infants are entered into the Covenant with God by vertue of their Fathers faith: for God ingaged him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be the God of their Father and his ſeed: into which Covenant they are infolded; And if they have but the ſeeds of faith in them, their fathers actions may be accounted theirs: <hi>For if the roote be holy, ſo are the branches,</hi> Rom. 11.16. <hi>And if the Parents be holy, ſo are the children,</hi> 1 Cor. 7.14.</p>
            <p>Then ſteps up a ſecond ſervant of theirs ſaying, he that is in Chriſt is juſtified, but we muſt be in Chriſt before that we can beleeve: therefore we muſt be juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied before that we can beleeve. But here the ſervant b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>trays his M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> to be ſuch a Chriſt, that any limbe of the Devill may be a reall member of his body, and any ſtrumpet whore remaining ſo, may be his ſpouſe. But the meſtinger of the Lords Chriſt ſaith, <hi>If any man be in Chriſt, he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s a new ere ture: Old things are dine away, all things are become new,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.17. And he takes it for blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:111244:12"/>to ſay any ſuch remaining ſo are members of his body: what, a member of Chriſt, and a member of a harlot? (God forbid) <hi>he that is joyned to the Lord to one ſpirit,</hi> 1 Cor. 6.15.17. That is, one ſpirit, acts all the members of Chriſt, as one spirit acts all our members. Now here you will be put to your ſhiſts, for either you muſt be forced to ſay all thoſe abhominations which are done before gonver on, are the actings of Gods ſpirit in them, or elſe you muſt deny that the ſpirit of God acts them by his grace. But if you ſay the ſpitit of God is not in them, then ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>they are none of his,</hi> Rom. 8.9. And ſo not juſtified. But you play the ſophiſter to prove that all our ſinfull actions are moved by the ſpirit of God before converſion, ſaying, <hi>the act of beleeving is the fruit of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> Gal. 5.22 But this will not cover your naked neſſe, for that is the grace of faith: yet all other graces are the fruits of Gods ſpirit, becauſe hee wrought them in us, but the actings of thoſe graces are partly from Gods ſpirit and partly from ours, and cannot ſo properly be called the fruits of his ſpirit. Againe, what a damuable ſtuggard is the ſpirit of the <hi>Antinomians</hi> Chriſt to lye as a drone in their ſoules twenty or forty yeares, and doe nothing? well may they pull their ſhoulder from the law of God and from all workes of ſanctification, being led by ſuch an idle ſpirit. But the true Chriſt, hath no idle members, nor the true Vine no barren dead branches. But you ſay, if faith be a good fruit, men muſt be good trees, elſe we may gather grapes of thornes, and ſigs on thiſtles. I anſwer, Faith is the fruit of Gods ſpirit, which is a good tree, and cannot beare evill fruits. But what a faith have theſe <hi>Antinomians,</hi> that will not make the tree of their body good? Againe, you ſay, he that hath the ſpirit of Chriſt, hath Chriſt, ſo I ſay too, but you ſay you have the ſpirit before you beleeve, and therefore have Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you beleeve: but have what ſpirit you will, you are no childe of God by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption, till you receive Chriſt by faith, <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.12. And have what ſpirit you will, <hi>it is not the ſpirit of adoption, unleſſe it make you cry Abba Father,</hi> Galat. 4.5, 6. <hi>He is called the ſpirit of grace and ſupplication,</hi> Zech. 12.10. Which none can have before converſion. But here I ſmell an empty trunck for their Chriſt to move in perſonally, and he muſt move them as we move a ſtone, according to their tenets. But the true Chriſt makes us living ſtones to offer a living ſacrifice aceptable to God, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5. <hi>But they will not come to him that they may have life,</hi> Iohn 5.4. <hi>He that hath the ſonke hath life, and he that hath not the ſonne hath not life,</hi> 1 John 5.12. Then here is the cauſe, why they ſtill remaine dead ſtones and empty trun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ks.</p>
            <p>A third ſtands up, ſaying, the Elect are juſtified, therefore ſome that do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve are juſtified before they beleeve: your argument, they that cannot be char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with any thing, are juſtified; but who can lay any thing to the charge of Gods elect? <hi>It is God that juſtifies, who ſhall condemne? It is Chriſt that dyed, yea rather that is riſen againe,</hi> Rom. 8.33. But will it follow, becauſe ſome of the elect are juſtified called, and glorified, that therefore all the elect are ſo? Saith the true Chriſt, <hi>Other ſheepe I have which are not of this fold, them alſo I muſt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:111244:13"/>bring in,</hi> John 10.16. Neither let them bring in their common divelliſh evaſion, ſaying, that is meant of their owne apprehenſion: but is it the voyce of the ſheepe, or the voyce of the ſhepheard that ſpake this? Chriſt ſaith, that they are not of this ſold; but I hope Chriſt was not miſtaken through miſapprehenſion: ſaith the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, <hi>He that beleeveth not the ſonne ſhall not ſeelife, but the wrath of God abideth on him,</hi> John 3.36. Saul, Saul, <hi>why perſecuteſt thou me,</hi> Acts 9.4. Was not this choſen veſſell here taxed with ſinne? <hi>And ſuch were ſome of you</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>being mooved by the Holy Ghoſt, and ye were carried after dumb Idols,</hi> 1 Cor. 6.11, 12.2. And ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> he that wrong<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t effectually in <hi>Peter,</hi> the ſame ſpirit, was mighty in me. Now by the ſame ſpirit he withſtood <hi>Peter</hi> to his face, becauſe he was to be blamed, <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.8.11. ſee 13, 14. And ſaith the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell, <hi>thou ſhalt be dumb, becauſe thou beleeveſt not my words,</hi> Luke 1.20.22, <hi>And ſinne and death is paſſed upon all men,</hi> Rom. 5.12. Then are the elect char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with nothing: <hi>He that committeth ſinns the ſervant of ſin,</hi> John 8.34. Till the Sonne of God make him free, and then they are free indeed. <hi>verſ.</hi> 36.</p>
            <p>A fourth ſtands up, ſaying, they that have their ſinnes taken a way are juſtified, but the elect have their ſins taken away before they beleeve, <hi>Ergo,</hi> the elect are juſtified before they beleeve; Your firſt part you ſay is proved, that ſins are taken away, becauſe <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>they are covered</hi> Pſal. 32.1. And the <hi>minor</hi> you ſay is proved, becauſe <hi>Chriſt is the Lamb of God that taketh away the ſinnes of the world,</hi> Iohn 1.29. <hi>And becauſe the Lord laid on him the in quities of us all.</hi> Iſa 53.6. <hi>Himſelfe bare our ſinnes in his own body on the Tree,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.24. <hi>Our old man is crucified with him, that the body of ſinne might be deſtroyed,</hi> Rom 6.6. But is cove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing a thing the taking away the being of it? Sin is compared to things moſt loath ſome: but when ſuch a thing may be covered, yet it hath a being under that covering, <hi>Deut</hi> 23.13. <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.23. And is Chriſt come &amp; hath begun to take away our ſins? <hi>Yet we are not free from ſinne till death,</hi> Rom. 6.7. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, our ſinnes were not taken from us and lofuſed into Chriſt, no more then we have ſtript him of his righteouſneſſe: bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>by imputation they are accounted to be his, although they remaine in us: and his righteouſneſſe is accounted to bee ours, although it remaine in him ſtill: and for what was laid on Chriſt, was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the guilt and puniſh nent; <hi>He was woanded for our tranſgreſſions, &amp; bruiſed for ur in quities, and the chaſtiſement of our peace <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> on him, and by his ſtrepes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aled,</hi> Iſa 53 5. But if our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> had beene infuſed into him, they had been his and not ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s: and if his rig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſueſſe had beene infuſed into us, it were ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s and not his: for ſinne and puniſhment they goe together, ſo that often he one is named for the other: if thou doſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot well, ſinne lyeth at the doore, that is, puniſhment lyeth at the doo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>for ſin <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> lay then within him,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en. 4.7. ſee 13. Nay further although the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing power of none b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> taken away, yet the being of ſinne is not taken away, no not in the juſtified: Thus hee runs into one ertour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> def<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d another: yet all is too little to make a falſhood to be truth, yet thus they doe in that den.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:111244:13"/>
            <p> Then a fifth ſtands up, ſaying, wee were made ſinners in the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that we had done either good or evil: Therefore we are made righteous in the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> before that we have done either good or evil: The conſequence you ſay is proved, <hi>Rom</hi> 5.18.19. <hi>As by the offence of one, judgement came upon all to condemnation: Even ſo by the righteouſneſſe of one, the free gift came up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> unto juſtification of life.</hi> Now ſay you, the Emphaſis hes in theſe words, <hi>us</hi> and <hi>ſo,</hi> but why may not <hi>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l</hi> be put in without feare to the univerſall gratious. For as all men being in the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> by nature, ſinne and death came upon all men: Even ſo, all that are by faith in the ſecond <hi>Adam:</hi> the gift came upon all to juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of life; Yet here is no univerſall grace for all men without exception but for all the faithful that are tranſlated out of the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> and grafted into the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond. But you it ſeems can find no better man of your judgement, then that Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Beliarmin of ſtinking memory, whom you bring in with his helliſh Tenet, ſaying, that Chriſt may be put on without any proper act of the ſeule. But if I would confi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ne this by men, I could ſhew you one long before <hi>Bellarmin,</hi> and of better crenite, that ſaid, he that made thee without thee, will not ſave thee without thee: But this dead ſtone and empty trunke, neither deſires to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed with grace nor delights in actuall motion, but ſtill remaines among the dead, and as void of grace as an empty trunke.</p>
            <p>A ſixt comes and acts his part; ſaying, where there is full ſatisfaction made, and the party offended accepting of that ſatisfaction, and contented to reſt in it, there muſt needs follow perfect remiſſion of ſinnes: But in Chriſt crucified before we beleeved, was full ſatisfaction made, and God was contented to reſt in that ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, therefore there will follow perfect remiſſion of ſinnes. Then you prove the fulneſſe of Chriſts ſatisfaction from <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.11, 12, 13. And of Gods ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation from <hi>Math.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.11. But to what purpoſe you prove the fulneſſe of Chriſts ſatisfaction, or of Gods acceptation, I know not: For I ſuppoſe you never heard any of our Divines make any queſtion of it: the which if you could, why did you not produce him, that he may be aſhamed of it, and cleare your ſelfe of that which thouſands know to be ſcandall, to your eternall ſhame be it ſpoken. Then here is your errour, this argument is not rightly ſtated: For all men were in the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> by nature, and he ſtanding as a publike perſon in the roome of all men, ſo that what he did, it was reputed to all men, ſo by his ſin all dyed; So the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> ſtanding as a publike perſon for all the elect, as they are in him by ſaith, ſo they are juſtified. But as none is guilty of <hi>Adams</hi> ſinne, till they have a being in <hi>Adams</hi> nature, ſo none is righteous by the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> till they have a being in him by grace: and they muſt have a being in the firſt <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dams</hi> nature, before that they can have a being in the ſecond <hi>Adams</hi> grace; And while they were only in the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> there was no difference betweene the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect and reprobate, between us and them before faith, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.9. <hi>Rom</hi> 3.22. The Scripture hath concluded all under ſinne, <hi>that the promiſe by faith in Ieſus Chriſt might be given to them that believe.</hi> Gal. 3.22. <hi>Wee which beleeve doe
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:111244:14"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> into reſt, but thoſe that do not beleeve, cannot enter in, although the worke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the foundation of the world,</hi> Heb. 4.4.</p>
            <p>A ſeventh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> up in the den, and ſets upon the faithfull meſſenger, ſaying, if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in the ſight of God, then we are hated of him, for hee hateth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> workers of unquity. And if this be ſo, abſurdities will follow, then God will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to day, and hate to morrow, or hate to day, and love to morrow. I anſwer, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> properly, God hates nothing but ſin, he loves his own worke in the very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> &amp; reprobates. Hence your inference is falſe, to ſay that God wholly hates <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> his Creatures. But thus it is is, when the devills and reprobates have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ed God to be their Lord, and ſeeme to weare grace which is his livery in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> teaſonable creatures, but chuſe to ſerve ſin and to weare his livery, <hi>and ſo yield themſelves ſervants to ſinne,</hi> John 8.34. Now when God beholds ſinne, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ndes the heart &amp; affections of devills and reprobates incorporated in it, he comes accidentally to hate them, becauſe where the hearts &amp; affections are, there be thoſe men and Devills.</p>
            <p>Hence it is, that their affections being ſo incorporated in ſinne draw all their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>es to ſerve ſin: In this condition lay all men, both the Elect and reprobate in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> fall of <hi>Adam:</hi> As ſoone as they had any being, the Divell and ſinne ſet upon them, and got their heart and aſſections incorporated into it, till Chriſt comes, who is ſtrenger then this ſtreng man, who binds him and caſts him out, and ſpoyles his goods, and turnes the ſtreame of his affection upon himſelfe: ſo that although they ſlow but ſlowly that way, yet now being incorporated or fixed on Chriſt; So that when the Lord lookes upon his owne ſonne in whom his ſoule delighteth, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> findes there the affections of his people, he comes to love them with the ſame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that he loves his ſonne although not ſo high in degree, yet with the ſame kind <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, becauſe theſe affections being ſet upon Chriſt, draw all the ſtreame of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> obedience to ſerve him, that he delights in, although we have ſome interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which do much hinder the ſtream of our obedience; yet he conſiders this as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> burden and infirmity, and lookes not ſo much upon the worke done, as upon the heart and affection where it is placed; And finding them in Chriſt, his holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and righteouſneſſe is put upon all our obedience and makes it acceptable and well pleaſing to him. But before, when our affections were incloſed in ſinne, we were eſteemed accordingly then as a ſlave to the Divell, and a ſervant of ſin, and now as a childe of God. <hi>For of neceſſity there muſt be a change in us, from the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of Saton to God,</hi> Acts 26.18. The ſtony heart taken out, and the heart of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> given to us. For as there was a change from the ſtate of innocency, <hi>in which God loved us,</hi> Ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 1.27.21. So there renſt be a change into that condition <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> God may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>Put for the preſent, wee are not werthy to be beloved,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eph. 2.2. <hi>Before the decree being forth, then I will call them beloved, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ere not beloved,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. 9.25. Yet as ſoone as we are borne, we have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> God loves, but not as his children by adoption, till we have faith, which knits <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Chriſt, and makes us beloved. The Apoſtle ſets downe the way of Gods
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:111244:14"/>proceeding thus; Firſt, <hi>Elect,</hi> then <hi>holy,</hi> and then <hi>beloved,</hi> Coloſſ. 3.12. Then I conclude, that we are neither beloved nor juſtified before faith, ſee <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.17. Thus the faithfull meſſenger of the Lord Chriſt defended himſelfe with the ſword of the ſpirit which is the Word of God, againſt this ſeven-headed <hi>Hidra</hi> in be Dan.</p>
            <p>Now I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhew you thoſe five incurable wounds that this faithfull meſſenger gave him, that cut ſo deepe, that a man might ſee the very bone periſhed. In this wound was written that we are juſtified by faith, therefore not before faith, this was harſh to him that had none. But the ſervant of the <hi>Antinomians</hi> Chriſt, thought to ſalve it up, ſaying, that he ſpake of the act of beleeving, as though that faith in the true Chriſt could be in the ſoule, and no act of beleeving. But this ſhewes what a faith theirs is. The Apoſtle of the true Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Faith without workes is dead,</hi> James 2.17. Now if their faith be no better, I grant that they may be juſtified aſwel without it as with it, But it ſeemes he hath gotten ſome old heretick of his ſide, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> ſaid, that it was a wreſting of the Scripture to ſay that we are juſtified by faith, but he is aſhamed to name him, and therefore I ſuppoſe his conſcience is convinced, and hath checked him for ſpeaking of it: but he ſaid a man may be both juſtified with faith and without it, in a different ſenſe. Firſt, to be reputed and accounted juſt; I anſwer, but this is Gods worke alone. But then ſecondly, It may be taken to declare or manifeſt us to be juſt, as workes Juſtifie; I anſwer, as faith is a worke, it declares, yet not to others, but to our ſelves. <hi>Haſt thou faith? have it to thy ſelfe before God,</hi> Rom. 4.22. But faith it ſelfe is many times as hard to be known as our juſtification: I meane that act of it that juſtifies us, which is to take and apply Chriſt and his benefits unto us; Thus it juſtifies, &amp; is very hard to be known, but as it workes by love, and acts all other graces, ſo it ſanctifies and may eaſily be known: and by this meanes we come to know that we are juſtified. I hoſe fruits of faith juſtifie the trueth of our faith, that it is li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and not a dead faith when it bringeth forth fruits. <hi>But faith is the hand of the ſoule, taking hold of Chriſt the Iuſtifier, and ſo it is counted for righteouſneſſe,</hi> Rom. 4.5. So then God juſtifies by forgiving and pronouncing a ſinner to be juſt, and our works juſtifie by declaring to others that God hath juſtified us, but faith juſtifies by receiving and applying Chriſt and his merits, and ſo makes us juſt. If you did but know what true faith was, you might ſoone know where to place it in point of Juſtification, ſo ſhould you not exalt it into Gods place, nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſe it into the place of workes.</p>
            <p>The ſecond deadly wound that was given to <hi>Hidra,</hi> in his Den, was this; <hi>He that beleeueth not ſhall be damned,</hi> Mar. 16.16. And this cut ſo deepe, that he almoſt deſpaired of help: For ſaith he, if it be finall, it is a note of damnation. Now this is all that we require, for we do not ſay that every man ſhall be damned that is in the ſtate of unbeleife, for then all ſhould be damned: but we ſay that fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall unbeliefe damnes the ſoule: and this you grant, and yet you ſaid that Infants are juſtified before they have faith; Now if they ſhould dye being juſtified, are
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:111244:15"/>they damned, becauſe they do not beleeve? or are they ſaved, and yet dye in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beliefe? How will you get out of this circle? This den may be called the land of darkneſſe without order, <hi>Iob</hi> 10.22, Being full of Theeves, and without go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, daſhing and ſplitting themſelves one againſt another.</p>
            <p>A third deadly wound the faithfull meſſenger gave him in his den, was this; <hi>Without faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe God.</hi> Therefore wee cannot bee juſtified without it. Now a man pleaſeth God when he doth thoſe things that God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires, and in that manner that he requires, and to that end as he requires; Now theſe he approves to be well done, becauſe they are grounded upon his Word, &amp; acted by a juſtified perſon, and tend to his glory; Now this you grant, ſaying, we cannot come to God without faith, and therefore cannot pleaſe him: but you being ſenſible that your faith is nought, if you have any, and therefore you ſeeke another way to cure it, ſaying, although wee cannot come to God before wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, yet God can come to us, and Juſtification is Gods act upon a ſinner, and not a ſinners act upon God.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, For to pronounce a ſinner juſt, is Gods act, but to take and apply that righten ſneſſe of Chriſt that makes us juſt, is our act of faith. And to ſay that God will pronounce any juſt, before that they have by faith put on Chriſt, <hi>Rom</hi> 13. This were to make God an unrighteous Judge to pronounce them juſt which are not juſt: For what juſtice hath a ſinner, till the juſtice of Chriſt is made over to him, and accounted for his? Therefore faith in Chriſt muſt needs goe before God pronounce them juſt.</p>
            <p>Again, they do not only blaſphe are God as an unrighteous Judge, pronouncing them juſt which are yet unjuſt: <hi>When at hee will by no meanes cleare the guilty,</hi> Exod. 34.7.</p>
            <p>But alſo by this we may ſee what a Chriſt our <hi>Antinomians</hi> boaſt ſo much of w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> comes ſneaking a day after the fair, and brings them faith, when they are juſt before, &amp; brings his righteouſneſſe when they need it not, &amp; comes to help them when they have tryed their cauſe before the Judge, and quitted before he comes! Such a Chriſt is not worth ſeeking after. But what is your meaning of Gods comming to you, when you have no faith to come to him? Is God come to you, and yet you remaine at a diſtance from him, or doth God moove perſonally to you, and you ſit ſtill, as a man may come to you while you are ſitting? I had thought God had filled all places, and did not move from place to place as man doth; Theſe are but poore fig-leaves to hide your nakedneſſe, then the trueth is, Gods comming to us, and our comming to him is the ſame thing, only the cauſe of the motion is in God, and the motion it ſelfe in us: So then when God moves us to come to him, this is his comming to us, and then we cannot be aſunder; Now he moves us by his ſpirit, infuſing faith into us, and ſo our faith taking hold on him, we are drawn by his ſpirit into unity and communion with him.</p>
            <p>The fourth deadly wound given to <hi>Hedra</hi> in his den, is this; <hi>Whatſoever is not of faith, is ſinne,</hi> Rom. 14.23. This is terrible to him that hath no faith:
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:111244:15"/>Therefore he being ſenſible that there is ſomething in it that would bite cruelly, if he ſhould ſuffer it to faſten upon him: therefore hee ſhifts his hands of it with all the ſpeed he can, ſaying, he anſwered it in the third already, when as the meane time it gnawes upon his conſcience as a gangreine that is incurable, for God and fin are at a deadly enmity, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.7. <hi>Iam.</hi> 4.4.</p>
            <p>The fifth deadly wound that this faithfull meſſenger gave to the <hi>Antinonsians</hi> Chriſt is his den, is this; <hi>We are by nature children of wrath,</hi> Epheſ. 2.3. This he knows not well how to rid his hands of, but ſaith, if we could prove it to be ſo in Gods account, as well as in our owne eſteeme, and that wee are ſo exempted from grace untill we beleeve, it were ſomething.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, God eſteemes them as they are in themſelves before converſion, ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his own purpoſe aſide, to be but as Reprobates. Neither was hee moved by any love to them from all eternity, to have ſuch a purpoſe toward them. The cauſe of Gods decrees and purpoſes was love to himſelfe, to ſet forth his own glory. This was the ground of all Gods purpoſes to us, for then there was nothing elſe but himſelfe to love; Now all reprobates have their deſcent from the Devill as they are reprobates. <hi>Ye are of your father the Devill, for his workes ye doe,</hi> John 8.44. <hi>And they are called the ſeed of the Serpent,</hi> Gen. 3.15. <hi>Know you not. that to whom ye yeeld your members ſervants to obey, his ſervants ye are, to whom you obey,</hi> Rom. 6.16. Now before converſion, the Elect are ſervants of ſinne, as well as the reprobates. <hi>Ye were the ſervants of ſinne</hi> (ſaith the holy Ghoſt) <hi>but now ye are become the ſervants of ryghteouſneſſe,</hi> Rom. 6.17, 18. A gaine, the ſeed of the woman <hi>(ſaith the holy Ghoſt)</hi> is none but Chriſt. <hi>Hee ſaith not to ſeeds, as of many, but as of one, which is Chriſt,</hi> Gal. 3.16. So then as all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind lye in the fal of <hi>Adam.</hi> They are the ſeed of the Serpent, <hi>till they are begotten againe by the immortall ſeed to a lively hope,</hi> 1 Pet. 13.23. <hi>And borne againe of the water and the ſpirit,</hi> John 3.5. So then what is ſaid of Reprobates, is ſaid of the Elect before converſion. For they are of their father the Devill, that do his workes, going on in a courſe of ſinne: Theſe are in the ſnare of the Devil, led cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive at his will, and yet may be recovered out of lt, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.26. <hi>Such were ſome of you, but ye are waſhed; ye were carried away unto theſe dumb Idolls,</hi> 1 Cor. 6.10, 11, 1.2, 2. <hi>Ye were without Chriſt, being aliens and ſtrangers from the Covenants of promiſe, and without God in the world,</hi> Epheſ. 2.12. And ſaith the holy Ghoſt; <hi>Hee that beleeveth not the ſonne ſhall not ſee life, but the wrath of God abideth on him,</hi> John 3.36. And the Lord calls them his adverſaries and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies. <hi>Yet he wl purge away their droſſe, and take away their tinne, and Zisn ſhalbe redeemed with judgement,</hi> Iſa. 1.24.25.27. <hi>I have wounded thee with the wound of an enemy, yet I will reſtore health unto thee, and heale thy wounds ſaith the Lord,</hi> Jer. 30.14.17. <hi>And the Lord hateth all workers of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>iquity. and the Lord will ab hor the bloody and deceitfull man,</hi> Pſal. 5.5, 6. Here is no exception made, whether they be elect or reprobate, but upon the condition of faith and repentance. For ſaith the holy Ghoſt: <hi>There is no difference, for all have,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:111244:16"/>ſinned,</hi> Rom. 3.22, 23. And ſaith <hi>Peter: He put no difference between us and them, purifying our hearts by faith,</hi> Acts 15.9. Here comes the difference, when the Lord gives faith, and by it we receive Chriſt and his benefits. <hi>What haſt thou th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a that thou didſt not receive from God, ſo he made thee to differ from another,</hi> 1 Cor. 5.7. And the holy Ghoſt ſaith, <hi>I will call them my people which were not my people, and her beloved which was not beloved,</hi> Rom, 9.25. Thus you ſee I bring Gods own teſtimonies becauſe that you ſhal not ſay men ſpeak of them from miſapprehenſion. Now let God be true, and all the Antinomians lyers, which would by a ſubtle evaſion overthrow all the Scripture, ſaying; When God ſhall command any duty. or forbid any vice, or promiſe any mercy, or threaten any judgment for ſin, all the Scripture muſt be brought to this. Do they apprehend it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they do not, it is not ſo. Suppoſe the Propher ſay, <hi>thou waſt angry with me,</hi> Iſa. 12.1. This they put off with miſapprehenſion. And when <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, I was a Perſecutor, a Blaſphemer and injurious, this they ſay was miſapprehenſion, when any ſpeake thus of themſelves before converſion. But what will they ſay to thoſe words of Chriſt; <hi>Saul, Saul, why perſecuteſt thou me,</hi> Acts 9.5. And when the Apoſtle ſaith; <hi>We had our converſation in times paſt, in the luſts of the fleſh, and we were children of wrath by nature, even as others.</hi> This they put off with miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>apprehenſion, <hi>Epheſians</hi> 2.3. But how will they put off this; <hi>You were dead in treſpaſſes and ſins, and ye were Gentiles in the fleſh, &amp; ye were without Chriſt, and without God in the world,</hi> verſ. 1.11, 12. Thus you ſee the wound is incurable, it cannot be healed, which the faithful meſſenger gave the roaring lyon in his den.</p>
            <p>Now I ſhall proceed to ſee how the Antinomians Chriſt is able to ſtand in the preſence of the Lords Chriſt. Firſt, their errours were laid open to the view of the world in five generall heads; And then perceiving them to fly, a faithfull meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger was ſent after them to their laſt place of refuge, and ſo he going to their den was ſet upon, and I have given thee a juſt account of their Combat, and now we ſhall ſee whether they have been led all this while by the true Chriſt or not. Now this Meſſenger hath brought him to his tryall. Now if the <hi>Antinomians</hi> Chriſt be the true Chriſt, then we will follow him. But if thoſe whom they ſcornfully cal Legaliſts, ſerve the true Chriſt, let all follow him, we will compare them together and both with the Word of God.</p>
            <p>Our Chriſt was promiſed when <hi>Adam</hi> had ſinned, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. And in that promiſe by faith, all the elect were ſaved before his comming in the fleſh. But our <hi>Antinomians</hi> Chriſt tells ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, that they were ſaved before his comming in the fleſh, for their ſincere obedience to the morall law of God. This <hi>Simpſon</hi> affirmed before the Committee of Divines in my hearing; And that promiſed ſeede of the woman, (they ſay) was nothing concerning redemption, but only it was a word ſpoken to the Serpent as a part of his curſe, therefore they renounce it. This was witneſſed by foure of them, <hi>viz.</hi> Mr. <hi>Wetton,</hi> Mr. <hi>George,</hi> Mr. <hi>Banes,</hi> and one more againſt me, and ſome others.</p>
            <p>Our Chriſt is the ſubſtance of the Covenant of grace, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42.6. And all the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:111244:16"/>Elect are ſaved by him. But the <hi>Antinomians</hi> Chriſt was the ſubſtance of the firſt Covenant, the Covenant of workes, witneſſe Dr. <hi>Criſpe</hi> in his book, <hi>page</hi> 121.</p>
            <p>Our Chriſt comes openly, ſaying, <hi>I ſpeake openly to the world, I ever taught in the Sinagogues and in the Temple, whether the lows alwayes reſort, and in ſecret have I ſaid nothing.</hi> John 18.20. And faith <hi>Paul, I am not aſhamed of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell of Chriſt,</hi> Rom. 1.16. <hi>He went into the Sinagogue and ſpake boldly,</hi> Acts 19.8. But the <hi>Antinomians</hi> Chriſt <hi>creeps into houſes, and leads captive ſilly women laden with ſins, and led away with divers luſts, ever learning, and never able to come to the knowledg of the trueth,</hi> 2 Tim. 3.6, 7. <hi>He is in the ſecret chambers, or in the deſars,</hi> Math. 24.26. He is in their private meetings, the nurſeries of al hereſies, while there is liberty to worſhip the Lord openly.</p>
            <p>Our Chriſt comes into the ſoule with power, <hi>pulling down the ſtrong holds of Satan binds the ſtrong man, and ſpoyles his goods,</hi> Math. 12.28. <hi>And caſts him out by the ſpirit of God,</hi> verſ. 29. But the <hi>Antinomians</hi> Chriſt comes into their ſoule, and lives there as an underling in that ſoule, where the Divell raignes as Lord and King, <hi>and leads them captive at his will,</hi> 2 Tim. 2.26, <hi>The Prince of the power of the ayre ruleth in the children of diſobedience,</hi> Epheſ. 2.2, See <hi>Criſp.</hi> page 320.</p>
            <p>When the ſpirit of our Chriſt comes into the ſoule, he takes out the ſtone out of the heart, <hi>and renews a right ſpirit in us,</hi> Pſal. 51. <hi>In righteouſneſſe and true ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe,</hi> Epheſ. 4.23.24. <hi>It is God that worketh in you both to will and to doe of his owne good pleaſure,</hi> Phil. 2.13. But the ſpirit of the <hi>Antinomians</hi> Chriſt is an idle ſpirit, living many years in the ſoule as an underling to the Divell, doing nothing.</p>
            <p>When our Chriſt puts his ſpirit into us, this ſpirit cauſeth us to walke in his ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and to keep his judgments and do them, <hi>Ezek</hi> 36.27. <hi>The holy Ghoſt wil teach you all things, and bring all things to your remembrance,</hi> John 14.26. <hi>And brings in every thought to the obedience of Chriſt,</hi> 2 Cor. 10.5. <hi>And leads into all truth,</hi> John 16.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. But the <hi>Antinomians</hi> Chriſt puts neither life nor motion in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thoſe where he comes, but ſtill they remaine dead ſtones and empty trunckes. See the tree of knowledge and counſell to <hi>Laodicea.</hi> Againe, when our Chriſt comes into the ſoule, he comes as a King, and commands obedience to the morall law, being the ſtatute law of heaven, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.89.103.20. Saying, <hi>you have heard that it hath been ſaid thus, but I ſay unto you thus,</hi> Math. 5. <hi>He taught as one having authority, and not as the Scribes,</hi> Mat. 7.29. He cleared the law from theſe falſe gloſſes of the Scribes and Phariſees, and delivered it in his own name; And when one asked what he ſhould do to have eternall life, then he ſends him to the Law. But the <hi>Antinomians</hi> Chriſt frees them from all obedience to the morall law, and makes them as idle as himſelfe.</p>
            <p>Our Chriſt commands us to take heed of drunkenneſſe and ſurfeiting and cares of this life, <hi>that we may be accounted worthy to eſcape the dangers of the dreadfull day, and to ſtand before the ſon of man,</hi> Luke 21.34, 35. But the <hi>Antinomians</hi> Chriſt perſwades them that a Drunkard or Whore-monger, or any vile perſon
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:111244:17"/>without any change or alteration in the world, if his heart do but ſay; I would have Chriſt: al that ſinfulneſſe though continued in, is no bar in the world to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this man from claiming his portion in Chriſt, ſee Dr. <hi>Criſp,</hi> page 314.320.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle of our Chriſt ſaith; <hi>Ye luſt and have not, and ye aske to ſpend it on your luſts. Ye adul erers and adultereſſes, know ye not that the friend-ſhip of this world is enmity with God.</hi> James 4. But the <hi>Antinomians</hi> Chriſt perſwades them that <hi>David</hi> did not offend the Lord in the ſin of adultery, nor <hi>Paul</hi> in his perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Saints of God: for all occaſion of quarrell and controverſie is abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly taken away, ſee Dr. <hi>Criſpe,</hi> page 303. Nay further they affirme, that if a man refraine adultery in obedience to the law, he ſins more then he that commits that that fearfull ſin in deſpight of the law: which makes them forſake all their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance that live in obedience to the law, and chuſe to themſelves ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane company that they may be ſure aro of their own opinions.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle of our Chriſt ſaith, every member is neceſſary, being led by one ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit into all truth, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16.13. <hi>And baptized into one ſpirit, and rejoyce in each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers happineſſe, and grieve at any injury done to their fellow-members, there is no ſchiſme in his body,</hi> 1 Cor. 12.12.13.25.26. But the <hi>Antinomians</hi> Chriſt leads ſome of his members, but the Divell leads many more of them then he, being whores and drunkards, without any change or alteration, ſee <hi>Criſp.</hi> p. 314.320. Who defie the law of God. For one of them ſaid, I am not bound to live with a dead man, I will take to me a ſpirituall husband. And ſhee like a ſtrumpet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooke her husband and took another, and yet a member of their Chriſt: witneſſe Mr. <hi>Ruſhbrook</hi> and his wife. If any ſhall ſay, he is a member of our Chriſt, &amp; bear no fruit, <hi>he takes him away, and caſts him into the fire, being a withered branch &amp; good for nothing,</hi> Joh. 15.2.6. <hi>He is not an unrighteous Iudge to cal evill good, he will not juſtifie the wicked,</hi> Iſa. 5. <hi>He wil by no meanes clear the guilty,</hi> Exo. 34.7 He went into his garden to ſee the fruits of the valley, whether the Vine flouriſh, and the Pomgranat budded, <hi>Cant</hi> 6.11. He ſaith: <hi>Herein is my Father glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that ye bear much fruit,</hi> (marke) <hi>ſo ſhall ye be my Diſciples,</hi> Joh. 15.8. But the <hi>Antinomians</hi> Chriſt pronounceth an unrighteous ſentence, calling evill good, ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifying the guilty before they have any faith to receive the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, whereby alone they may be juſt.</p>
            <p>Our Chriſt ſaith, <hi>being juſtified by faith, we have grace with God,</hi> Rom. 5.1. Therefore wee conclude, that a man is juſtified by faith without the deeds of the law, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.28. Hee that beleeveth on him that juſtifieth the ungodly (now mark) <hi>his faith is courted for righteouſneſſe,</hi> Rom. 4.5. But the <hi>Antinomians</hi> Chriſt ſaith, they are juſtified before and without faith, while they remain ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſee <hi>Criſp.</hi> page 136.155.</p>
            <p>Our Chriſt ſaith, <hi>he that beleeveth not ſhalbe damned,</hi> Mark 16.16. <hi>Neither ſhal he ſee life, but the wrath of God abideth on him,</hi> Joh. 3.36. But the <hi>Antino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mians</hi> Chriſt ſaith, a man may be ſaved without faith: ſee the counſell of Chriſt to <hi>Laodicea.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:111244:17"/>
            <p> Our Chriſt when he comes into the ſoule, he comes by water and blood to ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie aſwel as to juſtifie, 1 John 5.6. But the <hi>Antinomians</hi> Chriſt comes to juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie them, and yet not to ſanctifie at the ſame time. Nay further he ſaith, ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of life is not a jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the way of a juſtified perſon unto heaven, ſee <hi>Criſp</hi> p. 69.</p>
            <p>The ſpirit of our Chriſt is always working in us where it is, and by this working we know our ſelves to be juſtified. But the <hi>Antinomians</hi> Chriſt perſwades them that their juſtification cannot be known by their ſanctification, but by a revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on only.</p>
            <p>Our Chriſt ſaith, <hi>whoſoever committeth ſin is the ſervant of ſin,</hi> Joh. 3.34. But the <hi>Antinomians</hi> Chriſt tells them, if they act any ſin, that he is the author of it. For alas they cannot ſin, they are dead ſtones and empty trunks. Alas they doe nothing but what the ſpirit of their Chriſt leads them into: See the tree of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of good and evill.</p>
            <p>Our Chriſt ſaith, we that are in him are new creatures. <hi>Old things are paſſed away, &amp; al things are new.</hi> 2 Cor. 5.17. We are paſſed from death to life, &amp; made living ſtones to offer a living ſacrifice acceptable to God by Ieſus Chriſt, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5. But the <hi>Antinomians</hi> Chriſt loves his members aſwel when they were ſlaves and ſervants to ſin and Sathan, as when they are ſet free and become his children by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption: he loves them aſwel when they are prophane as when they are holy. Nay he gives a charge to all his members, that if one ſin, the reſt muſt not tell him of it, But comfort him; for to mourn for ſin is a diſhonour to their Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Our Chriſt ſaith, when God ſends forth the ſpirit of his ſon into our hearts, we will cry <hi>abba Father,</hi> Gal. 4.5, 6. <hi>It is the ſpirit of grace and ſupplication,</hi> Zech, 12.10. <hi>And he greatly delighteth in their prayers,</hi> Prov. 15.8. Cant. 2.14. But the <hi>Antinomians</hi> Chriſt tells them they need not pray. For ſaith one of them, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing grieves me ſo much as the time I have ſpent in prayer and other duties, that hath held me ſo long from my comfort.</p>
            <p>Our Chriſt ſaith, <hi>When you have done all that you can, you are unprofitable ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants,</hi> Luke 17.10. <hi>You have done but your duty.</hi> But the <hi>Antinomians</hi> Chriſt tells them, that all Chriſtian duties are but dirty dungy duties of ſanctification.</p>
            <p>Our Chriſt ſaith, <hi>If ye beleeve not that I am he, ye ſhal dye in your ſins,</hi> John 8.24. But the <hi>Antinomians</hi> Chriſt ſaith that faith is not abſolutely neceſſary to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, for it is but a worke of ours.</p>
            <p>Our Chriſt ſaw nothing to love in us, which moved him to redeem us; Till he adorned us and made us lovely there was no difference. <hi>For all have ſinned, and come ſhore of the glory of God,</hi> Rom. 3.22.23. Saith <hi>Peter, he put no difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us and them, purifying our hearts by faith,,</hi> Acts 15.9. But our <hi>Antino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mians</hi> Chriſt ſaw ſome cauſe of love before he came, even from all eternity, which moved him to redeeme them.</p>
            <p>Our Chriſt makes us righteous by his righteouſneſſe, when wee are in him by grace: as the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> made us ſinners when we have a being in him by nature, but not before. But the <hi>Antinomians</hi> are made righteous by their Chriſt before
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:111244:18"/>they be in him by grace. And, <hi>Adam</hi> never made them ſinners, for they were ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified from all eternity, and alwayes as righteous as Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Our Chriſt tells us that God pronounceth us juſt and faith applyes the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of Chriſt to make us juſt, and workes declare it. But our Antinomians Chriſt cannot direct them where to place their faith in point of juſtification, that it may not be exalted in the place of God, nor abaſed in the place of workes. But if their Chriſt were able to give them true faith, hee could direct them where to place it.</p>
            <p>Our Chriſt will not have his Temple defiled. <hi>For the Temple of God is holy, which Temple ye are,</hi> 1 Cor, 3.16, 17. <hi>He deſires truth in the inward parts,</hi> Pſal. 51.6. But the Antinomians Chriſt regards not where he dwells. It is all one to him if he live to a habitation of devills, and the hold of every foule ſpirit, and Cage of every unclean luſt, <hi>Revel.</hi> 18.2.</p>
            <p>Our Chriſt himſelfe bare the guilt and puniſhment of our ſins, and carried our ſorrowes: he alone trod the wine-pres of Gods wrath, and there was none with him. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.4.63.3. He ſaith I am he: <hi>Therefore if ye ſeeke me, let theſe goe,</hi> John 18.8. But the Antinomians Chriſt comes ſneaking a day after the faire, &amp; brings them faith when they are juſt before, and righteouſneſſe when they need it not, and comes to helpe them when they have tryed their cauſe before the Judge, and quitted before he comes.</p>
            <p>Our Chriſt, as God fills all places, and his humane nature is in the third hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, till the reſtitution of all things, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.21. So then as he is God, he doth not move, and as he is man, he will not come till the day of judgement. Therefore when it is ſpoken of his comming to us, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> our comming to him, it is the ſame thing: onely the cauſe of this motion is us God, and the motion it ſelfe in us: for when he works faith in us by his ſpirit, our faith takes hold againe, and ſo we are drawn into unity and communion with him. But our Antinomians Chriſt can come to them before that they have faith, while that they are at a diſtance from him. But how this can be, themſelves know not; ſee <hi>Den's</hi> 7. arguments.</p>
            <p>Our Chriſt ſaith, <hi>If thou beleeveſt, thou ſhalt be ſaved,</hi> Acts 16.31. Yea hee ſaith, only beleeve, <hi>Mar.</hi> 5.36. But the Antinomians Chriſt t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lls them that hee will ſave them without any ſuch conditions; which ſaith he, is the doctrine of le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall teachers: See counſell to Laodicea: ſee Dr, <hi>Criſp,</hi> page 128.</p>
            <p>Our Chriſt tells us, the only way to pacifie conſcience, is to exerciſe faith, for it is the hand of the ſoule, whereby wee receive all our mercies and comforts from Chriſt; And it brings us into unity with chriſt, and into obedience to the ſpirit of chriſt. But our Antinomians Chriſt tells them, that thoſe which ſay we cannot be ſaved without faith, do perplex the conſcience, and denies our mercies, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth the ſpirit of God, and doth not conſiſt with the right end, for which faith was wrought in them: ſee counſel to Laodicea.</p>
            <p>Our Chriſt came preaching the Goſpell of the Kingdome of God, and ſaying, <hi>repent and beleeve the Goſpell,</hi> Mar. 1.14, 15. And he ſaith, <hi>Doe unto all men,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:111244:18"/>as ye would they ſhould do unto you, even ſo do to them.</hi> And gives a reaſon, ſaying, <hi>this is the law and the Prophets,</hi> Math. 7.12. But the Antinomians chriſt will nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have them to beleeve nor repent as a duty, nor do to others as we would have them do to us: For ſay they, this is legall teaching; ſee counſel to Laodicea.</p>
            <p>Our Chriſt ſaith, humble your ſelves under the mighty hand of God, <hi>Iames</hi> 4.10. And bleſſed are they that weep now, for they ſhall laugh, <hi>Luke</hi> 6.21. And bleſſed are they that mourne, for they ſhalbe comforted, <hi>Math.</hi> 5.4. And our Chriſt ſaid unto us; <hi>The time will come that the Bridegroom ſhall be taken from you, and then ye ſhall faſt,</hi> Luke 5.35. But our Antinomians chriſt teacheth them that they muſt neither humble themſelves, weepe not mourn, laſt nor pray for ſin or affliction: ſee <hi>Criſp,</hi> page 109.110.230.</p>
            <p>Our Chriſt gave the Sacrament the night before he ſuffered, ſaying, <hi>Take, eate, drinke, do this in remembrance of me,</hi> 1 Cor. 11.24.25. Neither did chriſt blot out the forth commandement, when hee cleared them from the falſe gloſſes of the Scribes and Phariſees, but rather ſhewed his Diſciples how they ought more ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctly to obſerve and keep them. But the Antinomians chriſt tells them this is legal teaching: for the law is void to them, and ought not to be obſerved: ſee counſell to Laodicea.</p>
            <p>Our Lord Chriſt commands us to grow in grace, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.18. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.1.</p>
            <p>But the Antinomians chriſt ſaith, they are as righteous as he in reſpect of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, and therefore cannot grow in grace, neither need they to receive the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for that purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Our Chriſt was tempted of the Iſraelites in the wilderneſſe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.9. Yet he was reconciling the world to himſelfe, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.19. And afterwards when he came in our nature, they cryed out, crucifie him, and murthered the Prince of life, <hi>Acts</hi> 14.15. Yet he prayed for them, and his prayeres was heard. But the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinomians chriſt tells them that they never did offend him, but were reconciled to him from all eternity, and pronounced them juſt before they were, and ſo born as righteous as chriſt without any originall ſinne.</p>
            <p>Our Chriſt came to adopt all his ſons that did receive him. <hi>For as many as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived him, to them he gave power to become the ſons of God, to them that believe on his Name,</hi> John 1.12. For ye are all the children of God by faith in Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3 26. But the Antinomians Chriſt tells them that they were adopted from all eternity.</p>
            <p>Our Chriſt ſaith, <hi>ſearch the Scriptures,</hi> Iohn 5.39. And the noble <hi>Bereans</hi> are highly commended for ſearching the Scripture, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.11, But the Antinomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans Chriſt tells them that they neede not the written Word, without they are ſo full of light within, and that any thing is Scripture, if it be but written, and of an equall vallew with it; ſee the tree of Knowledge. <hi>But they rejecting the Word of the Lord, what wiſdome is in them?</hi> Ier. 8.9.</p>
            <p>Our Chriſt ſaid, <hi>If ye beleeved</hi> Moſes, <hi>ye would have beleeved me: But if yee beleeve not his writings, how ſhall ye beleeve my words,</hi> Iohn 6.47, 48. But the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:111244:19"/>
               <hi>Antinomians</hi> Chriſt &amp; <hi>Moſes</hi> are at a perpetuall enmity, becauſe <hi>Moſes</hi> requires obedience, and they are led by an idle ſpirit, which neither infuſeth grace into them, nor doe they deſire it, leſt they ſhould be bound to improve, or to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe it.</p>
            <p>Our Chriſt ſaith by his Apoſtle; <hi>If we or an Angell of heaven ſhould preach a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other Goſpel then that we have preached unto you, let him be accurſed,</hi> Gal. 1.8, 9. But the <hi>Antinomians</hi> Chriſt by their own confeſſion hath revealed to them a new light, that Gods faithfull people never ſaw before. But they that bring it, <hi>are falſe Apoſtles, deceitfull workers, transforming themſelves into the Apoſtles of Chriſt, and as Miniſters of righteouſneſſe. And no marvell, for Satan himſelfe is transformed into an Angel of light,</hi> 2 Cor. 11.13, 14. <hi>But they that ſay they ſee by his light, their ſin remaineth,</hi> John 9.41. They think of men above that which is written, <hi>therefore they are puffed up one againſt another,</hi> 1 Cor. 4.6.</p>
            <p>Our Chriſt is become a ſurety for us, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.22. And his righteouſneſſe is imputed to us, and accounted ours. But the <hi>Antinomians</hi> Chriſt tells them that he hath ſtripped them of their ſins, and they have ſtripped him of his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſo that they are deified, &amp; he is degraded of his God-head, and now they are made righteouſneſſe in the abſtract. See <hi>Hony-comb.</hi> And he is made ſin in the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for them.</p>
            <p>Our Chriſt by his Apoſtle, <hi>bids us to ſtrive together for the faith of the Goſpell,</hi> Phil. 1.27. And ſaith, <hi>ye have not yet reſiſted unto blood, ſtriving againſt firme,</hi> Heb. 12.2. He ſaid the time would come, <hi>that he which hath no ſword, ſhould ſell his garment to buy one,</hi> Luke 22.36. And when the Souldiers came to him to know what they ſhould doe, he bad them doe no violence by plundering any man, but be content with your wages. But he did not bid them leave fighting for the Goſpell and Religion, <hi>Luke</hi> 3.14. But the <hi>Antinomians</hi> Chriſt will not have them fight for the Goſpell nor Religion, yet hee will give way to fight for other things, which ſheweth him to be a carnall Chriſt, framed in their own fancy, and he and his Proſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lites are all alike, who ſay that they will fight for carnall things, but not for the Goſpell nor Religion.</p>
            <p>Our Chriſt is given for a <hi>Covenant of the people,</hi> Iſa. 49.8. And ſaith the Lord, <hi>they ſhall aske the way to Zion with their face thitherward,</hi> ſaying, <hi>come let us joyn our ſelves to the Lord in a perpetuall Covenant that ſhall never be forgotten,</hi> Jer. 50.5. But the <hi>Antinomians</hi> Chriſt will cauſe them to deſpiſe all bonds and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venants to the Lord and to his Chriſt, ſaying, <hi>let us breake their bonds aſunder, &amp; caſt away their cords from us,</hi> Pſal. 2.3. Yea, they abhor the very ſeales of that covenant already made with the Lords Chriſt, leſt by them they ſhould grow in grace, which is very hatefull to the Antinomians Chriſt. <hi>Theſe be thoſe truce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breakers, having aforme of godlineſſe, but deny the power of it, from ſuch turn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way,</hi> 2 Tim. 3.3.5.</p>
            <p>Our Chriſt is that good ſhepheard which gave his life for his ſheep, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 10.11. He ſaith, <hi>I pray not for the world, but for thoſe that thou haſt given me, for they
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:111244:19"/>are thine,</hi> John 17.9. But the <hi>Antinomians</hi> Chriſt tells them that he dyed for the whole world. Therefore ſaith Dr. <hi>Criſpe,</hi> we may collect the univerſality of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of all and every particular perſon in the world: ſee his book, p. 296.</p>
            <p>Our Chriſt tells his followers afore-hand, what it wil coſt them to be a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, ſaying, <hi>he moſt ſell all and give it to the poore,</hi> Lu. 18.22. <hi>and denie himſelfe,</hi> Luke 9.23. <hi>And hate father and mother, wife and children, brethren and ſiſters, and his own life alſo, elſe he cannot be my Diſciple,</hi> Luke 14.26. But the <hi>Antino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mians</hi> Chriſt tells them of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at paſtures, and fulneſſe of pleaſures: ſee <hi>Criſpe,</hi> p. 31.</p>
            <p>Our Chriſt was angry at the buyers &amp; ſellers in the Temple, &amp; whipped them out of it, <hi>Math</hi> 21.12.13. But the <hi>Antinomians</hi> Chriſt tells them that afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for ſin are the ſmiles of God, &amp; his choyceſt imbraces and ſtrokes are the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt manifeſting of Gods love to them, p: 43.</p>
            <p>Our Chriſt ſaith, <hi>God ſpared not his only ſon, but gave him up for us all,</hi> Rom. 8.32. But the <hi>Antinomians</hi> Chriſt tells them that his Father broke out furiouſly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, and he was ſatisfied to ſee his ſon tormented: Yea, it did his ſoule good to behold it: ſee blaſpheming <hi>Criſpe,</hi> page 46, 47.</p>
            <p>Our Chriſt requires of us thirſting, comming, buying, eating, hearkning, ſeeking &amp; calling upon God, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.1, 2. But the <hi>Antinomians</hi> Chriſt requires nothing, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to take the offer of him in a carnall manner, to keepe them from puniſhments.</p>
            <p>Our Chriſt bids us to aske, ſeek, and knock, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. <hi>And to ſtrive to enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſtraight gate.</hi> But the <hi>Antinomians</hi> Chriſt like <hi>Iudas,</hi> ſaith, what needs all this waſt? for he brings juſtification, loving kindneſſe and ſalvation, and laies it at our doors, and yet we will be doing and running 100. miles about in vaine: ſee <hi>Criſpe,</hi> page 63.</p>
            <p>Our Chriſt only admits of ſuch gueſts as have on their wedding garment, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.11.12. But the <hi>Antinomians</hi> Chriſt puts back thoſe that have ſome holineſſe, and admits of whores and drunkards remaining ſuch, page 66, 67.</p>
            <p>Our Chriſt approves and requires ſelfe-denyall, faſting and prayer, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther graces. But the <hi>Antinomians</hi> Chriſt tells them, that theſe are but the devices of the world: ſee <hi>Criſpe,</hi> page 68.</p>
            <p>Our Chriſt came <hi>to ſeeke and to ſave that which was loſt,</hi> Luke 19.10. But the <hi>Antinomians</hi> Chriſt comes to ſave thoſe that were never loſt, but juſtified and beloved from all eternity.</p>
            <p>Our Chriſt was offended with <hi>Peter</hi> for ſin after converſion, and ſaid, <hi>Get thee behind me Sathan, for thou art an offence unto me, for thou ſavoureſt not the things that be of God, but the things that be of men,</hi> Mat. 16.23. But the <hi>Antinomians</hi> Chriſt cannot be offended with them for ſin, <hi>Criſpe</hi> p. 303.</p>
            <p>Our Chriſt at his firſt viſible comming, bare the ſins of many. And for them that look for him, <hi>he ſhal appear the ſecond time without ſin unto ſalvation,</hi> Heb. 9.28. But the <hi>Antinomians</hi> Chriſt is expected to come to them once more to reign as an Emperour upon earth 1000. yeares before the day of judgment.</p>
            <p>Our Chriſt when he aſcended up on high, he gave gifts unto men, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.8.
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:111244:20"/>
               <hi>Of his fulneſſe wee receive grace for grace,</hi> John 1.16. But the <hi>Antinomians</hi> Chriſt gives no grace, but only comes perſonally into the ſoule, &amp; ſtil they remain dead ſtones and empty trunkes: ſee three of knowledge.</p>
            <p>Our Chriſt greatly deſires out beauty, being all glorious within, and our gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of wrought gold, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.11, 13. He ſaith our voyce is ſweete, and our countenance is comely, and is raviſht with one chaine of our neck, and ſaith, our love is better then wine, and our garments ſmel as Lebanon, <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.14, 4.9, 10, 11. But the <hi>Antinomians</hi> Chriſt neither beſtowes grace where it is wanting, nor delights in it where it is.</p>
            <p>Our Chriſt calls upon us to purge and cleanſe our ſelves from all filthineſſe of fleſh and ſpirit, <hi>perfecting holineſſe in the feare of God,</hi> 2 Cor. 7.1. But the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinomians</hi> Chriſt perſwades them from it, &amp; tells them that he wil do that himſelf.</p>
            <p>Our Chriſt is King of righteouſneſſe, aſwel as King of peace, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.2. <hi>He gives reſt to them that are heavy laden,</hi> Math. 11.28. <hi>But he gives no peace to the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked,</hi> Iſa. 57.21. But the <hi>Antinomians</hi> Chriſt brings peace to none but to the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in their corruption, unconverted before faith and calling.</p>
            <p>Our Chriſt by his Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>work out your own ſalvation with fear &amp; trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling,</hi> Phil. 1.12. And he ſaith, <hi>godly ſorrow worketh repentance to ſalvation,</hi> 2 cor. 7.10. And the end of our faith is the ſalvation of our ſoules, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.9. But the <hi>Antinomians</hi> Chriſt tells them that workes of ſanctification and holy walking is not the way to ſalvation: ſee <hi>Criſpe,</hi> page 69.20.</p>
            <p>Our Chriſt ſaith he loved his own that were in the world, and ſo he loved them unto the end, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 13.1. <hi>He wil never leave them nor forſake them,</hi> Heb. 13.5, 6. But the <hi>Antinomians</hi> Chriſt tells them that any ſad jealouſie concerning their preſent or future eſtate, puts them quite out of Chriſt: Dr. <hi>Criſp,</hi> p. 29.</p>
            <p>Our Chriſt will chide, rebuke, and threaten where he ſees cauſe, as wel as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2, 3. chap. But the <hi>Antinomians</hi> Chriſt is all for muſicke and flaggons of wine, <hi>page</hi> 80.31.</p>
            <p>Our Chriſt ſaith, <hi>the gate of heaven is ſtraight, and the way narrow, and few there be that find it,</hi> Math. 7. Therefore he bids us ſtrive: <hi>For many ſhall ſeeke to enter, &amp; ſhal not be able,</hi> Lu. 13.24. And he ſaid, how hardly ſhall a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ich man enter into the Kingdome of heeven, <hi>Mar.</hi> 10.23. <hi>The righteous ſhall ſcarcely be ſaved,</hi> 1 Pet. 4.18. We muſt through much tribulation enter into the Kingdome of God, <hi>Acts</hi> 14.22. But the <hi>Antinomians</hi> Chriſt tells them that the way to heaven is the moſt eaſie to bit of any in the world, and without any hardneſſe, they may make any progreſſe in it: <hi>Criſp,</hi> p. 83.18.</p>
            <p>Our Chriſt ſaith by his Apoſtle, that we are bleſſedd in the deed or in the way of doing, <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.25. But the Antinomians Chriſt tells them that they provoke God that ſeek for any bleſſing in the duties of holy walking: <hi>Criſp,</hi> p. 113.4.</p>
            <p>Our Chriſt ſaith by his <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> give all diligence to make your calling and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection ſure, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10. Bu the Antinomians Chriſt ſaith, if they take him up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his general tender, it is as good ſecurity as any in the world; yea, it is as good ſecurity as God can make them: ſee <hi>Criſp,</hi> p. 163.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:111244:20"/>
            <p> Our Chriſt cals the weary and heavy laden ſinners, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.28. And excludes thoſe that ſay Lord, Lord, and will not do his will, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.21. And caſts out him that came without his wedding garment, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12. But the Antinomians Chriſt ſends out his generall pardon for all theeves and whores without exception: ſee <hi>Criſp,</hi> p. 162. And if they wil but carnally take him, they may be theeves ſtill.</p>
            <p>Our Chriſt ſaith by his <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> that in every Nation, he that feareth God and worketh righteouſneſſe, is accepted of him, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.34. But the Antinomians Chriſt tells them that righteouſneſſe is that which puts a man a way from Chriſt, but ſinfulneſſe cannot: ſee Dr. <hi>Criſp.</hi> p. 149.</p>
            <p>Our Chriſt when he comes into the ſoule, changeth the will to imbrace him, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to receive him gladly. But the Antinomians Chriſt comes into the ſoule violently againſt the will to juſtifie him: As a Phyſician when he brings phyſick to his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, who ſhuts his teeth, and will not receive it, then he forceth his mouth open, and poures it downe his throate: ſee <hi>Criſpe,</hi> p. 151.15.</p>
            <p>Our Chriſt requires faith and repentance as conditions of the covenant, <hi>Mar.</hi> 5.36. <hi>Acts</hi> 8.38.16.31. Although theſe graces are his gifts: ſee <hi>Epheſ</hi> 2.8. <hi>Acts</hi> 5.31. But the Antinomians Chriſt tells them of a covenant without any conditions on their ſide, ſee Dr. <hi>Criſpe,</hi> p. 184.</p>
            <p>Our Chriſt loves righteouſneſſe and hates wickedneſſe, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 45.7. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 7.14.14 But the Antinomians Chriſt is kept off by righteouſneſſe, but not by ſin: ſee <hi>Criſp</hi> p. 249. He only hates righteouſneſſe, but he doth not hate ſin: witneſſe Mr. <hi>Wet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> Mr. <hi>George,</hi> Mr. <hi>Baines,</hi> and one more, affirmed againſt me and others on theſe grounds. Firſt, ſin is nothing, then how can God hate nothing. Secondly, ſin cannot hurt of it ſelfe, then why ſhould God hate it? Thirdly, ſin had its firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in God, then why ſhould God hate i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>? Fourthly, God created <hi>Adam</hi> a ſinner, which appears by his fall, and he ſaith, I create evill, then why ſhould he hate it? Fiftly, God is the author of all things, &amp; motions, therefore of ſin, &amp; why ſhould God hate it? Sixtly, God doth puniſh ſome for the glory of his juſtice, but not through any hatred of their ſin. This laſt reaſon affirmed by Mr. <hi>Banes,</hi> is now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voaked; Thus we ſee by what ſpirit theſe men are led, being aſhamed of his error.</p>
            <p>And now I have ſet before you the Chriſt of the Legaliſts, as they ſcornfully call us, and the Chriſt of the Antinomians. Now if it ſeem evil to you to ſerve the Lords Chriſt: chuſe you this day whom you will ſerve, whether the Antinomians fained Chriſt, or the true Chriſt of God. <hi>But as for me and my houſe, we wil ſerve the Lord,</hi> Joſh. 24.15. Halt no longer between two opinions: But if <hi>Baal</hi> be God follow him, but if the Lord be God follow him. And like <hi>Iehn,</hi> deſtroy the name of <hi>Baal</hi> out of Iſrael, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 10.28. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.17. Let us not put the Lord to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide the controverſie by fire from heaven, having his word the true Judge of all controverſies. Therefore <hi>whoſoever ſhall deſpiſe the Word ſhal be deſtroyed, and he that feareth the Commandement, ſhall be rewarded,</hi> prov. 13.13. Then be not led away with a fained Chriſt, but cleave to the Lords Chriſt, who is able to keep that which thou committeſt to his truſt, and to preſent thee faultleſſe and unrepro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:111244:21"/>in his ſight, <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 1.22. Now the Lord open thine eyes to ſee clearly into all theſe things that differ, and give thee grace to hold faſt that which is good, that thou maiſt be ſetled upon the true foundation, and there ſtand like mount Zion unmoveable for ever, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 125.1.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>The grounds of true Chriſtian Religion very neceſſary to build us on the true Rocke, Ieſus Chriſt.</head>
            <p>WHat is the true Chriſtian Religion? Anſw. It is the way to worſhip God through Jeſus Chriſt according to his own appoyntment. Firſt, it is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>the way of holineſſe,</hi> Iſa. 35.8. <hi>The new and living way,</hi> Heb. 10, 20. <hi>The narrow way,</hi> Mat. 7. <hi>the way everlaſting,</hi> Pſ. 139.14. And it muſt be in Chriſt. <hi>For God was in Chriſt reconciling the world to himſelfe,</hi> 2 Cor, 5.19. And according to his own appointment. For all thoſe Ceremonies &amp; Types of Chriſt were done as the Lord commanded <hi>Moſes</hi> Exo. 40. Therefore Chriſt as a ſon over his owne houſe, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.6. Spake <hi>as having authority, &amp; not as the Scribes</hi> Mat. 7.29. He ſaith, <hi>all power in heaven &amp; earth is givento him,</hi> ver. 28.18. Therefore he in his own name ſaith; Thus you have heard, but I ſay thus unto you, <hi>Math.</hi> 5.28.</p>
            <p>What are the parts of Religion to be known? <hi>Anſw.</hi> They are two. Firſt, is concerning truths to be known, that you may prove <hi>what is that good, acceptable, &amp; perfect will of God. Thou art a Iew &amp; knowſt his wil,</hi> Rom. 12.2, 3.18. The 2 concerning truths to be practiſed. <hi>Thy people ſhalbe willing in the day of thy power.</hi> Pſ. 110.3. If ye be willing &amp; obedient, ye ſhal eat the good of the land, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 3.19. Not he that ſaith Lord, Lord, <hi>but he that doth the will of my Father ſhalbe ſaved.</hi> Math. 7.21. The doer of the work ſhal be bleſſed in the deed, <hi>Iam</hi> 1.25. Let us hold faſt our profeſſion, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.14.10.23. <hi>He that holdeth out to the end ſhall be ſaved,</hi> Mark 13.13.</p>
            <p>What are the grounds of Religion? <hi>Anſw.</hi> They are two. Firſt, it is a right knowledge of God, as hee hath revealed himſelfe unto us in his word, concerning his unity of eſſence in the Trinity of perſons, his names and attributes, and works of Creation and providence. The ſecond maine ground of Religion, is a right knowledg of our ſelves, as we were firſt created righteous &amp; holy after Gods own Image, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.26. Since the fal none is righteous, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.10. Thirdly, as we are in the ſtate of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>race righteous in part, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3 12.15.16. Fourthly, in the ſtate of glory perfect in degrees as creatures. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12 23.</p>
            <p>How do you know there is a God? <hi>Anſw.</hi> I know there is a God by the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of conſcience, accuſing for ſin committed, and is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> were Gods deputy to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign and condemn us for it; which could not be but from a diſpleaſed God, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 17.8. John 8.9. Secondly from the comfortable refreſhing wee finde in our ſoules, when we are faithful and conſcionable in our obedience to the Lord, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.1. <hi>Acts</hi> 22.1. Thirdly I know there is a God by the frame of the world. By theſe v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ble things are clearly ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en <hi>his eternal power a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d God-head</hi> Rom. 1.20. The heavens could not make themſelves, becauſe they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not keep themſelves from periſhing, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102.25.26. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.10.11. Neither
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:111244:21"/>could the earth make it ſelf, nor the ſilly creatures that are in it could not make it, nor themſelves, they being all mortall and vanity: which plainly ſhews that their firſt beginning was by a divine power: Fourthly, all nations do acknowledg that there is a God, and that he ought to be worſhipped, although they cannot find out the true God, nor truely how to worſhip him. Fifthly, I know there is a God that provideth food for all creatures; and not onely ſo, but in making their food nouriſhing being of it ſelfe without life, yet without which they could not live; although our cloaths being void of heate, yet keepeth our bodies warm, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> could not be without a God; alſo that all the creatures being at variance, &amp; feed one upon another, &amp; yet every kind preſerved, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> could not be without a God.</p>
            <p>How many Gods be there? <hi>Anſ.</hi> There be many idol-gods, which are nothing in the world, and many that are called gods &amp; Lords. But to us there is but one God; <hi>There is none other Gods but one,</hi> Cor. 8.4, 5 6 In this God there are 3. real diſtinct Perſons, having ſubſiſtance in the ſame Eſſence; <hi>The Father, the Word, and the holy Ghoſt, and theſe three are one</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> John 5.7.</p>
            <p>How do you know the true God from all falſe gods? <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, the true God is known from all falſe gods, by the ſimple purity of his divine nature, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing void of all compoſition: the creatures are made up of the 4 Elements, but God is not ſo, and his eſſence is free from all diviſion or parts. We may not ſay this is one part of God, and that is another, as we ſay of the creature. Again, what is in God cannot be multiplyed or encreaſed, as to have more wiſedome or more ſtrength. Neither can there be any decreaſe of any thing that is in God. Againe, no accidents can cleave to him or adde any thing to his perfection: but what ever he is, he is the ſame eſſentially.</p>
            <p>But are not the three Perſons ſo many parts of his God-head? <hi>Anſw.</hi> No, the Father is God, the Son is God, &amp; the holy Ghoſt is God; and yet not three Gods, but one God. This Trinity in Unity, and Unity in Trinity is a holy miſtery, and is rather to be religiouſly adored by faith, then curiouſly ſearched by reaſon, further then God hath revealed in his word. The mean time let us neither confound the Perſons, nor divide the ſubſtance of his perfect Eſſence.</p>
            <p>Secondly, we may know the true God from all falſe gods by this, that he is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite; Firſt, in his unmeaſurable greatneſſe. <hi>Great is the Lord, and greatly to be praiſed, and his greatneſſe is unſearchable,</hi> Pſal. 145.3. <hi>Behold God is great, and we know him not,</hi> Job 36.26. <hi>Behold heaven, and the heaven of heavens cannot containe thee,</hi> 2 Chr. 6 18. He is omnipreſent in all places. Whither ſhall I goe from thy preſence? <hi>To heaven, thou art there, to hell, thou art there, to the bottom of the ſea thou art there,</hi> Pſ. 139.7 8.9. But no other God is ſo. Secondly, God is infinite in his unmeaſurable age and time of his being, there was none before him, nor ſhal e any after him. <hi>He is</hi> Alpha <hi>&amp;</hi> Omega, <hi>the firſt and the laſt.</hi> Rev. 1.8. <hi>His days cannot be ſearchen out</hi> Job 36.26. <hi>Thy yea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es have no end,</hi> Pſa. 202.27. <hi>From everlaſting to everlaſting thou art God,</hi> Pſal 90.2. <hi>The Lord is the true God, he is the living God, and an everlaſting King,</hi> Jer. 10.10. But no other God is ſo.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:111244:22"/>
            <p> Thirdly, God is infinite in his wiſedome &amp; underſtanding. <hi>Oh the depth of the riches both of the wiſedome and knowledg of God; how unſearchable are his judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and his wayes paſt finding out</hi> Rom. 11.33. <hi>Great is the Lord, his under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding is infinite,</hi> Pſa. 147.5. <hi>The Lord knows the hearts of men,</hi> Pſal. 94.11. <hi>He ſeeth not as man ſeeth, he looketh on the heart,</hi> 1 Sam. 16.7. <hi>Hee knowes all things,</hi> John 21.17. <hi>Thine eyes are open upon all the wayes of the ſons of men,</hi> Jer. 32.19. <hi>All things are naked and open unto the eyes of him with whom wee have to do,</hi> Heb. 4.13. <hi>Yea the darkneſſe hideth not from thee, but the night ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth as the day, the darkneſſe and the light are both alike unto thee,</hi> Pſal. 139.12. But thus no other God can do.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, God is infinite in this, that he is unchangeable or immutable. The fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite creatures change daily; <hi>But the Lord is the ſame yeſterday, to day, and for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,</hi> Heb. 13.8. I am the Lord, I change not, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.6. <hi>With him there is no va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riableneſſe not ſhadow of turning,</hi> Jam. 1.17. <hi>The heavens wax old as a garment, and as a veſture ſhalbe changed. But thou art the ſame for ever,</hi> Pſ. 102.27. Heb. 1.12. God ſaid to <hi>Moſes, I am that I am,</hi> Exo. 3.14. <hi>That men may know that thou whoſe name alone is</hi> Jehovah, <hi>art the moſt high over all the earth,</hi> Pſal. 83.18. Hee hath his being, of and from himſelfe, being alone Independant, who gives ceing to all his promiſes, &amp; all creatures have their being from him. <hi>In him we live, move, and have our being; he giveth to all life and breath, and all things,</hi> Acts 17.25.28. Therefore he alone is unchangeable, but all other Gods are va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, <hi>Zech.</hi> 10.2.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, God is infinite in his righteouſneſſe and holineſſe? The Judge of all the earth will do right, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.25. The Almighty will nor pervert judgement, he accepteth not the perſons of Princes, nor regardeth the rich more then the poore, for they are all the work of his hands, <hi>Iob</hi> 34.12.19. And his holineſſe is ſuch, that cannot be defiled with ſin, although he is in all places where ſin is committed, and hath a hand in all finfull actions. The hand that is ſtretched out to ſlay ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, is moved by the Lord, and the tongue that blaſphemes his holy Name is mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by him. <hi>For in him we live, move, and have our being,</hi> Acts 17.28. <hi>Yet he is righteous in all his wayes, and holy in all his works,</hi> Pſal. 145.17. <hi>His work is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, for all his wayes are judgment: a God of truth without iniquity, juſt &amp; true is hee,</hi> Deut. 32.4. Hee wil by no meanes cleare the guilty, <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.7. Nor ſpare his owne Son when our ſins were imputed to him, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.32. <hi>Who is able to ſtand before this holy Lord God?</hi> 1 Sam. 6.20. The Angels cover their faces, as not being able to behold the glory of his holineſſe; and they cover their feet, being aſhamed that he ſhould behold their infirmity. And they cry out one to another, ſaying, holy, holy, holy, Lord of Hoſts, the whole earth is full of thy glory. And the Prophet cryes out, ſaying, <hi>Woe is me, for I am undone, becauſe I am a man of unclean lips, and I dwel in the middeſt of a people of uncleane lips. For mine eyes have ſeen the King, the Lord of Hoſt,</hi> Iſa. 6.2.3.5. <hi>For who among the Gods is like unto thee, glorious in holineſſe,</hi> Exod. 15.11.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:111244:22"/>
            <p> Sixtly, God is infinite in power, he can do more then he wil do, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.9. Is any thing too hard for the Lord, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.14. <hi>Ier.</hi> 32.17. <hi>Who hath reſiſted his will,</hi> Rom. 9.19. <hi>Our God is in the heaven, and hath done whatſoever he pleaſed,</hi> Pſal. 115.3.135.6. Our God in fixe dayes made the heavens, the earth, the ſea, and all the creatures in them, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. But thoſe gods that have not made the heavens and the earth, even they ſhal periſh from the earth, and from under thoſe heavens. But our God hath made the earth by his power, <hi>he eſtabliſhed the world by his wiſedome, and hath ſtretched out the heavens by his diſcretion,</hi> Ier. 10.11, 12. Then let us not halt between two opinions. When the people ſaw his power, they fell on their faces, and ſaid, <hi>the Lord he is the God, the Lord he it the God,</hi> 1 Kings 18.21.39.</p>
            <p>Of what did the Lord make the world, and by what meanes is it continued and upheld? <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Lord made all things of nothing. <hi>Things that are ſeen, were made of things which do not appeare,</hi> Hebr. 11.3. <hi>And he upholdeth all things by the word of his power,</hi> Heb. 1.3. For the earth hangeth upon no thing, <hi>Iob</hi> 26.7.</p>
            <p>But was man made of nothing? <hi>Anſw.</hi> The firſt matter was made of nothing, being the earth and the reſt of the Elements. And then the Lord God formed the body of man of the duſt of the ground, and breathed into his noſtrills the breath of life, <hi>and man became a living ſoule,</hi> Gen. 2.7.</p>
            <p>But had not the woman alſo a ſoule given to her? <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yes, <hi>Hannah pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out her ſoule before the Lord,</hi> 1 Sam. 1.15. And ſaith <hi>Mary,</hi> my ſoule doth magnifie the Lord, and my ſpirit rejoyceth in God my Saviour, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.46, 47. And the Lord opened <hi>Lidia's</hi> heart that ſhe attended unto thoſe things that were ſpoken by <hi>Paul,</hi> Acts 16.14. And <hi>Mary</hi> kept the ſayings of Chriſt in her heart, <hi>Luke</hi> 2.19.51.</p>
            <p>In what eſtate or condition was man created? <hi>Anſw.</hi> In a bleſſed eſtate: <hi>In the image and likeneſſe of God which conſiſted in knowledge,</hi> Col. 3 10. <hi>In righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe and true holineſſe,</hi> Epheſ 4.24. And in his ſoveraignty over all the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures here below, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1:28: Pſalm 8.6, 7, 8.</p>
            <p>Wherefore did God create all things? <hi>Anſw.</hi> God made all things for his own glory. <hi>The heavens declare the glory of God, and the earth ſheweth forth his han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy worke,</hi> Pſ. 19:1: The Lord made all thing, for himſelfe, <hi>Pro.</hi> 16.4.</p>
            <p>In what did God require that <hi>Adam</hi> ſhould glorifie him? <hi>Anſw.</hi> In fulfilling a Covenant of workes. <hi>Ye ſhal keep my ſtatutes and my judgements,</hi> (which if a man do) <hi>he ſhal live in them; I am the Lord,</hi> Levit. 18 y. Gal. 3.12.</p>
            <p>Had <hi>Adam</hi> power to fulfill that Covenant of works? <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yes, for he then had the morall law written in his heart, for ſome remainders of it are yet left in man by nature. The Gentiles which have not the written law, do by nature the things contained in the law, which ſhew the worke of the law written in their hearts, Rom. 2.14, 15.</p>
            <p>What is the ſum of the morall law? <hi>Anſw.</hi> The ten Commandements which are called the tables of the Covenant, <hi>Deut.</hi> 9.9.11. In which are contained all duties both to God and man. For what doth the Lord thy God require of thee,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:111244:23"/>but to feare the Lord thy God, to walk in all his wayes, and to love him, and to fear the Lord thy God with all thy heart &amp; with all thy ſoule, to keep the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements of the Lord and his ſtatutes which I command thee this day for thy good, <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.12, 13.</p>
            <p>What is the ſum of the firſt Commandement? <hi>Anſw.</hi> It forbids the having of more gods then one, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.6. Alſo it forbids to chuſe or to ſet up any thing for our God that is not God, thou ſhalt have no other god. Alſo it commands us to take the Lord for our God. Chuſe you whom you will ſerve; <hi>I and my houſe will ſerve the Lord,</hi> Joſh. 24.15. And to cleave unto him, <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>0. Thou haſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouched the Lord this day to be thy God, <hi>Deut.</hi> 26.17, 18.</p>
            <p>What is the ſum of the ſecond Commandement? <hi>Anſw.</hi> It forbids al true divine worſhip to be given to any falſe god; Thou ſhalt not bow down to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> nor wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip them. And it forbids all falſe worſhip to be given to him in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>They wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip me, teaching for doctrine, the precepts of men,</hi> Mar. 15.9. Being no more vain Oblations. Alſo it commands all true divine worſhip to be given to the true God. <hi>Thou ſhalt worſhip the Lord thy God, &amp; him only ſhalt thou ſerve,</hi> Mat. 4.10.</p>
            <p>What is the ſum of the third Commandement? <hi>Anſw.</hi> It forbids all unreverent ſpeaking of the name of God or of his Attributes, or ſwearing by him upon ſlight occaſions; Thou ſhalt not take the name of the Lord thy God in vain. Alſo it for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids al unreverent corriage toward the Lord in the way of his worſhip, in his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, or towards the works of his providence. Alſo it commands all reverent ſpeaking of the name and attributes of God. <hi>For holy and reverend is his Name,</hi> Pſ. 111.9. As alſo towards him in his Ordinances. <hi>God is greatly to be feared in the aſſembly of the Saints, &amp; to be had in reverence of all that are about him,</hi> Pſ. 89.7. Alſo in the works of God; <hi>When I conſider the heavens, the workes of thy hands, the Sun, Moon, and Stars which thou haſt ordained. What is man that thou art mindful of him?</hi> Pſal. 8.3, 4.</p>
            <p>What is the ſum of the fourth Commandement? <hi>Anſw.</hi> The ſum of the fourth Commandement reſpects the time when God will chiefly be worſhipped, ſerved, honoured, and reverenced, and that is on his owne day by him appoynted for the ſame uſe, and therfore it is called the Lords day. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.10. The Sabbath of the Lord thy God ſanctified &amp; ſet apart for that uſe; So that we muſt neither rob God of his day, or any part of it to employ it about any other occaſions, not minding our own pleaſures, nor ſpeaking our own words, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59.13. Alſo it forbids us to appoynt any days for divine worſhip, to dedicate them to the Lord, except it bee dayes of humiliation or thankſ-giving to remove ſome judgement, or to ſeek ſome mercy, or to render prayſe for ſome bleſſing received, and for ſome certaine time, and then to return to their firſt Inſtitution, which was to labour 6. dayes. Thus we muſt chuſe the true God, and worſhip him with true worſhip and reverence in his owne time. And this is the ſum of our duty to the Lord immediatly as it is contained in the four firſt Commandements, being the firſt Table of the law.</p>
            <p>What is the ſum of the fifth Commandement?</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:111244:23"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It forbids all negligence and diſobedience to Magiſtrates or Parents, or any that the Lord hath put in authority over us; ſuch as thoſe filthy drae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers that deſpiſe dominion, and ſpeak evil of dignities <hi>Jud.</hi> 8. alſo it commands us to give them vivell honour and reverence, and obedience; ſee <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.1. <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.2.1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.1, 2.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the ſumme of the ſixth Commandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It forbids all injuries done to the bodies or ſoules of others, as en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, hatred, malice, or ſtripes, or murder it ſelfe, <hi>thou ſhalt not kill:</hi> alſo it commands all duties of love and charity which tend to their preſervation ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of body or ſoule.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the ſumme of the ſeventh Commandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It forbids all unchaſt thoughts tending to adultery and adultery it ſelfe, and all idle words and geſtures tending that way, <hi>let not fornication be ence named among you, as becommeth Saints.</hi> Eph. 5.3. alſo it commands to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void all ſuſpected places and perſons, abſtain from all appearance of evil 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.22. <hi>Prov.</hi> 5.8.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the ſumme of the eighth Commandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It forbids all fraud, or deceit, or ſtealing, or any wrong to others in their eſtate. <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſteale;</hi> alſo it commands all duties of neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood and friendſhip that may preſerve or increaſe it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the ſumme of the ninth Commandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I it forbids all reproaches and ſcandals unjuſtly caſt upon them, and ſhould neither raiſe a falſe report againſt them, <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.1. nor take up a falſe report raiſed by others, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15.3. <hi>but as the north-wind drives away raine, ſo doth an angry countenance a backbiting tongue,</hi> Prov. 25.23. alſo it commands all duties of love, for love ſuffers long and is kind, charity envieth not, vanteth not it ſelfe, is not puffed up, doth not behave it ſelf unſeemly, ſeeketh not her owne, is not eaſily provoked, thinketh no evill, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.4, 5.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the ſumme of the tenth Commandement?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It forbids the riſing of ſinfull luſts to any of the forenamed evils, and it commands to ſuppreſſe thoſe ſinfull luſts in their firſt riſings before conſent be given to them; now whereas all the Commandements forbid luſting with conſent, this forbids it before conſent, and commands to ſuppreſſe it before conſent, this is the ſumme of the morrall law, the covenant of works.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>How did the Lord try mans obedience to that covenant of works?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> By prohibiting onely one tree in the Garden, ſaying, <hi>of the tree of Knowledge of good and evill thou ſhalt not eat of it, for in the day thou eateſt thereof thou ſhalt ſurely dye,</hi> Gen. 2.17.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>When</hi> Adam <hi>was permitted to eat of all the reſt, would not he refraine that one at Gods command?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:111244:24"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>A.</hi> No, although he had power ſufficient given to him whereby he might have ſtood, yet in caſe <hi>Adam</hi> loſt that ability, all new ſupplies were ſhut up from him; it is true, he had a great portion of grace given to him into his own hands to keep, but no ſupportance from the Lord to keep him from falling, and he being a mutable creature could not but fall and nothing is immutable but God alone, and Satan in the ſerpent beguiled them, ſaying, <hi>you ſhall not dye, but yee ſhall be as Gods knowing good and evill, and they ſaw the tree was good for food and pleaſant to the eye, and a tree to be deſired to make one wiſe, ſo they did both eat of it and fell together,</hi> Gen. 3.4.6.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Why did not God ſupport them from falling?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> That man might ſee his weakneſſe, and that God might make knowne what he had decreed from all eternity, and for the honour of his juſtice and mercy in the execution of his decrees in redeeming ſome and leaving others in that miſerable condition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the ſtate of all men ſince the fall of Adam?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> We have all loſt our righteouſneſſe, ſo that now there is none righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, no not one, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.10. and we have loſt our holineſſe, <hi>we are all as an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane thing,</hi> Iſa. 64.6. and we have loſt our knowledge, ſo that every man now is bruitiſh in his knowledge. <hi>Jer.</hi> 10.14. having the underſtanding darkned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alienated from the life of God through the ignorance that is in them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the blindneſſe of their heart, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.18. and we have loſt the ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty over the creatures here below; will the Unicorne now be willing to ſerve thee? wilt thou truſt him becauſe his ſtrength is great? wilt thou leave thy labour to him? wilt thou beleeve that he will being home thy ſeed and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it into thy Barn or doth the Eagle fly at thy command? <hi>Job</hi> 39.9.11, 12. Thus we have loſt all our happineſſe wherein we were created, and not onely ſo but we are children of wrath, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.2. and ſlaves of Satan led captive at his will, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.6. and under the curſe, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.10: and lyable both to a corporal, ſpirituall and eternall death, Rom. 5.12. 1 Cor. 15.22.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Was that actuall ſinne of</hi> Adam <hi>our actuall ſinne as ſome would have it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No; for by one mans ſinne death entred into the world and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of one many be dead, by one that ſinned, for the judgement was by one to condemnation, for by one mans offence death reigned by one, and by the offence of one judgement came upon all men to condemnation, and by one mans diſobedience many were made ſinners. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12.15, 16, 17, 18, 19.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then how came that ſinne of</hi> Adam <hi>to be ours if we did not then actually com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is ours potentially, we being all then in his loynes as the fruit is in the body of the tree, and alſo being begotten and borne by thoſe polluted parents, we receive originall defilement from them, for <hi>Adam</hi> being defiled begat his
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:111244:24"/>children in his owne likeneſſe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 5.3. and ſo his defilement ſpread over all men, as when bondſlaves had children they were all borne ſlaves by the law of God, <hi>Ex.</hi> 21.4. and by mans law, the fathers treaſon cuts off his poſterity from his inheritance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But cannot we recover our ſelves out of this miſerable condition?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No; we cannot think one good thought as of our ſelves, <hi>all our ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency is of God.</hi> 2 Cor. 3.5. <hi>it is God that worketh in us both to will and to doe of his own good pleaſure,</hi> Phil. 2.13. <hi>we are all dead in trespaſſes and ſinnes,</hi> Eph. 2.1. none of them can by any meanes redeeme his brother nor give to God a ranſome for him, for the redemption of the ſoule is precious and ceaſeth for ever, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 49.7, 8. ſo that man hath neither power nor will to help himſelfe but is dead in ſinne, <hi>O Iſrael thou haſt destroyed thy ſelfe, but in me is thy help,</hi> Hoſea 13.9.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What meanes hath God appointed and decreed to help us out of this damnable eſtate?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By Jeſus Chriſt the eternall Sonne of God, he tooke our nature upon him that ſo he might be a fit mediator between God and man, <hi>the Word was made fleſh and dwelt among us</hi> Ioh. 1.14. he took not on him the nature of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels but he took on him the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> wherefore it behooved him to be made like unto his brethren, that he might be a mercifull and a faithfull high Prieſt in all things pertaining to God, to make reconciliation for the ſins of the people, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.16.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherefore muſt our Redeemer be both God and man?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> He was man to dye and ſuffer in that nature that had ſinned, and he was God, that he might overcome death and riſe againe, which none could doe but God alone: againe, he muſt be God and man to ſanctifie that nature that had ſinned and was defiled with it, and he was God, that ſo by the worthineſſe of his perſon, he may bring a ſatisfaction ſufficient to reconcile an offended God, for in that he dyed for us, it was a thouſand times more in value, then if all men and Angels had dyed eternally for one poore ſinner, for it is unpoſſible that creatures ſhould bring a ſatisfaction worthy of the acceptation, and ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to appeaſe the wrath of their Creator.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But if our Mediator was both God and man, then he muſt be two perſons, but how can that be?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Although he be both God and man, yet he is not two, but one Chriſt, as one body and ſoule make but one man; neither are they one by turning the God-head into fleſh but by taking the man-hood into God, as the miſletow lives in the Oake without any rooting ſo is the humarity in the God-head by a hupaſtacicall union unconceiveable unto us, neither may we without dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, ſearch too farre into this holy miſtery.</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:111244:25"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>In what manner did God the father make that new covenant with God the ſonne, touching our ſalvation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The Father promiſed to give unto chriſt his Son all the elect as they fall in the ſeverall ages of the world, upon condition, that the Sonne will give him a full ſatisfaction for their ranſome; hereupon ſayth the Sonne, <hi>O father deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them from going downe into the pit, for I have found a ranſome,</hi> Iob 33.24. upon this they concluded, and the ſonne of man came not to be miniſtred unto, but to miniſter and to give his life a ranſome for many, <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.28. for ſayth <hi>Iohn, thou haſt given him power over all fleſh, to give eternall life to as many as thou haſt given him,</hi> Ioh. 17.2. ſo the father ſet the ſonne a day to pay the ranſome, and took his word to performe it, and gave him all the elect that fell in the times before his comming in the fleſh, in the time of their being; and now chriſt hath actually payd the ranſome, he takes his fathers word for all the reſt of the elect that fall in the ſeverall ages of the world, ſince the debt was actually payed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then hath Chriſt payed this ranſome, and in his humanity dyed for his people?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes; he was wounded for our tranſgreſſions, he was bruiſed for our iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties the chaſtiſement of our peace was upon him, and with his ſtripes we are healed <hi>Iſa.</hi> 52.5. <hi>chriſt hath once ſuffered, the juſt for the unjuſt, that he might bring us to God, being put to death in the fleſh, but quickned by the spirit,</hi> 1 Pet. 3.18. <hi>who did no ſinne, neither was guile found in his mouth; who when he was reviled reviled not again; when he ſuffered he threatned not, but committed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to him that judgeth righteouſly, who his owne ſelfe bare our ſinnes in his owne body on the tree, that we being dead to ſinne ſhould live unto righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, by whoſe ſtripes ye are healed,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.22, 23, 24. thus chriſt hath paſſive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuffered all the penalty of the law to free us from the curſe and penalty of it, and to ſanctifie both afflictions and death unto us; <hi>O death where is thy ſting, O grave where is thy victory! the sting of death is ſinne, but thankes be to God which hath given us victory through our Lord Ieſus chriſt,</hi> 1 cor. 15.55 56.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To what uſe ſerveth the active obedience of chriſt to the law of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It ſerveth to ſanctifie all our diſobedience and failings in the perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of holy duties, ſo that now a willing mind is accepted according to that a man hath, 2 <hi>cor.</hi> 8.12. row Chriſt takes notice when the ſpirit is willing, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the fleſh be weak, Mat. 26.41. for our Saviour hath performed per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect obedience to the law of Gad for us, it was his meat and drinke to doe his Fathers will, Iohn 4.32.34. he ſayth, <hi>I doe alwayes thoſe things that pleaſe him,</hi> Iohn 8.29. <hi>I ſeeke not mine owne will, but the will of him that ſent me,</hi>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:111244:25"/>Iohn 4.30.7.16. as by the diſobedience of one many were made ſinners, ſo by the obedience of one many were made righteous, <hi>Romans</hi> 5.19.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But did Chriſt obey or ſuffer for himſelfe as ſome would have it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No; for although his humane nature was a creaturne, yet being u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited to the ſecond perſon, and ſo making one Chriſt, there was no obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience due from himſelfe to the law, neither came he by the ordinary way of mankind into the world, therefore free from that law that <hi>Adam</hi> was bound unto with all his poſterity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But did we actually doe all that which chriſt did in our nature as well as he, as ſome would have it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No; the gift by grace is by one man, Ieſus Chriſt, and by him hath abounded to many, and righteouſneſſe ſhall reigne in life by one Ieſus chriſt; even ſo by the righteouſneſſe of one, the free gift came upon all to juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of life; <hi>by the obedience of one ſhall many be made righteous,</hi> rom. 5.15, 16, 17, 18, 19. hence I conclude, that we did not act in Chriſts perſon as well as himſelfe, ſaying, it was a common lumpe of all mankind that chriſt obeyed and ſuffered in; we for him, as well as he for us, and he for himſelfe as well as for us; This is Antinomian blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But if we did not act as well as chriſt, how comes his righteouſneſſe to be ours?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By imputation; for as he is a bleſſed man to whom the Lord will not impute ſinne, <hi>rom.</hi> 4.8. ſo he is a bleſſed man unto whom God will impute righteouſneſſe without workes, <hi>rom.</hi> 4 6. now as <hi>Adams</hi> ſinne is imputed to all in <hi>Adams</hi> nature ſo the ſecond <hi>Adams</hi> righteouſneſſe is imputed to all that are in him by greace; <hi>to him that worketh not, but beleeveth on him that justifieth the ungodly, by faith instrumentally it is coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trd for righteouſneſſe,</hi> rom. 4.5.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then did chriſt alone in his owne perſon doe all the workes of our redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yes; <hi>he looked and ſaw there was none to helpe, therefore his owne arme brought ſalvation, and his righteouſneſſe it ſustained him,</hi> Iſaiah 59.16.6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.5. <hi>neither is there ſalvation in any other; there is none other other name given under Heaven among men whereby we muſt be ſaved,</hi> Acts 4.12. <hi>he trod the Wine-preſſe alone, and there was none with him,</hi> Iſaiah 63.3. <hi>he by himſelfe purged our ſinnes,</hi> Hebr. 1.3. <hi>and he wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed away our ſinnes in his owne blood,</hi> revel. 1.7. <hi>he is the Lambe of God, that taketh away the ſinnes of the word,</hi> Iohn 1.29.</p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:111244:26"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Did Chriſt dye for all men without exception?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No; for Chriſt would not ſo much as pray for the world, much leſſe would he ſpill his blood for them, but the firſt is true, therefore not the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.9. againe, if Chriſt had dyed for them and they not ſaved, either the Father brake Covenant, and did not give him all that he bought of him, or elſe the world, and the divell, and ſinne were too ſtrong both for the father that have them, and the ſonne that bought them, which were no other then blaſphemy to think.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>How doe you know that Chriſt dyed for you?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A. The good Sbe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heard gave his life for the ſheep,</hi> Joh. 10.11. and I know my ſelfe to be one of his ſheep, for I know his voyce, <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.4. both the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret voyce of his ſpirit and the publike voyce of his word, when I am charged to let the word of Chriſt dwell in me richly, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.16. <hi>when I turne aſide to the right hand or to the left, I ſtill heare his voyce ſaying unto me, this is the way walk in it,</hi> Iſa. 30.21. <hi>and I know it is the voyce of my beloved that knocketh ſaying open to me my ſister</hi> cant. 5.2. <hi>becauſe he leadeth me into al truth &amp; makes me ſee an excellency in him above all other.</hi> Cant. 5.9.10, 11, 12 13, 14, 15, 16. Pſal. 45.2. then ſayth Chriſt, <hi>I know my ſheep and I am knowne of mine.</hi> Joh. 10.14. and they will eſteeme of all things elſe but as dung, aad droſſe, and loſſe, for the excellent knowledge of Chriſt, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.78.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By what other mark doe you know that you are one of the ſheep of Chriſt for which he dyed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The ſheep of Chriſt doe not onely know his voyce and delight in hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it, but in obeying it and follownig him, <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.4.27. they will walke as Chriſt walked, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.6. and they will learne of him that is meek and lowly in heart, and they ſhall find reſt for their ſoules, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.29. and as he ſayd, <hi>it as my meat and drink to doe the will of him that ſent me, and to ſiniſh his worke, and he did alwaies thoſe things that pleaſed him.</hi> Joh. 4.34.8.29. and concerning his ſurferings, he ſayd. <hi>I lay downe my life. no man taketh it from me,</hi> Joh. 10.17, 18 <hi>the cup that my father hath given me, ſhall I not drinke it?</hi> Iohn 18.4.11. Chriſt ſuffered, leaveng us an example that we ſhould follow his ſteps, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.21. <hi>to you it is given in the behalfe of Chriſt, not onely to beleeve on him, but to ſuffer for his ſake,</hi> Phil. 1.29. <hi>they which follow the Lamb whitherſoever he go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, theſe were redeemed from among men.</hi> Rev. 14.4.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What other reaſons have you to prove that Chriſt dyed for you?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Chriſt loved the church and gave himſelfe for it, that he might ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie and cleanſe it with the waſhing of water by the word <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.25.26. and the church is his body, <hi>chap.</hi> 1.22, 23. for as the body is one and hath many mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, ſo alſo is chriſt, 1 <hi>cor.</hi> 12.12.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But how doe you know your ſelfe to be a living member of chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:111244:26"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>A.</hi> As all our members are acted and moved by the ſoule or ſpirit that is in us, ſo are alll the members of chriſt by his ſpirit, for by one ſpirit we are all baptized into one body, whether we be Iewes or Gentiles, bond or free, and have been all made to drink into one ſpirit, 1 <hi>cor.</hi> 12.13. and our body dyes when the ſoule is gone; but ſayth <hi>Paul, ye are not in the fleſh but in the spirit, if ſo be that the ſpirit of God dwel in you, now if any man have not the ſpirit of chriſt he is none of his,</hi> rom. 8.9. and ſo if on of our members ſuffer, all the members ſuffer with it, or if one member be honoured all the members rejoyce with it, if we doe ſo then we are the body of Chriſt, and members in particular, 1 <hi>cor.</hi> 12.26, 27. <hi>hereby we perceive the love of God, becauſe he layd downe his life for us, and we ought to lay downe our lives for the brethren,</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.16.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVhat are the conditions between God and his reople in the new covenant, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the covenant of grace?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> God will ſay, <hi>it is my people,</hi> and they ſhall ſay, <hi>the Lord is my God Zech.</hi> 13.9. that is, God makes many gracious promiſes unto us, and we by faith ſhall receive and apply them to our ſelves; yea, that faith on our part where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the covenant is made to us, it alſo is within the promiſe made on Gods part, they ſhall ſay, <hi>the Lord is my God.</hi> the covenant it ſelfe is a promiſe, <hi>I will make an everlasting covenant with them,</hi> and the conditions on our part are all within that promiſe, <hi>I will put my feare in their hearts that they ſhall not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from me,</hi> beſides all other promiſes on Gods part that are included in that covenant, for ſayth the Lord, <hi>I will bring upon them all the good that I have promiſed them,</hi> Ier. 31.40 41. 42. Heb. 8.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But is not the righteouſneſſe of chriſt imputed to us for our justification, before <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat we have faith?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> No; for our perſons muſt be united to Chriſt by faith, as Thomas be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving, ſayd, <hi>my Lord and my God,</hi> Iohn 20.27, 28. ſo we come to have a true right and title to the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, for as we were all in the loynes of <hi>Adam</hi> by nature, when God made that covenant of works with him and all his Poſterity, ſo none hath right to the righteouſneſſe of the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> till he be cut off from the old <hi>Adam,</hi> and by faith grafted into Ieſus Chriſt, and ſo we come to partake of the root and fatneſſe of the true Olive tree, <hi>rom.</hi> 11.17.17.24.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>How is Jeſus chriſt tendred in the Ghspell?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The Angell ſayd unto them, <hi>feare not, for behold I bring you good ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dengs of great joy, which ſhall be to all people, for unto you is borne this day in the city of</hi> David <hi>a Saviour, which is Chriſt the Lord,</hi> Luk. 2.10.11. ſayth the Lord <hi>I will give thee for a covenant of the people, to establiſh the earth to cauſe to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit the deſolate heritages, that thou mayeſt ſay to the priſoners goe forth,</hi> Iſa. 49.8, 9.</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:111244:27"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>What is requ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>red of them to whom he is thus tendered? A.</hi> Onely beleeve, Mar. 5.36. beleeve in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and thou ſhalt be ſaved, Acts 16.31. <hi>Whoſoever beleeveth on him, ſhall not periſh, but have everlasting life,</hi> John 3.16.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is that faith that gives us right to Chriſt, and a true title to all his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits in the worke of our redemption? A.</hi> It is a ſaving faith, and not a hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call faith, ſuch as the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> ſpeakes of, <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.19. and it is a living faith and not a dead faith, <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.17. I live by faith in the Sonne of God, who gave himſelfe for me, Gal. 2.20. and it is called a juſtifying faith, not for the worthineſſe of it, as being an excellent grace of God, but as an inſtrument applying Chriſts righteouſneſſe for our juſtification.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>How came we by this faith? and how is it wrought in us? A.</hi> Faith is the gift of God, Eph. 2.8. and it is wrought in us by his ſpirit: thou haſt wrought all our workes in us Iſa. 26.12. Phil. 2.13. the inſtrumentall meanes that the ſpirit of God, for the moſt part, uſeth, is the Preaching of the Word: ſo then Faith cometh by hearing the word preached, Rom. 10.14.17.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What call you the Word of God? A.</hi> The two Teſtaments: the firſt is from the beginning of <hi>Geneſis</hi> to the end of he propheſie of <hi>Malachy;</hi> this is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the old Teſtament: and from the firſt of <hi>Matthew</hi> to the laſt of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation is called the new Teſtament.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>How doe you prove theſe two Testaments to be the Word of God? A.</hi> Firſt, becauſe of the true relating of things to come, and the accompliſhment of them at the time appointed, which none could doe but he that knowes all things both paſt, and to come. Secondly, they lay open the particular and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret thoughts and luſts of the heart, which ſheweth that they are the words of him in whoſe ſight all things are naked and open, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.12.13. Thirdly, they command all duties of piety, equity and ſobriety, and forbiddeth all vice in ſuch a ſort, that all the writings of men though layd together, could not d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e. Fourthly, they diſcover a ſtate of damnation to man and conclude him in it, and they reveale a ſure way of ſalvation, which never could enter into mans heart, but as it was revealed by the ſpirit of God, which found and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained that way. Fiftly, it is a word of power, to the pulling down of ſtrong holds, and caſting downe imaginations and every high thing that exalts it ſelf, and every thought to the obedience of Chriſt, 2 <hi>cor.</hi> 10.4, 5. Sixtly, the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall conſent and agreement it hath, though pend by divers, and at ſundry time, which argueth, <hi>that holy men spake as they were moved by the holy Ghoſt,</hi> 2 Pet. 2.21.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What part of this word of God is the moſt concerned in the covenant of grace? A.</hi> In the promiſes of the Goſpell, and fulfilled in the perſon of Chriſt, both in his active and paſſive obedience, as I ſayd before, and working faith and all other graces in his people.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:111244:27"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>But are chriſtians that ore entred into this new covenant contained in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, are they I ſay freed from the old covenant contained in the law? A.</hi> They are freed from the curſe and penalty of the law, and from the legall fulfilling of it, to that end which <hi>Adam</hi> was bound to doe it in the time of innocency, for although the ten Commandements publiſhed at Mount <hi>Sina<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> were the ſame for ſubſtance that was in <hi>Adams</hi> heart before the fall; yet the manner of <hi>Adams</hi> obedience and theirs differ much: thus <hi>Adam</hi> was then bound to a covenant of workes, but they ſtand as a people redeemed not onely from <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rao<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> bondage, but from the bondage of ſin and ſatan, Gods wrath and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, figured out by that from <hi>Aegypt</hi> in the preface; againe, <hi>Adam</hi> was to ſtand by his perfect obedience to it, or to fall if he failed in the leaſt title; but the law at Mount <hi>Sinai</hi> was a rule to ſquare their obedience by, but the penalty is taken off, as I ſayd before, and they and we are bound to doe our ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt endeavour to obey it, although we can never legally fulfill it, but evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gellically as we are in Chriſt, to teſtifie our thankfulneſſe and obedience to our Redeemer, 1 <hi>cor.</hi> 6.19, 20.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What are the maine differences between the covenant of workes, and the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of grace? A.</hi> The firſt covenant was of mans workes, the ſecond of Gods grace; againe, the firſt was made to <hi>Adam,</hi> and in him to all his poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; the ſecond was made with Chriſt, and ſo in him for all the elect; called the ſeed of the woman, but not with the ſeed of the ſerpent, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. againe, the firſt ſtood upon mans righteouſneſſe, the ſecond upon the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, made ours by imputation; againe, the firſt was ſoon broken, ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding upon the mutability of mans will, but the ſecond ſtands upon a ſure foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, being Gods unchangeable will, and ſo never can be broken; for ſayth the Lord, <hi>I will establiſh with thee an everlasting covenant,</hi> Ezek. 16.60. againe, the firſt was a covenant of juſtice without mercy, the ſecond was a covenant of mercy, yet in Chriſt juſtice and mercy met together, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 85.10.89.28. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, <hi>the firſt man is of the earth earthly, the ſecond man is of the Lord from heaven, and as the earthly, ſo were all they in that covenant, and as the heavenly, ſuch are they alſo that are heavenly, and as we have borne the image of the earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly we ſhall alſo beare the image of the heavenly,</hi> 1 cor. 15.47 48.49.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What be the offices of Chriſt to make him an alſufficient ſaviour? A.</hi> Firſt, he was a Prieſt, as he was both God and man, and he ſacrificed his body, <hi>Mat.</hi> 20, 28. and his ſoule was made an offering for ſinne, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.10. upon the altar of his Godhead, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.16. ſo chriſt was once offered to beare the ſinnes of many <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.28. alſo by his integrity or purity of his humane nature, and his obedience in performing all that the law requires, as I ſhewed before; thus Chriſt hath ſatisfied for our ſinnes, and he makes interceſſion for us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>How doth Chriſt make interceſſion fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> us? A.</hi> He appeares continually be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:111244:28"/>his Father in heaven, <hi>rom.</hi> 8.34. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.25. making their prayers accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to God by Ieſus chriſt, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.2. by applying the merits of his owne perfect ſatisfaction to them, <hi>rev.</hi> 9.3.4.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What other office hath Chriſt? A.</hi> He is a Prophet, to reveale unto his church the way and meanes of ſalvation; it is written in the Prophets, <hi>and they ſhall be all taught of God every man, therefore he that hath heard and hath lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of the Father commeth to me,</hi> Iohn 6.45, he teacheth continually by the miniſtery of word, and by the inward teaching of his holy ſpirit, <hi>Iohn</hi> 14.26.16.13.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What other office hath Chriſt? A.</hi> He is a King, that he may bountifully beſtow on us all the meanes of ſalvation, he overcame the divell, and hell and the grave, and death, as aconqueror, ſee <hi>Acts</hi> 2.24.32.10.14. 1 <hi>cor.</hi> 15.55.57. <hi>all power in heaven and in earth is given to me, goe ye therefore and teach all nations,</hi> Mat. 28.18, 19. <hi>on this rocke will I build my church, and the gates of hell ſhall not prevaile againſt it,</hi> Mat. 16.18. thus he is both a King to furniſh, and to defend his church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You told me that faith was wrought in the ſoule by the fririt of God, by the preaching of the Word, now the question is, how the Lord prepares the ſoule to receive that excellent grace of faith? A.</hi> The Lord ſayth, <hi>I will give them one heart, and I will put my spirit within you;</hi> but the manner how this is wrought is this, <hi>I will take the ſtony heart out of their fleſh, and then I will give them an heart of fleſh, then they ſhall walke in my ſtatutes and keepe mine ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances and doe them,</hi> Ezek. 11.19, 20. here you ſee the firſt worke is to take the ſtone out of the heart, which (in reaſon) ſhould be as painfull as to take the ſtone our of the bladder, this is done by that ſharp knife of the morall law, when it bruiſeth and humbleth us, and worketh in us a ſight of our ſinne, for by the law is the knowledge of ſinne; <hi>I had not knowne ſinne but by the law for I had not knowne luſt, except the law had ſayd, thou ſhalt not luſt,</hi> rom. 3, 20.7 7.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is ſorrow for ſinne? A.</hi> It is when a mans conſcience is touched with a lively feeling of Gods diſpleaſure for any ſinne; <hi>they were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oricked in their hearts,</hi> and ſayd <hi>what ſhall we doe?</hi> Acts 2.37. with an utter diſpairing of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation in regard of any thing in our ſelves; <hi>O wretched man that I am, who ſhall deliver me from this body of death!</hi> rom. 7.24. and ſo acknowledge our deſerved ſhame ſhould be eternally, <hi>czra</hi> 9.6.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>How doth God worke this ſorrow in us? A.</hi> By the terrible curſe of the law, thus he which breakes but one of the commandements of God, though it be but once in all his life time, and that onely but in thovght, is ſubject too, and in danger of eternall damnation for it, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.10. <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.10.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>When the heart is thus prepared how doth God ingraf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> faith in it? A.</hi> By caſting into it inward motions, which are the ſeeds of faith; firſt, when the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:111244:28"/>heart is humbled under the burden of ſin, then to acknowledg &amp; to feel that we ſtand in need of chriſt, this is the ſeed of faith, for we ſee that we have ſpent our money for that which is not bread, and our labour for that which ſatisfieth not, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.2. ſecondly, a hungry deſire and a longing to be made partaker of chriſt &amp; his merits, theſe alſo are the ſeeds of faith, for ſuch are bleſſed and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to be filled, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.4. <hi>rev.</hi> 21.6. thirdly, uſing the meanes when we ſee the need of chriſt and have a longing deſire after him flying from the ſentence of the law, pricking the conſcience, <hi>to the throne of grace ſuch ſhall obtaine mercy and find grace to help in time of need,</hi> Heb. 4.16.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>How is this done? A.</hi> Firſt as the Prodigall did, to think our ſinnes pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, and to ſay, <hi>Father, I have ſinned againſt heaven and before thee, and am no more worthy to be called thy ſonne, make me as one of thy h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>red ſervants,</hi> Luk. 15.18, 19. then with loud cryes for Gods ſavour in chriſt, in pardoning ſinnes with a fervent perſeverance herein, till the deſire of our heart be granted, as the woman of <hi>Canaan</hi> did, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.22, 23.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What followes after this? A.</hi> Then God according to his mercifull pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe lets the poore ſinner feele the aſſurance of his love wherewith he loveth him in chriſt, ſee <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.7. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.24. <hi>Job</hi> 33.26. this aſſurance is a lively evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of faith.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Are there divers degrees and meaſures of faith? A.</hi> Yes; the leaſt meaſure of faith that any man can have is this; when a man of an humbled ſpirit, by reaſon of the littleneſſe of his faith, doth not yet feele the aſſurance of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſſe of his ſinnes, and yet he is perſwaded that they are pardonable, and therefore he deſireth they ſhould be pardoned, and with his heart prayeth to God for pardon, and though he ſee no light, yet he will ſtay upon his God, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 50.19. this may be called ſmoaking flax or a bruiſed reed, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42.4. or the graine of muſtard-ſeed, <hi>Mat.</hi> 17.20.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>How doe you know that ſuch a man hath faith? A.</hi> Theſe deſires and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers are teſtimonies of the ſpirit, <hi>rom.</hi> 8.23.26. <hi>gal.</hi> 4.6. whoſe propesty it is to ſtirre up longings after heavenly things with ſighes and groanes for Gods fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and mercy in chriſt, now where the ſpirit of God is, there is chriſt dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.17. and where chriſt dwelleth there is true faith, how weak ſoever it be, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.17.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the greateſt meaſure of f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h? A.</hi> When a mans faith encreaſeth daily, and at length he is fully perſwaded of Gods love to himſelf in particular, and that his owne ſinnes are fully pardoned and forgiven, for the merits of chriſt; <hi>I am perſwaded that nothing is able to ſeperate us from the love of God that is in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord,</hi> rom. 8.33.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>9. this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y evidence of a ſtrong faith.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hath a christian this full aſſurance of faith at the firſt? A.</hi> No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:111244:29"/>of God is revealed from faith to faith, <hi>rom.</hi> 1.17. and they muſt pray the Lord to encreaſe their faith, <hi>Luke</hi> 17.5. and they muſt with all dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence adde to their faith vertue, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5. and fight the good ſight of faith, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.7. <hi>but they a eſtro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g who are of fullage, and by reaſon of uſe have their ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nſes exerciſed to diſcerne both good and evill,</hi> Heb. 5.14. <hi>ſuch are not weake in faith, they will not ſtagger at the promiſe of God through unbeliefe, but being ſtreng in faith they will give glory to God, being fully perſwaded that what God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>oneiſed he was able alſo to performe,</hi> rom. 4.19.20 21.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Is this justifying faith commanded in the law? A.</hi> No; not by the law of works, but by the law of faith, <hi>rom.</hi> 3.27. the law doth not reveale it, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>fore it doth not command it; but the law is ſo far from revealing juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying ſaith, that it never knew it; and <hi>Adam</hi> had the morall law written in his heart and yet he had no juſtifying faith, which apprehendeth Chriſt as a Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our and Redeemer; this ſaith <hi>Adaem</hi> knew not by the law of works, till the law of faith came in the promiſed ſeed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What benefits come by this faith in Chriſt? A.</hi> Hereby we are both juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and ſanctified, <hi>being justified by faith,</hi> rom. 5.1. <hi>and ſanctified by faith in me,</hi> Acts 26.18. <hi>purifying their hearts by faith,</hi> Acts 15.9. then our per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are accepted with God, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.4.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is it to be justified before God? A.</hi> It comprehendeth two things: firſt, to be cleered from the guiltineſſe and puniſhment of ſinne; <hi>who ſhall lay any thing to the charge of Gods elect? it is God that justifieth,</hi> rom 8.33. <hi>there is no condemnat on to them which are in Chriſt Jeſus; who is he that condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth? it is Chriſt that dyed, ye rather that he is riſen againe,</hi> rom. 8.1.34. ſecondly, we are accepted as perfectly righteous before God by him, <hi>all that beleeve are iuſtified from all things from which they could not be juſtified by the law of Moſes,</hi> Acts 13.39.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What other benefits comes along with iuſtifying faith? A.</hi> Then all our prayers and and ſervices are acceptable with the Lord, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.4. <hi>Prov.</hi> 15.8. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.2. and it makes us to eſcape all the dangers threatned againſt the wicked at the day of judgement, <hi>Luke</hi> 21.36. and it makes us worthy of the Kingdome of God, <hi>Luke</hi> 20.35. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Yea Chriſt is yours, and all is yours both things treſent and things to come,</hi> 1 Cor. 3.21, 22.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>How may a man know that he is juſtified before God? A.</hi> He need not to ſearch the ſecret counſell of Gods decrees, nor ſeeke for revelations, or an Angell from heaven to tell him; but this is the way for any that would truly find it, we muſt ſearch to ſee whither we in heart and life be ſanctified, and if we find this we may ſafely conclude our ſelves to be juſtified.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is ſanctification? A.</hi> It is a renewed holineſſe which fits and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares the creature for the Lords uſe; <hi>goe yee out of the middeſt of her; be ye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eane that beare the veſſels of the Lord,</hi> Iſa. 52.11. <hi>for he will be ſanctified in
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:111244:29"/>all that come nigh him,</hi> Levit. 10.3. <hi>if any man purge himſelfe, he ſhall be a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſſell unto honour, ſanctified and meet for the Maſters uſe, and prepared unto every good worke,</hi> 2 Tim. 2.21.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But may not a man have faith and be juſtified without ſanctification? A.</hi> No; for faith as an inſtrument both juſtifies and ſanctifies; for as it receives and applies Chriſt and his merits to us in particular, ſo it juſtifies; and as it workes by love and acts all other graces in their lively motion, ſo it ſanctifies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But Infants may be juſtified, are they alſo ſanctified? A.</hi> Yes; <hi>before I formed thee in the belley I knew thee;</hi> here is Gods decree, but as yet not brought forth, <hi>Zeth.</hi> 2.2. the man is not formed therefore as yet neither juſtified nor ſanctified, but ſayth the Lord, <hi>before thou cameſt out of the wombe I ſanctified thee,</hi> Ier. 1.5. <hi>many ſhall rejoyce at the birth of</hi> John, <hi>becauſe he ſhall be ſilled with the holy Ghoſt, enen from his mothers wombe,</hi> Luke 1.14, 15.</p>
            <p>Proceed: <hi>What be the parts of ſanctification? A.</hi> Two, mortification and vivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication; mortification is that power whereby ſin is abated and crucified in the faithfull; <hi>how ſhall we that are dead to ſin l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve any longer therein,</hi> rom. 6.2. <hi>they which are Christs have crucified the fleſh with the affections and lusts,</hi> Gal. 5.24.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By what meanes is mortification wrought in us? A.</hi> By the death and bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall of Chriſt, we are buried with him by baptiſme into his death, <hi>rom.</hi> 6.4. <hi>our old man is crucified with him, that the body of ſin might be deſtroyed, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o.</hi> 6.6.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the other part of ſanctification? A.</hi> It is viviſication, whereby inherent holineſſe is begun and increaſed in us, we receive the firſt fruits of the ſpirits; <hi>be renewed in the spirit of your mind, and put on the new man, which after God is created in righteouſneſſe and true holineſſe,</hi> Eph. 4.23, 24. <hi>you hath he quickned that were dead in trespaſſes and ſinnes: I am crucified with Chriſt, nevertheleſſe I live, yet not I but Chriſt liveth in me, and the life which I now live in the fleſh, I live by the faith of the ſonne of God,</hi> Gal. 2.20. <hi>we which ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e the firſt fruits of the spirit doe groane within our ſelves, waiting for the adoption</hi> (to wit) <hi>the redemption of our bodies,</hi> rom. 8.23.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the efficient cauſe whereby theſe graces are wrought in us? A.</hi> The holy Ghoſt applying the power of the death and reſurrection of Chriſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth holineſſe in us; he will deliver his ſoule from going into the pit, and his life ſhall ſee the light; loe all theſe things worketh God oftentimes for man; to bring back his ſoule from the pit to be enlightned with the light of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, <hi>Job</hi> 33.28; 29.33. <hi>that the offering up of the gentiles might be acceptable, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſanctified by the holy Ghoſt,</hi> rom. 15.16.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>How is this grace preſerved in us? A.</hi> It is preſerved by the vertue of chriſts reſurrection; that I may know him and the vertue of his reſrurection, <hi>phil.</hi> 3.10 firſt chriſt did in his own fleſh overcome death and ſin and live to God, and was exalted above every name, &amp; then he infuſeth this power into us &amp; we receive it by faith, wherby we dye unto ſin daily, and live to God in newneſſe of life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In what part of us is this grace of ſanctification wrought? A</hi> In every
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:111244:30"/>part of body and ſoule, the very God or peace ſanctifie you wholly, <hi>and I pray God yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r whole spirit, ſoule and body may be perfect and blameleſſe unto the comming of our Lord Jeſus chriſt,</hi> 1 Theſ. 5.23.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>How do you know when the mind is ſanctified? A.</hi> When ſpirituall underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding is given unto it, to acknowledge the known truth of Gods word and when ſpirituall wiſdome is given to apply that truth knowne, to the well ordering both of things and actions, as perſon, place, and time requires, then we come to diſcerne both good and evill, <hi>heb.</hi> 5.14. and to diſcerne of things that are excellent, <hi>phil.</hi> 1.10. and to try the ſpirits whether they be of God, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.1. and to try doctrines, <hi>Joh.</hi> 7.17. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.21. <hi>Acts</hi> 17.11. and ſo we come to med<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tate on the word and workes of God, and to delight in his law and to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe our ſelves in it night and day, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1.119.15. and we diſcerne our owne want of knowledge, by which meanes we ſhall entreat the Lord to teach us, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.18.33.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>When is the memory ſanctified? A.</hi> When it is made a treaſury of good things; <hi>a good man out of the good treaſure of his heart; bringeth forth good things,</hi> Mat. 35. <hi>Mary kept all thoſe ſayings in her heart,</hi> Luke 2.51. and <hi>David</hi> ſayd, <hi>thy word I have hid in my heart, that I might not ſinne againſt thee,</hi> Pſal. 119.11. Secondly, when we remember our ſinnes to loath them; <hi>then ſhall ye remember your owne evill wayes, and your doing that were not good, and ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>th your ſelves in your owne ſight for your iniquities, and for your abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> Ezek. 36.31.16.63.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>When is the conſcience ſanctified? A.</hi> When it doth excuſe us for all ſin; when we are certaine that they are forgiven us in Chriſt; <hi>having faith and a good conſcience, which ſome have put away,</hi> 1 Tim. 1.19. <hi>I know nothing by my ſelfe, yet am I not hereby justified,</hi> 1 Cor. 4.4. <hi>I have in all good conſcience ſerved God untill this day,</hi> Acts 23.1. herein I exerciſe my ſelfe to have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes <hi>a conſcience void of offence both towards God and towards men,</hi> Acts 24.16. <hi>try me, O Lord, and prove me, examine my raines and my heart, for thy loving kindneſſe is before mine eyes, and I have walked in thy truth,</hi> Pſal. 26.1, 2.3. hence ariſeth in us that peace of conſcience that paſſeth all underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which ſhall keepe our hearts and minds through Chriſt Ieſus, Phil. 4.7. this makes the righteous as bold as a lyon, Pro. 28.1. if our hearts condemne us not then have we conſcience towards God. 1. Ioh. 3.21.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>When is the will ſanctified? A.</hi> When our wils is regulated by Gods re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed will; when the ſpirit is willing though the fleſh be weake, Mat. 26.41. When to wil is preſent but how to performe that which is good we finde not, rom. 7.19. for it is God that worketh in us both to will and to doe of his own good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Phil. 2.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>When are the affections ſanctified? A.</hi> Our hope is ſanctified when we
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:111244:30"/>wait for the accompliſhment of our redemption, rom. 8.23, 24, 25. and when we ſhew the ſame diligence in full aſſurance of hope unto the end, Heb. 6.11. Our feare is ſanctified, when we feare to offend the Lord becauſe of his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Hoſea 3.5. they ſhall feare and tremble for all the goodneſſe and for all the proſperity that I will procure unto it, <hi>Jer.</hi> 33.9 <hi>If ye call him father, paſſe the time of your ſojourning here in feare,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.17. our love of God in Chriſt is ſanctified when it is as a fire that cannot be quenched; <hi>many waters cannot quench love, nor the floods drowne it,</hi> cant. 8.7. when this love burnes up all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther love, and when we eſteeme of all outward things but as loſſe and dung for the excellent knowledge of Chriſt, and to win chriſt, <hi>phil.</hi> 3.7, 8. our zeale is ſanctified when we regard not what becomes of us, ſo God may be glorified, <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.32. <hi>rom.</hi> 9.3. our ſorrow and anguiſh of mind is ſanctified, when our eyes can guſh out with teares, becauſe men keep not Gods law, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.136. as <hi>Lots</hi> righteous ſoule was vexed with the filthy converſation of the wicked, he dwelling amongſt them, <hi>in ſeeing and hearing vexed his righteous ſoule from day to day with their ungodly deeds,</hi> 2 Pet. 2.7, 8. our joy is ſanctified when Gods countenance more rejoyceth our hearts then the increaſe of come and wine, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.7. and when we rejoyce that the Goſpell is preached, <hi>phil.</hi> 1.18. and when we rejoyce in the fruitfulneſſe of is, in the converſion of ſoules, <hi>Luke</hi> 15.7.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>How doe you know when the body is ſanctified? A.</hi> Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n it is a fit inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the ſoule to accompliſh that which is good, <hi>as ye have given your members ſervants to uncleanoeſſe and to iniquity, to commit iniquity, ſo now give your members ſervants unto righteouſneſſe in holineſſe, rom.</hi> 6.19.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cannot we be ſaved without holineſſe? A.</hi> No; for heaven is promiſed to them that are ſanctified, <hi>Acts</hi> 26.18. <hi>and no uncleane thing ſhall enter into it,</hi> rev. 21.27. <hi>without holineſſe no man ſhall ſee the Lord,</hi> Heb. 12.14. <hi>the pure in heart they ſhall ſee God,</hi> mat. 5.8.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Are there degrees in holineſſe or ſanctification? A.</hi> Yes; <hi>that ye may grow up into him in all things, which is the head, even chriſt,</hi> Eph. 4.15. <hi>being kn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t together we may increaſe with the increaſe of God.</hi> col. 2.19. <hi>I beſeech you bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and exhort you, by the lord Ieſus chriſt, that as you have received of us how you ought to walke and to pleaſe God, ſo ye would abound more and more, for this is the will of God, even your ſanctification, that every one may know how to poſſeſſe his veſſell in ſanctification and honour.</hi> 1 Theſ. 4.1.3, 4.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>May a man attain to perfection in degrees of his ſanctification the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e? A.</hi> No; ſaith Paul, <hi>not as though I had already attained either were already perfect;</hi> but I fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low after; if that I may apprehend that for which alſo I am apprehended <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n chriſt Ieſus; <hi>brethren I count not my ſelfe to have apprehended but this one thing I doe, forgetting thoſe things which are behind, and re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ching f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rth unto th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſe
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:111244:31"/>things which are before, I preſſe toward the marke; for the price of the high calling of God in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> Phil. 3.12, 13, 14.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What meanes hath God appointed to helpe us in our groth of grace? A.</hi> The ſacraments and prayer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is a ſacrament? A.</hi> A ſacrament is an outward ſigne whereby Chriſt and his ſaving graces are by certaine extetnall rights ſignified and ſealed to a chriſtian; <hi>Abraham</hi> received the ſigne of circumciſion, and it was alſo the ſeale of the righteouſneſſe of faith, which he had when he was yet uncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed, <hi>rons.</hi> 4.21. <hi>yee ſhaell circumciſe the foreskin of your fleſh, and it ſhall be a ſigne of the covenant between me and you,</hi> Gen. 17.11.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hath any others power to make a ſacrament beſides chriſt? A</hi> No; for the ſigne will conſirme nothing at all but by the conſent of him, at whoſe hands the benefit promiſed muſt be received; then none but chriſt can appoint ſignes of grace, becauſe none but he alone hath power to beſtow grace; chriſt is the author of our ſalvation, therefore he alone may appoint the meanes, which are the word and ſacraments; <hi>chriſt is the onely Law-giver, who is able to ſave and to destroy,</hi> Iam. 4.12. <hi>and he alone can make a ſacrament offectuall by his spirit, and he by his wiſedome beſt knowes of what to institute the ſacramentall ſignes, neither may any preſume to adde or to diminiſh to that he hath done,</hi> rev. 22.38, 19.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>How doth chriſt make a ſacrament? A.</hi> By bringing the word of inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution to the element; the word is two-fold, either a word of command, as in baptiſme, <hi>goe yee into all the world baptizing them, In the name of the father, ſonne and holy Ghoſt;</hi> and in the Lords ſupper, <hi>take, eat, drinke, doe ye this;</hi> the other part of inſtitution is a promiſe, whereby chriſt ordained elements that they might be inſtruments and ſeales of his grace, as in baptiſme, <hi>I baptize thee in the name of the father, of the ſenne, and of the holy Ghoſt;</hi> and in the Lords ſupper, <hi>this is my body which is given for you, and this is my blood of the new Testament;</hi> therefore the word of inſtitution ought to be pronounced di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly in the adminiſtration of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>May the impiety of the Miniſter make a nullity of the ſacrament to a worthy receiver? A.</hi> No; no more then the piety of a good Miniſter can profit an unworthy receiver, becauſe all the efficacy and worthineſſe thereof dependeth onely upon Gods inſtitution.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What be the parts of a ſacrament? A.</hi> They be two: the outward ſigne or ſenſible matter of the element, or the action converſant about the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Is there any naturall change in the ſigne or element after conſecration? A.</hi> No; it is but ſevered from a common to a holy uſe, therefore there is no force or efficacy in the externall ſignes, to make us inherently holy, as there is in Bathes naturally to purifie corrupt diſeaſes; but all the efficacy is appropriate
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:111244:31"/>to Gods holy ſpirit; yet ſo, as it is an inſeparable companion of true faith and repentance, in ſuch as turne to the Lord; therefore by Gods ordinance a certaine ſignification of grace, and ſealing thereof agreeth to the ſigne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the thing ſignified by the outward element. A.</hi> It is Chriſt and his graces: firſt of Chriſt, and then of his graces; for as no man can receive fruit of any ground till firſt he have a juſt title to it, no more can we have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit by Chriſt before we have a true title to him by faith.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the action of God in the ſacrament. A.</hi> It is either the offering of Chriſt, or the application of Chriſt and his graces to the faithfull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the action of Faith in the Sacrament? A.</hi> It is the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, deſire, apprehenſion and receiving of chriſt, in the lawfull uſe of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the end why Sacraments were ordained? A.</hi> For the better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of our faith, for God doth as it were, by certaine pledges bind <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſelfe unto us, yet the ſacrament doth not ſtrengthen us, by any inherent power of it ſelfe, as a ſoveraigne medicine doth cure a patient, but rather by a certaine reaſoning upon uſing the ſignes framed by the holy Ghoſt thus:</p>
            <p>All ſuch as are converted rightly uſing the ſacraments ſhall receive chriſt and his graces.</p>
            <p>But I am converted, and either doe now or elſe heretofore.</p>
            <p>I have rightly uſed the ſacraments; therefore I ſhall receive chriſt and his graces.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is another end why the ſacrament was ordained? A.</hi> That it might be a badge of that profeſſion, by which the true church of God is diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed from all other congregations; a third end is, that it might be a meanes to preſerve and to ſpread the doctrine of the Goſpell: a fourth end is, that it might preferve and bind the faithfull to continue loyall and thankfull to their Lord God: fiftly, it ſerves as a bond of mutuall amity among the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Is a ſacrament neceſſary to ſalvation? A.</hi> No; yet the covenant of grace is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely neceſſary to ſalvation for it comprehendeth chriſt Ieſus, who is the ſubſtance of that covenant, ſo that we muſt of neceſſity receive it, or we periſh eternally; now a ſacrament is but a prop or ſtay for faith as an help to en. creaſe it; but it cannot intitle us into the inheritance of the ſonn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s of God as the covenant doth, but onely as a ſeale to that covenant that we by faith received before.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But doth not the want of a ſacrament condemne? A.</hi> No; it is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of it that is damnable, ſo then, the neglect of it is a grievous ſinne
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:111244:32"/>to be repented of, and there is hope of pardon, but if ſome be juſtly hindred from it, either by living in ſome place where it cannot be had, or taken away by death, to ſuch God will have mercy, not ſacrifice.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the difference betwixt a ſacrament and a ſacrifice? A.</hi> In a ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment God beſtowes his graces upon us, but in a ſacrifice we returne unto God faith and thankfull obedience.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>How doth our ſacraments and thoſe in the old Teſtament differ? A.</hi> They were many, and ours but few; ſecondly, they pointed at chriſt to come, but theſe ſhew that he is already come; thirdly they were to the poſterity of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> alone, but theſe are to the whole church, called out of both Iewe, and Gentiles.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>How many ſacraments is there in the church of chriſt? A.</hi> Two; the firſt is baptiſme, wherein chriſtians are admitted into the church of God; the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond is the Lords ſupper, whereby the church is nouriſhed and preſerved to eternall life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is baptiſme? A.</hi> It is a waſhing with water as they are command <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. <hi>In the name of the Father, Son, and holy Ghoſt:</hi> that being in the covenant and ingrafted into chriſt, they may have perpetuall fellowſhip with him; <hi>he that beleeveth and is baptized ſhall be ſaved,</hi> Marke 16.16. Acts 2.38.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>May we baptize in no other name, nor leave out any of the three perſons in Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity? A.</hi> No; chriſt is not divided, nor <hi>Paul</hi> crucified for you, neither were you baptized in the name of <hi>Paul; I thanke God I baptized none of you but</hi> Criſpus <hi>and</hi> Gaius, <hi>least any ſhould ſay, that I did baptize in my own name,</hi> 1 cor. 13.14, 15.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Who are thoſe within the covenant that are to be baptized? A.</hi> They are of two forts: firſt, ſuch as are growne in yeers, and joyne themſelves to the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible church, teſtifying their faith and repentance, and hold the foundation of Religion taught in the ſame church they are to be baptized in: the Eunuch ſayd to <hi>Phillip I beleeve that Chriſt is the ſonne of God, and ſo they went both into the water and he baptized him,</hi> Acts 8.38. <hi>they were baptized of</hi> Iohn <hi>in</hi> Iordan <hi>confeſſing their ſinnes,</hi> Mat. 3.6. <hi>repent and be baptized everyone of you,</hi> acts 2.38. <hi>if a ſtranger dwell with thee and will obſerve the Paſſover of the Lord, let him circumciſe all his males, and then let him come and obſerve it, and he ſhall be as one borne in the land, for no uncircumciſed perſon ſhall eat thereof,</hi> Exod. 12.48.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Who elſe are in in the covenant and ought to be baptized? A.</hi> Infants born of chriſtian parents; <hi>the unbeleeving husband is ſanctefied by the wife, and the unbeleeving wife is ſanctified by the husband, elſe were your children unclean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:111244:32"/>but now they are holy,</hi> 1 cor. 7.14. <hi>if the first fruits be holy ſo is the whole lumpe, if the root be holy ſo are the branches,</hi> rom. 11.16. <hi>I will eſtabliſh my covenant with thee and with thy ſeed after thee, for an everlasting covenant to be thy God, and the God of thy ſeed after thee,</hi> Gen. 17.7.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>How are children of chriſtian parents in the covenant? A.</hi> Not as they are the ſinfull off-ſpring of the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> for ſo they beget them in their owne likeneſſe; nor ſecondly, as they are by grace the ſonnes of God, for they are not made the ſonnes of God by naturall generation, but by adoption; <hi>yet they may beleeve for themſelves and others according to the covenant of grace, Gen.</hi> 17.7. as <hi>Adam</hi> did ſinne both for himſelfe and others, and as parents in bargaines doe covenant both for themſelves and their heires after them; <hi>thus the parents being the firſt fruits, ſanctifies the whole lump of their poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> rom. 11.16.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is it to be baptized, In the name of the father, ſonne and holy Ghoſt? A.</hi> It is to be made one of Gods family which is his church, and to be made partaker of the priviledges thereof, as <hi>Jacob</hi> ſayd, <hi>the Angel which hath delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red me from all evil bleſſe the lads and let my name be named upon them and the name of my fathers,</hi> Gen. 48.16. <hi>in that day ſhall ſeven women take hold of one man, ſaying, we will eat our owne bread and weare our owne garments, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly let us be called by thy name to take away our reproach.</hi> Iſa. 4.1</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What doe we learne from hence? A.</hi> We learne that in this waſhing of baptiſme is ſealed a ſolemne contract and covenant between God and the baptized: firſt, of God the father, who vouchſafeth to receive him into fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, and of God the ſonne to redeem him, and of God the holy Ghoſt to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie and regenerate him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What doth the baptized bind themſelves unto? A.</hi> He promiſeth to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge invocate and worſhip none other God but the true Iehovah, which is the father, ſonne and holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVhat is the viſible or externall matter of baptiſme? A.</hi> It is water: for the Miniſter may not baptize with any other liquor, but only with naturall water according to thoſe examples we have in Scripture, &amp; of the primitive church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the externall forme of baptiſme? A.</hi> It is the miniſters waſhing the baptized, according to the preſcrpt of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Suppoſe it was the ancient custome to dip or dive all the body of the baptized in the water, muſt their example of neceſſity be followed? A.</hi> No; for the word baptize ſignifies ſprinkling as well as dipping or diving, and ſayth the Lord, <hi>I will sprinkle cleane water upon you,</hi> Ezek. 36.25. againe by reaſon of ſome cold countries, and the weakneſſe of young Infants, neceſſity and chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty may diſpence with ceremonies, and mittigate the ſharpneſſe of them.</p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:111244:33"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>What reſemblance is there between the element of water, and the thing ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thereby? A.</hi> As water waſheth away the filth of the body, ſo the blood of Chriſt Ieſus cleanſeth us from all ſinne, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.7.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What doth the ac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> of the Minister wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing the body of the baptized ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie? A.</hi> This ſeale<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and I confirmeth a double action of God: firſt, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grafting or incorporating the baptized into Chriſt; <hi>as many as are baptized into Chriſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſt,</hi> Gal. 3.27. <hi>by one spirit we are all baptized into one body, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> ſecondly, it ſealeth to us our regeneration; <hi>not he the worker <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> which we have done, but according to his mercy he ſaved us by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> king of regeneration, and renewing of the holy Ghoſt,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tus 3.5.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What doth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> water, or sprinkling it upon the baptized ſignifie? A.</hi> It doth ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> the ſhedding of the blood of Chriſt for the remiſſion of all our ſinne; and the imputation of his righteouſneſſe; <hi>ariſe and be bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d, and wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> away thy ſinnes, calling upon the name of the Lord,</hi> Acts 22.16. and it ſignifies mortification of ſinne by the power and death of Chriſt; <hi>know ye not that all they which have been <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> into Chriſt, have been baptized into his death? the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> crucified with him that the body of ſinne might be destroyed,</hi> rom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What doth the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in or under the water ſignifie unto us? A.</hi> It ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies the buriall of ſinne, or a continuall encrea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of mortification both by the power of Chriſt's death and buriall; <hi>we are buried with him by baptiſme in o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>is death,</hi> rom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.4.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What doth the comming out of the water ſignifie unto us? A.</hi> It concernes our ſpirituall vivification to newneſſe of life in all holineſſe and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, by the power of Chriſts reſurrection; for like as Chriſt was raiſed up from the dead by the glory of the father, ſo we all ſhould walke in newneſſe of life; <hi>for if we be grafted together in the likeneſſe of his death, we ſhall be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of his reſurrection,</hi> rom. 6.4 5.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What doth the action of the party baptized ſignifie, when he offers himſelfe before the M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ter and the congregation to be baptized? A.</hi> It ſignifies that he doth conſecrate himſelfe the Lord, and that he utterly renounceth the fleſh the world, and the devill the like figure which now ſaveth us, even bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, <hi>not the putting away the filth of the fleſh, but the anſwer of a good conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence towards God,</hi> 1 Pet. 3.21.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Suppoſe any question the lawfulneſſe of his baptiſme, may he be re-baptized? A.</hi> No; for as in naturall generation a man is but once borne, ſo he can be but once new borne, therefore if a man be baptized be a Miniſter that is an heretick, not yet degraded from his calling, and if he obſerve the forme of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:111244:33"/>
               <hi>In the name of the father, ſonne and holy Ghoſt,</hi> it is a reall bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>How may a man profitably uſe his baptiſme all his life long? A.</hi> Firſt, when any ſinfull luſt ſhall ariſe in thy ſoule, then begin to meditate of that ſolemne Vow which thou did deſt make to God in thy baptiſme: Secondly, if through infirmity thou fall into any ſinne, ſtill have recourſe to thy baptiſme for thy encouragement and comfort; for although baptiſme be but once adminiſtred yet that once teſtifieth, that all thy ſinnes paſt, preſent and to come, are waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed away, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.20. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.25, 26, 27. it is called the ſacrament of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, <hi>Marke</hi> 1.4. laſtly, to make a profitable uſe of thy baptiſme, then thou muſt not reſt till thou have a feeling of that renewing power fignified in baptiſme, namely, the power of Chriſt's death, mortifying thy ſinne, and the vertue of his reſurrection renewing thy ſpirit, ſoule and body, in all holy obedience.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>How is it that many feele not the fruit of their baptiſme? A.</hi> The fault is not in God, but in themſelves, in that they doe not keepe the condition of the covenant to receive Chriſt by ſaith, and to repent of their ſinnes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>When ſhall a man ſee the effect of his baptiſme? A.</hi> When he receives Chriſt by faith, though it be many yeers after then he ſhall feel the power of God to regenerate him, and to work all thoſe things which he offered him in baptiſme.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is done in the Lords ſupper? A.</hi> The former covenant ſolemnly ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified in baptiſme, is renewed in the Lords ſupper, between the Lord and the receiver.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What doe the elements of bread and wine ſignifie unto us? A.</hi> They are ſignes and ſeales of the body and blood of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What doth the actions of the Minister about the ſame elements ſignifie unto the receiver? A.</hi> They ſignifie unto the receiver fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re actions of God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: Firſt, his taking the bread and wine into his hands, doth ſeale unto us the action of God the father, who from all eternity did ſeparate and elect his ſonne to performe the duty of a mediatour between God and man; <hi>mine elect in whom my ſoule delighteth,</hi> Iſa. 42.1. <hi>him hath God the Father ſealed,</hi> Iohn. 6.27.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What doth the Ministers bleſſing of the elements with the recitall of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes ſignifie and ſeale unto the receiver? A.</hi> The bleſſing of them ſignifies, that thoſe elements are now taken from a common to a holy uſe, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citall of the promiſes, ſeales unto us that action of God by which in the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of time, he ſent Chriſt to performe the office of mediatour, unto which he was fore-ordained.</p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:111244:34"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>What doth the breaking of bread and powring out of the wine ſignifie to the receivers? A.</hi> This ſealeth the action of God, offering Chiiſt unto all, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iving him onely to the faithfull, for the encreaſe of their faith and repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What doth the receivers action in taking the bread and wine in his hand ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie? A.</hi> This ſealeth a ſpirituall action, namely, his apprehending of chriſt by the hand of faith, <hi>as many as received him, to them he gave power to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the ſonnes of God, even to them that beleeve on his name,</hi> Ioh. 1.12.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What doth his eating of the bread and drinking of the wine ſignifie? A.</hi> This ſealeth his application of Chirſt by the ſame faith, by a feeling of his true union and communion, to encreaſe daily by faith, as our bodies are ſtrengthned by the bread and wine; <hi>the cup of bleſſing which we bleſſe, is it not the communion of the blood of Christ? the bread which we breake, is it not the communion of the body of Chriſt?</hi> 1 Cor. 11.16.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Is not the bread in the ſacrament after conſecration turned into the body of Chriſt? A.</hi> No; firſt, becauſe this ſacramentall bread was eaten before the death of Chriſt, therefore unpoſſible to be a corporall eating of his fleſh; ſecondly, the bread is broken and diſtributed after conſecration but the whole body of Chriſt is received by every ſingle communicant: thirdly, the bread is the communion of Chriſt, therefore not his very body: fourthly, the body of Chriſt was made of the ſubſtance of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> therefore not of bakers bread: fiftly, this bread is ſubject to mold that is left after conſecration; this ſhewes that it is will reall bread: ſixtly, if the ſigne be tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into the ſubſtance, then what ſigne remaines? this would overthrow the ſacramentall union between the ſigne and the thing ſignified.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But is not chriſts body corporally preſent in the ſacament? A.</hi> No; <hi>this doe in remembrance of me,</hi> 1 cor. 24.25. ſecondly, <hi>the heavens muſt receive him till the reſtitution of all things,</hi> act. 3.2. Thirdly, the body of Chriſt can be but in one place, <hi>he is not here, come ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ee the place where the Lord lay,</hi> mat. 28.6.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>When are we fitly prepared to receive the Lords ſupper? A.</hi> Firſt, if we bring a right knowledge of mans fall, and a promiſed reſtoration into the covenant by Chriſt, he is the mediatour of a better covenant, which is eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed upon better promiſes <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.6. <hi>ſo often as yee ſhall eat this bread and drinke of this cup, yee ſhew the Lords death till he come, and we muſt by our knowledge diſcerne the Lords body</hi> 1 cor. 11.26, 29.</p>
            <p>Secondly, we muſt have a true faith in Chriſt, for we receive ſo much as we beleeve that we receive, <hi>for unto us was the Gospell preached, as well as to them, but the word preached did not profit them, not being mixed with faith in them that heard it,</hi> Heb. 4.2.</p>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:111244:34"/>
            <p> Thirdly, we muſt have true repentance for all our ſinnes, both originall and actuall, being the ſtate wherein we lay in the breach of the firſt co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, we muſt bring renewed faith and repentance to teſtifie our thankfulneſſe to God for his great goodneſſe, to receive us into a new cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, not of works, but of grace, wherein he promiſes to be mercifull to our righteouſneſſe, and to remember our iniquities no more, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.13. and to teſtifie our love both to God and his people, <hi>he ſo loved us, that he gave his onely begotten ſonne for us,</hi> Ioh. 3.16. <hi>and Chriſt gave his life a ranſome for us,</hi> mat. 20.28. <hi>therefore we ſhould love him that firſt loued us,</hi> 1 Ioh. 4.19. alſo our love muſt be to his people; <hi>if thou bring thy gift to the Altar, and there remembreſt that thy brother hath ought againſt thee, leave thy gift be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Altar, and goe firſt and be reconciled to thy brother, and then come and offer thy gift.</hi> mat. 5.23, 25.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But what if I in part find theſe things in me, when withall I find my heart exceeding rebellious, and very corrupt? A.</hi> Thou mayeſt come as a welcome gueſt for all that, for Chriſt came to preach the Goſpell to ſuch a poore heart as thine and to heal ſuch a broken heart, &amp; to deliver ſuch a captive from cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, and to give ſight to thee ihat feeleſt want of it, and to ſet at liberty thy bruiſed ſoule, <hi>Luke</hi> 4.18.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>How ſhall I come to the ſacrament, I want faith? A.</hi> If thou be ſenſible of thy want of faith, thou mayeſt come; for it is grace that diſcovers thy want, and not nature, therefore pray the Lord to encreaſe thy faith, <hi>Luke</hi> 17.5. and ſay with teares, <hi>I beleeve, Lord help my unbeliefe, Marke</hi> 9.24. then come and Chriſt will eaſe thee, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.28. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55.22.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What other meanes hath God appointed us to uſe for our groth in grace? A.</hi> Prayer which is a familiar ſpeech with God in the name of Chriſt, in which either we crave things needfull, or give thanks for things received, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.1.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>May we not pray to Saints or Angels? A.</hi> No; for they doe not know our wants; <hi>Abraham <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of us,</hi> Iſa. 63.17, neither can they help us <hi>they pray to Gods that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſave,</hi> Iſa. 45.20. and the command of Chriſt is, <hi>come unto me all ye that are heavy laden and I will give you reſt,</hi> mat. 11.28.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But may we not make Saints our med<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tours or interceſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs? A.</hi> No; <hi>there is but one mediatour between God and man the man Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> 2 Tim. 2.5. <hi>he is our onely high Prieſt who is entred into heaven, now to appeare in the preſence of God for us,</hi> Heb. 9.24. <hi>Chriſt alone is our interceſſor in heaven for us,</hi> rom. 8.34. heb. 7.25.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For whom muſt we pray? A.</hi> for all men living none exempted, but they
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:111244:35"/>that ſinne againſt the holy Ghoſt; <hi>there is a ſinne unto death, I doe not ſay that yee ſhall pray for it,</hi> 1 Ioh. 5.16.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But may we not pray for the dead? A.</hi> No; when <hi>Davids</hi> child was dead he ceaſed praying for it, ſaying, <hi>now he is dead, wherefore ſhould I faſt?</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Sam. 12.22, 23. there is no repentance in the grave when they are dead? <hi>he that is unjuſt let him be unjuſt ſtill, and he that is filthy let him be filthy ſtill, and he that is holy let him be holy ſtill,</hi> rev. 22.11. <hi>it is the blood of Jeſus Chriſt that cleanfeth us from y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l ſinne,</hi> 1 Ioh. 1.7. <hi>and if thou be not purged thou ſhalt not be purged from thy filthineſſe any more,</hi> Ezek. 24.13.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For what muſt we pray? A.</hi> Chriſt hath taught us to pray for ſix things eſpecially: Firſt, that God may be glorified: ſecondly, that God may reigne in our hearts as in his Kingdome: thirdly, that we may doe Gods will faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, conſtantly and cheerfully, as it is done in heaven.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe three c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ncerning God, what things be they that we muſt pray for our ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ves? A</hi> Firſt, that we may rely wholly on Gods providence for all the meanes of this temporall life: ſecondly, that our ſinnes may be forgiven, that we may be at peace with God: thirdly, that by his power we may be kept from all temptations, that they prevaile not againſt us to ſinne againſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Why are thoſe petitions concerning Gods glory, kingdome and will, ſet downe before theſe three petitions for our ſelves? A.</hi> Becauſe we ſhould preferre Gods glory, kingdome and will before and above all other things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is Gods kingdome here on earth? A.</hi> It is his church and people in which Chriſt rules as King.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is that viſible Church in which Chriſt rules as King? A.</hi> Firſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatively, it is not amongſt any Libertines whatſoever, as the Antinomians, who cry out of the bondage of his law, which is the ſtatute law of heaven; neither the Anabaptiſts, who deſpiſe the lawes of men, being regulated by the law of God: nor the Prelacy, which exalt themſelves into the throne of God and man uſurping all power to themſelves; nor the Browniſts, which ſeperate from all eccleſiaſticall government: all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ount it a bondage that Chriſt ſhould rule as King.</p>
            <p>Now I anſwer affirmatively, that church that hath the truths of doctrine and the right way of diſcipline according to Gods Word, and freely yeelds obedience unto both, I meane in the generall, although ſome ſingle perſons faile in any of theſe, yet this is the true Corne-field of Chiſt, although ſome tares be in it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>May any ſepa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ate from that Church which hath true doctrine, when there for the preſent may be ſome want in d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſcipline in the matter or in the execution.
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:111244:35"/>A.</hi> No: for diſcipline is not eſſentiall to the being of a Church, but onely to the well being of it; it may be the Church of Chriſt, and yet want his diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline; againe, we may not ſeperate from the Church till Chriſt ſeperate from it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But how ſhall we know when chriſt leaves a church? A.</hi> Firſt, the church doth leave Chriſt; but while we hold the truths of doctrine, we have not left Chriſt; but ſuppoſe we like a Strumpet, have deſerved to be put away, and a bill of divorce to be given to us; <hi>yet bleſſed be God, whoſe going <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are ſtill ſeene in his Sanctuary,</hi> Pſal. 68.24.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But how doe you know that a bill of divorce is not given to us? A.</hi> If Chriſt had left his church here, he would have taken away the hedge of protection, and leave us to be deſtroyed by the wilde Beaſts, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 80.12. that is, <hi>the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates ſword ſhould not have been drawn in the defence of it, neither would he receive our offerings,</hi> Iudges 13.23. Secondly, if God had left us, he would have called away his Miniſters from us; for they are not to ſtay where they find none to receive them, <hi>John</hi> 4.35. but to ſhake off the duſt of their feet as a witneſſe againſt them, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.11. Thirdly, when chriſt leaves a church, it is becauſe he hath no more to call in that church; for when <hi>Paul</hi> was depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting from <hi>Macedonia,</hi> the Lord bad him to ſtay, for he had much people in that city. <hi>Acts</hi> 18.10. ſo bleſſed be God, we ſee the worke of the Miniſtery ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding fruitfull in converting multitudes to the Lord, which plainly ſhewes that chriſt hath not left us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But were not your Miniſters ſome few yeers agon called from you and the h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dge of protection broken downe, and Idolatry comming in apace? A.</hi> Our affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were then to the truths of God and the miniſtry fruitfull by thoſe that ſtayed with us; and therefore I ſee no lawfull call they had to depart from their flocks when the Wolves were comming, except thoſe whoſe particular perſons were aimed at; neither was it the Magiſtrates, by the ſword of juſtice, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to law that was turned againſt the church, but it was the Prelates uſurped power that did perſecute Gods people, againſt both the lawes of God and the lawes of the Kingdome.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the effect of ſepration? A.</hi> Seperation is the cauſe of diſtractions and civill warres, and ſo ends in confuſion; therefore no toleration is to be granted to ſuch a Vyper as ſeperation, that eats out her mothers bowels.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the ſtate of all men after they have lived a while here? A. All muſt dye and be as water spilt upon the ground,</hi> 2 Sam. 14.14. <hi>death is paſſed upon all, for that all have ſinned,</hi> rom. 5.12.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Why muſt Gods people dye, hath not Chriſt taken away their ſinne? A.</hi> Chriſt hath forgiven their ſinne, and covered it with his righteouſneſſe, Pſal.
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:111244:36"/>32.1. but he doth not take away the being of ſin til death, <hi>Ro.</hi> 6.7. <hi>no man liveth and ſinneth not,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 8.46. <hi>he is a lyar that ſaith he hath no ſinne,</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.8.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What followes the day of death? A.</hi> A particular judgement; <hi>it is appointed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> all m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n once to dye, and from death to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gement,</hi> Heb. 9.27. <hi>the body returns to duſt, and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of all returne to God; the ſpirit of man goes upward,</hi> Eccl. 3.21.12.7.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What followes the particular judgement? A.</hi> The general day of judgement, that day of God, wherein the heavens being on fire ſhall be diſſolved, and the earth ſhall melt with fire and heat, and the workes that are therein ſhaall be burnt up, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.10.12.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Who ſhall be the Judge? A.</hi> Ieſus Chriſt the Sonne of God, <hi>we muſt all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare before the Judgement-ſeat of Chriſt,</hi> rom. 14.10, 12. 2 cor. 5.10.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What will be the manner of his comming? A. The Sonne of man will come in a cloud with power and great<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> glory,</hi> Luke 21.27. <hi>and attended with his holy A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gels</hi> Marke 8.38. <hi>and with all his Saints in heaven,</hi> 1 Theſ. 3.13. <hi>and thoſe that are alive at that day, ſhall he changed in the tw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nkling of an eye.</hi> 1 Cor. 15.51, 52. <hi>and caught up into the clouds, to meet the Lord in the ayre,</hi> 1 Theſ. 4.17. <hi>thoſe in heaven ſhall come with Chriſt, and thoſe on earth ſhall meet him, and they ſhall be ever with the Lord, the dead in Chriſt ſhall riſe firſt,</hi> 1 Theſ. 4.16.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What will Chriſt doe when he is come? A.</hi> When the Sonne of man ſhall come in his glory, and all the holy Angels with him, <hi>then ſhall he ſit upon the throne of his glory</hi> mat. 24.31. <hi>and all Nations ſhall be brought before him, and he ſhall ſeperate them, as a Shepheard doth his ſheep from the goats, and ſet the ſheep on his right hand, and the goats on his left,</hi> ver. 32.33.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>How ſhall men at that day be ſummoned before the Judge? A. He ſhall ſend his Angels with a great ſound of a Trumpet,</hi> mat. 24.31. <hi>and when the Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet ſhall ſound, the dead ſhall be raiſed,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.52. <hi>and the living chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged.</hi> 51.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>How will chriſt examine every mans cauſe? A.</hi> The books of every mans doings ſhall be laid open, and their conſciences ſhall be made to accuſe, or to excuſe them, and every man ſhall be tryed by the workes which he did in his life time, becauſe that workes are manifeſt ſignes either of faith or unbeliefe, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.10. <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.12. 2 <hi>cor.</hi> 5.10.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What followes their examination? A.</hi> Then he will give ſentence of abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution and ſalvation to the godly, ſaying to them, <hi>come ye bleſſed of my Father, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Kingdome prepared for you from the foundation of the world;</hi> and to the wicked he will ſay, <hi>depart from me ye curſed into everlasting fire, prepared for the devill and his angels,</hi> mat. 25.34.41.</p>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:111244:36"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>What is the estate of the godly after the day of judgement? A. The Saints ſhall them inherit all things.</hi> rev. 21.7. Dan. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.27. 2 Pet. 3.13, 14. Iſa. 56.22. <hi>and they ſhall enjoy the preſence of God, where are rivers of pleaſures for evermore,</hi> Pſal. 16.11. <hi>and they ſhall ſee chriſt face to face,</hi> 1 cor. 13.12. 1 Ioh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 3.2. <hi>and we ſhall re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gne with chriſt for ever,</hi> Revel. 5.10.21.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 7.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the ſtate of the wicked after the day of judgement? A.</hi> It is eternall perdition and deſtruction, which ſtands in three things eſpecially: Firſt, <hi>they ſhall be puniſhed with everlasting destruction, from the preſence of the Lord, and from the glory of his power,</hi> 2 theſ. 1.9. Secondly, <hi>their fellowſhip ſhall be the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill and his angels,</hi> mat. 25.41. thirdly, <hi>their torment ſhall be fire and brimſtone hurning eternally,</hi> Rev. 21.8. Iſa. 33.14. <hi>Who can dwell with everlaſting bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, where the Worme of a guilty conſcience dieth not, and the fire of Gods wrath is not quenched,</hi> mar. 9.44.46. <hi>fire and brimſtone, and a horrible tem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſt, this is the portion of their cup,</hi> Pſal. 11.6.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What is the end the Lord hath in all theſe things? A.</hi> His owne glory; what if God be willing to ſhew his wrath, and to make his power knowne on the veſſels of wrath fitted to deſtruction, and that he might make knowne the riches of his glory on the veſſels of mercy, which he had afore prepared unto glory, <hi>rom.</hi> 9.22, 23.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Watch ye therefore and pray alwayes that ye may be accounted worthy to eſcape all theſe things that ſhall come to paſſe, and to ſtand before the Sonne of man,</hi> Luke 21.36. Now the God of peace that brought againe from the dead our Lord Ieſus, that great Shepheard of the ſheep through the blood of the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Covenant, make you perfect in every good worke, to doe his will, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in you that which is well pleaſing in his ſight, through Ieſus Chriſt, to whom be glory for ever and ever, <hi>Amen, Heb.</hi> 13.20 21.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
